[MUSIC PLAYING]
[音乐播放]
[AUDIENCE EXCLAIMING]
[观众惊呼]
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
SPOT: Hello, world.
SPOT：你好，世界。
This is CS50, Harvard University's introduction
这是 CS50，哈佛大学的介绍
to the intellectual enterprises of computer science
到计算机科学的智力事业
and the art of programming.
以及编程的艺术。
Woof, woof.
汪汪。
[LAUGHTER]
[笑声]
I'm sorry, Dave.
对不起，戴夫。
[PINK, "WHAT ABOUT US"] What about us?
[粉红乐队，"我们呢" ] 我们呢？
What about us?
我们呢？
La-da-da-da-da-da-da.
啦哒哒哒哒哒哒哒。
We are searchlights.
我们是探照灯。
We can see in the dark.
我们能在黑暗中看到。
We are rockets pointed up at the stars.
我们是对着星星发射的火箭。
We are billions of beautiful hearts.
我们是数十亿颗美丽的心。
And you sold us down the river too far.
而你把我们卖得太远了。
What about us?
我们呢？
What about all the times you said you had the answers?
你那些说过你拥有答案的时候呢？
What about us?
我们呢？
What about all the broken happy ever-afters?
那些破灭的童话故事呢？
What about us?
我们呢？
What about all the plans that ended in disaster?
那些以灾难告终的计划呢？
What about love?
爱情呢？
What about trust?
信任呢？
What about us?
我们呢？
La-da-da-da-da-da-da.
啦哒哒哒哒哒哒哒。
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
大卫·马兰：好的。
So--
所以--
[APPLAUSE, CHEERING]
[掌声，欢呼]
This is CS50, Harvard University's introduction
这是 CS50，哈佛大学的介绍
to the intellectual enterprises of computer science
到计算机科学的智力事业
and the art of programming.
以及编程的艺术。
And this is Spot.
这是 Spot。
And our thanks to our friends at 3D Cowboys
感谢我们 3D 牛仔的朋友们
for bringing him by class today.
今天让他来上课。
Perhaps a round of applause for our special Professor [INAUDIBLE]..
也许我们应该为我们特殊的教授[听不清]鼓掌。
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
My name is David Malan.
我叫大卫·马兰。
And I actually took this class, CS50, myself, some years ago.
我几年前确实自己上过这门课，CS50。
But I almost didn't.
但我差点没上。
And I didn't because when I got to campus, as a first-year,
我之所以没有上，是因为当我作为大一新生来到校园时，
I really gravitated toward things already familiar, things
我真的很倾向于那些我已经熟悉的事物，那些
with which I was already comfortable, specifically, government.
我感到舒适的事物，特别是政治。
And I came in here thinking I was going to major or concentrate in government.
我来到这里时认为我将会主修或专注于政治。
And it was only once I got to sophomore year, fall semester,
直到我升入大二，秋季学期，
that some friends of mine were coming to this class called
我的一些朋友才开始上这门叫做
CS50 that was very much to beware at the time, in that it
CS50 的课，当时这门课令人望而生畏，因为它
was an unfamiliar field to so many of us, myself included.
对我们很多人来说都是一个陌生的领域，包括我自己。
But I got up the nerve to go over the threshold, sit in on the first class,
但我鼓起勇气走过门槛，坐在第一堂课上，
just shop it, so to speak.
算是试听一下吧。
And I was hooked.
我就迷上了。
I found that homework was, for the first time, fun.
我发现作业第一次变得有趣了。
And this was after having enrolled only because the professor let
而这仅仅是因为教授允许我
me enroll pass/fail or [INAUDIBLE] because I didn't really
我以 pass/fail 或者[听不清]的方式报名，因为我真的
think I could even cut it.
不认为自己能应付得了。
But fast forward to five Mondays later in the semester,
但快进到学期后的五个星期一，
I actually switched to a letter grade, deciding,
我实际上改成了字母成绩，决定，
wow, this is actually something for me.
哇，这实际上对我来说很合适。
And I say this because computer science, what
我说这话是因为计算机科学，我
I didn't realize about it at the time, really
当时并没有意识到它，实际上
is this very general purpose way of thinking and way of solving problems.
是一种非常通用的思维方式和解决问题的方式。
And even if this is the only CS class you ever take,
即使这是你唯一上过的 CS 课程，
even if this is the only formal training you have in programming
即使这是你唯一接受的编程方面的正规培训，
as a practical skill, it's just so darn applicable
作为一项实用技能，它真的非常适用
to so many other fields-- the arts, humanities, social sciences,
于很多其他领域——艺术、人文、社会科学，
natural sciences, and beyond, and certainly within the STEM fields,
自然科学，以及其他领域，当然也包括 STEM 领域，
themselves.
本身。
That said, it's going to often feel a little something like this.
也就是说，它经常会让你感觉有点像这样。
This is from our friends at MIT, down the road, which is one of their hacks
这是来自我们麻省理工学院的朋友，就在附近，这是他们其中一个黑客
whereby they connected a fire hydrant to a drinking fountain,
他们将一个消防栓连接到一个饮水机上，
with a little sign up there that says, "GETTING AN EDUCATION FROM MIT IS LIKE
上面有一个小牌子写着，“在麻省理工学院接受教育就像
DRINKING FROM A FIRE HOSE," which is to say that it's
从消防水带喝水”，也就是说，它
going to feel, quite often, in this class,
经常会在本课程中感受到，
too, that there's just a lot of information.
同样，这里有大量的资讯。
And you can't possibly absorb it all, but realize
你不可能全部吸收，但是你要明白
that's to be expected, especially in an introductory class.
这是可以预期的，特别是在入门课程中。
The whole point is for so much of it to feel new, but with practice, with time,
重点是让其中的很多内容对你来说都是新的，但随着练习，随着时间的推移，
with years, even, looking back, will you get all the more
甚至几年后，回顾往昔，你会越来越
comfortable with the material.
对这些内容感到熟悉。
But you're not meant to feel comfortable along the way.
但在学习过程中，你并不一定要感到舒适。
And so let me encourage you, invite you, expect
因此，我想鼓励你，邀请你，期待
you to get comfortable feeling uncomfortable along the way,
你在学习过程中能习惯感到不舒服，
whether you have or have not prior computer science or programming
无论你之前是否学习过计算机科学或编程
experience.
经验。
Now, back in my day, the class' syllabus was a little bit different.
在我那个时代，课程大纲有点不同。
And, really, when I and all of my classmates exited the class,
事实上，当我和其他同学从课堂上离开时，
we would say to friends that we learned how
我们会告诉朋友，我们学会了如何
to program in C, which is a language that we, ourselves, will still
用 C 语言编程，这是一种我们自己仍然会
learn in this class.
在本课程中学习的语言。
But that was it for languages.
但这只是关于语言的。
But nowadays, as you'll see, we'll explore not just
但现在，正如你将看到的那样，我们将探索的不只是
this older language called C, but a more modern language
这种叫做 C 的古老语言，而是一种更现代的语言
called Python that's very much in vogue for data science, and web applications,
叫做 Python，它在数据科学和 Web 应用程序中非常流行，
and much more.
等等。
But we'll also introduce you, along the way,
但我们也会在学习过程中向你介绍
to another language called S-Q-L or SQL, which is specifically for databases.
另一种叫做 S-Q-L 或 SQL 的语言，它专门用于数据库。
And SQL is a different type of programming language
而 SQL 是一种不同类型的编程语言
that's just going to give you different ways of solving problems,
它只是会为你提供解决问题的不同方法，
different building blocks with which to express problems you want to solve.
不同的构建块，用它们来表达你想要解决的问题。
We'll introduce you, toward the end of the semester,
我们会在学期结束时向你介绍
yet another language, JavaScript, often used
另一种语言，JavaScript，它经常与
with markup languages called HTML and CSS, with which maybe you
叫做 HTML 和 CSS 的标记语言一起使用，如果你之前做过网站，你可能
have some experience if you've made websites.
有一些经验。
But we'll do this because so many of today's actual real-world software
但我们会这样做，因为当今许多实际的现实世界软件
is web-based.
都是基于 Web 的。
Or it's phone-based, mobile-based, but even then,
或者它是基于手机的，基于移动设备的，但即使是这样，
it's using these same languages, like JavaScript.
它也使用这些相同的语言，比如 JavaScript。
And so by the end of CS50, in particular,
因此，到 CS50 结束时，特别是
you won't know how to program in X, or Y, or Z, per se.
你并不会知道如何用 X、Y 或 Z 等特定语言编程。
But, period, you'll learn how to program.
但是，你会学会编程。
And, indeed, among the goals of this class
事实上，这门课的目标之一
is to equip you with enough of a set of concepts, enough practical skills
就是让你掌握足够多的概念，足够多的实用技能
and experience that after CS50, again, if you never take another CS class,
和经验，这样你就可以在 CS50 结束后，再次学习，如果你再也不上任何计算机科学课程，
you can teach yourself new languages.
你可以自学新的语言。
And you won't feel--
你不会感到——
you won't have been reliant on a class to, indeed,
你不会依赖一门课程来，确实，
introduce you to each and one of those ideas.
向你介绍每一个想法。
And what are we going to do, then, in this class?
那么，我们在这门课上要做什么呢？
And, really, what are we going to start doing today?
而且，事实上，我们今天要开始做什么呢？
Well, we're going to learn how to solve problems.
好吧，我们将学习如何解决问题。
And that's really what computer science is all about.
而这正是计算机科学的本质。
We'll, very specifically, today, knock off a few to-dos.
我们今天将非常具体地完成一些待办事项。
We'll learn how to represent simple things, like numbers.
我们将学习如何表示简单的东西，比如数字。
We'll learn how to represent letters of an alphabet, like English.
我们将学习如何表示字母表中的字母，例如英文。
We'll learn how to represent colors-- red, green, blue,
我们将学习如何表示颜色——红色，绿色，蓝色，
and everything in between.
以及介于两者之间的所有颜色。
We'll learn how to represent, more interestingly,
更有趣的是，我们将学习如何表示
full-fledged images that you might see on the web or your phone.
你在网络或手机上看到的完整图像。
We'll talk about representing videos and even audio files.
我们将讨论如何表示视频，甚至音频文件。
So, by the end of today, alone, you will exit here
所以，仅今天结束时，你将离开这里
with a newfound mental model for how you can
带着一种全新的思维模式，了解如何
represent all of today's media and multimedia that we take for granted
表示我们习以为常的当今所有媒体和多媒体
and use most every day.
并且每天都在使用。
But we'll also focus today, ultimately, on how
但我们今天最终还会专注于如何
to write algorithms, like step-by-step instructions for solving
编写算法，就像解决问题的分步指令一样
some problem, specifically, implementing algorithms with code.
一些问题，具体来说，是用代码实现算法。
And that's what we'll find.
这就是我们要找到的。
An algorithm is just something you can express
算法只是你可以用英语或任何人类语言表达的东西，但代码是对它的翻译
in English or any human language, but code is a translation of that
但代码是对它的翻译
to, presumably, the 0's and 1's that you've probably heard
到，据推测，是 0 和 1，你可能已经听说过
is all that computers ultimately speak.
是计算机最终使用的语言。
And if you're feeling like that's a lot for today,
如果你觉得今天要学的东西很多，
if you're feeling like that's a lot for the whole semester,
如果你觉得整个学期要学的东西很多，
realize and take comfort in knowing that -thirds of you
请意识到并安心地知道，你们中三分之二的人
have never taken a CS course before.
以前从未上过 CS 课程。
So even if you think, like I did all those years ago,
所以，即使你像我几年前一样认为，
that, surely, my friends, the kids I didn't even in the class,
肯定的，我的朋友，那些甚至不在课堂上的孩子，
must know more than I, have been programming
一定比我懂得更多，并且一直在编程
since they were six years old.
从他们六岁起。
That's just not the case.
情况并非如此。
You're in very much good company.
你与很多优秀的人为伴。
And within the class will you find different tracks,
在课堂上，你会发现不同的学习路线，
by way of the homework assignments, called "problem sets,"
通过课后作业，称为“问题集”，
by way of the sections or recitations.
通过课节或课外辅导。
There will be different tracks for those of you
对于你们中的人，会有不同的学习路线，
less comfortable, more comfortable, somewhere in between.
那些不太舒服的，更舒服的，以及介于两者之间的。
And if you really don't know why you are here today,
如果你真的不知道今天来这里的原因，
we'll even have sections for those least comfortable, where you just
我们甚至会为那些最不适应的人设立课程，在那里你只需要
don't necessarily feel ready to dive into CS or maybe STEM, more generally.
不一定觉得自己准备好深入学习 CS 或更普遍的 STEM 领域。
But we'll get you there by way of the course's support structure.
但通过本课程的支持体系，我们会帮助你达到目标。
And it's very much grounded in this mindset.
这很大程度上基于这种思维方式。
What ultimately matters in this class is not so much
在本课程中，最终重要的是，并非你相对于你的同学身处何处，
where you end up relative to your classmates,
而是你相对于你自己而言，从哪里开始。
but where you end up relative to yourself, when you began.
所以，无论你之前是否有编程或 CSS 经验，
So whether you have or have not prior programming or CSS experience,
在评估时，在
it's not going to matter when it comes to evaluation, when
得到结果时，无论是一份成绩，还是一个合格的标记，或者类似的东西，
it comes to the output, be it a grade, or a satisfactory mark, or the like.
这将取决于，实际上，你今天身处何处，
It's going to depend on, really, where you are today,
在这个我们称为第零周的阶段，以及学期结束时，当你
in this, what we call week zero, versus the very end of the semester, when
用软件创造了你自己伟大作品的时候。
you will have built something grand, of your very own, in software.
但 CS50 也以其社区和文化为特征，这一点相当独特。
But CS50 is also characterized, fairly uniquely,
在学习过程中，你会发现你的学习体验
by its community, its culture.
充斥着许多社交和学术活动。
And along the way, you'll see that your experience
CS50 午餐，几乎每周五，我们都会在附近的一家名为 Changsho 的餐馆聚餐
is punctuated by a lot of social and academic events alike.
一起吃中国午餐。
CS50 lunches, most every Friday, we'll gather at a nearby restaurant
尽可能多的想要参加的人都可以加入我们，坐下来，与我随意聊天，
called Changsho where we'll have Chinese lunch together.
还有课程的教学人员、我们的朋友、来自业界的校友。
And as many of you as might want to attend
CS50 解谜日，本周末即将到来，这是一个机会，
that week will be able to join us, sit down, and chat casually with me,
让我们能够
the course's teaching staff, friends of ours, alumni from industry, as well.
一起玩游戏、一起学习、一起竞争。
CS50 Puzzle Day, coming up this weekend, will be an opportunity,
我们还有一些其他活动，比如
for us to, more formally, gather as a class and play some games, learn together, compete.
CS50 Hackathon，我们将举办黑客马拉松，
We have other events, too, like
持续 24 小时，
CS50 Hackathon, where we'll have a hackathon, a 24-hour period
旨在让你有机会尝试并构建
where you can try and build some software, some creative project, something that
一些软件，一些创意项目，一些能够
maybe pushes your boundaries.
挑战你的极限。
And if that's not enough,
如果你觉得这还不够，
there are even things called "club meetings"
还有叫做“俱乐部会议”的东西，
where we have clubs for just about any interest, coding related or not.
我们为几乎所有兴趣爱好设立了俱乐部，无论与编码相关与否。
There are clubs for games, for cooking, for filmmaking, for photography,
我们有游戏俱乐部、烹饪俱乐部、电影制作俱乐部、摄影俱乐部，
for just about anything you might imagine.
几乎所有你能想象到的。
So, as you can see,
所以，正如你所见，
CS50 is a lot more than just a class.
CS50 不仅仅是一门课程。
It's a community.
它是一个社区。
It's a family.
它是一个家庭。
And so,
所以，
I'm gonna give you a quick little orientation.
我将给你一个快速的小介绍。
To get started, you're gonna want to sign up for a course site.
首先，你需要注册一个课程网站。
So, it's a course website that is a hub,
这是一个课程网站，是一个中心，
where we'll post all the lecture notes, the problem sets, the forums, the like.
我们将在这里发布所有讲义、习题集、论坛等等。
So, to register, you're gonna want to go to CS50.harvard.edu,
所以，要注册，你需要访问 CS50.harvard.edu，
CS50.harvard.edu,
CS50.harvard.edu，
and you'll be able to sign up for the course with just an email address.
只需要一个电子邮件地址，你就可以注册这门课程。
Now, if you're already a Harvard student,
现在，如果你已经是哈佛大学的学生，
that's great.
那太好了。
You can sign up using your Harvard ID.
你可以使用你的哈佛 ID 注册。
Otherwise, just an email address will do.
否则，只需要一个电子邮件地址就可以了。
And then you're gonna want to download and install a program called "VS Code,"
然后你需要下载并安装一个名为“VS Code”的程序，
Visual Studio Code.
Visual Studio Code。
That's also a free program.
这也是一个免费程序。
It's the main program you'll be using to write code in this class.
它是你在这门课上用来编写代码的主要程序。
Now, I know some of you might be thinking,
我知道你们中的一些人可能在想，
"I've never programmed before.
“我以前从未编程过。
I've never touched a computer, never even seen one,
我从未触碰过电脑，从未见过它，
what am I gonna do?"
我要怎么办？”
Don't worry.
不用担心。
The course's designed for you too.
本课程也是为你而设计的。
You will come up to speed by the end of the semester.
你会在本学期结束之前达到预期水平。
So, let's get started.
所以，让我们开始吧。
I'm gonna turn off the lights
我要把灯关掉
so that we can all focus
这样我们才能集中注意力
and I'm gonna start with a demo.
我会从演示开始。
Here we go.
我们开始了。
Okay.
好的。
So,
所以，
it's just a way for us to introduce the course and our first lecture.
这只是一个介绍课程和我们第一堂课的方法。
So, what I want you to do is,
所以，我希望你做的是，
we're gonna start with a simple demo.
我们会从一个简单的演示开始。
So, I'm gonna run a little program called "Hello"
所以，我将运行一个小程序，名为“Hello”
and it's gonna ask you to enter your name.
它会要求你输入你的名字。
So, it's gonna say,
所以，它会说，
"What's your name?" And you just type your name and hit enter.
“你的名字是什么？”你只需要输入你的名字，然后按回车键。
And what it's gonna do is,
它将做的是，
it's gonna give you a little personalized output.
它将给你一个个性化的输出结果。
So,
所以，
"Hello, [Your Name], nice to meet you."
“你好，[你的名字]，很高兴认识你。”
All right.
好的。
So, let's try that.
所以，让我们试一下。
Here we go.
我们开始了。
So, it's gonna ask me for my name.
所以，它会询问我的名字。
It's gonna say,
它会说，
"What's your name?" And I type in "David," and hit enter.
“你的名字是什么？”我输入“David”，然后按回车键。
And it's gonna say,
它会说，
"Hello, David,"
“你好，David，”
"nice to meet you." And I can run it again,
“很高兴认识你。”我可以再次运行它，
and it'll ask me for my name again, and I'll type in "David," and it'll say,
它会再次询问我的名字，我将输入“David”，它会说，
"Hello, David, nice to meet you." And I can run it as many times as I want.
“你好，David，很高兴认识你。”我可以根据需要运行它任意多次。
And I can even do something like this.
我甚至可以这样做。
"What's your name?"
“你的名字是什么？”
And I can type in,
我输入，
let's say, "CS50." And it'll say, "Hello, CS50, nice to meet you."
比如，“CS50”。它会说，“你好，CS50，很高兴认识你。”
So,
所以，
this is just a simple, very, very simple demo.
这只是一个简单，非常非常简单的演示。
But even this
但即使是它
illustrates the basic idea of a program, which is that you can
也体现了程序的基本思想，那就是你可以
take some input from the user,
从用户那里获取一些输入，
process it in some way, and then give back some output.
以某种方式处理它，然后给出一些输出结果。
And that's what all programs do at their core.
这就是所有程序的核心功能。
So, in the case of this simple program,
所以，在这个简单的程序中，
we took your name as input,
我们将你的名字作为输入，
and then we processed it by putting it into a sentence,
然后我们通过将其放入一个句子中来处理它，
and then we gave you back that sentence as output.
然后我们将这个句子作为输出反馈给你。
So, this is just a taste of what we'll be doing in this class.
所以，这只是我们在这门课上会做的事情的一个小小的预兆。
We'll be writing programs that are much more complex
我们将编写更复杂的程序
and that do much more interesting things,
并且做一些更有趣的事情，
but the basic idea is the same.
但基本思想是一样的。
It's all about taking input,
这都是关于接收输入，
processing it,
处理它，
and giving back output.
并反馈输出结果。
And so,
所以，
we'll get to writing programs that,
我们将编写一些程序，
for example, can recognize your face,
例如，可以识别你的面部，
that can translate languages,
可以翻译语言，
that can even play games with you.
甚至可以和你玩游戏。
But to get there,
但要达到这个目标，
we have to start somewhere.
我们必须从某个地方开始。
And so,
所以，
we'll start with the basics,
我们将从基础开始，
with the fundamentals.
从基本原理开始。
And we'll build up to those more complex programs.
然后我们将逐渐构建那些
even if you have no prior CS experience, just to solve problems,
即使您没有任何计算机科学的先前经验，只要为了解决问题，
not jigsaw puzzles, but puzzles in the logical sense.
不是拼图，而是逻辑上的谜题。
We'll hand you a packet of puzzles--
我们会给你一包谜题——
logic problems, or riddles, or the like--
逻辑问题，或谜语，或类似的东西——
that you, as teams, can solve together.
你可以作为团队一起解决。
And at the very end, we'll walk you through.
最后，我们会带你走一遍。
And along the way, there'll be not only these puzzles, but pizza, and prizes,
一路上，不仅有这些谜题，还有披萨，还有奖品，
and so much more, as well.
还有更多的东西。
Towards the end of the semester, we'll have a CS50 Hackathon whereby
在学期结束的时候，我们将举行 CS50 黑客马拉松，
we'll get together around 7:00 PM, at the start of reading period,
我们将在大约下午7点，阅读期开始的时候聚在一起，
and we'll finish up around 7:00 AM the next morning.
我们将在第二天早上7点左右结束。
And it will be this opportunity to really bond
这将是一个真正地团结的机会
with your classmates, your project partners, if you work in a team,
与你的同学，你的项目合作伙伴，如果你在一个团队工作，
on your very own final project, which is meant
在你自己的最终项目上，这是为了
to be a capstone of the course, something you build, yourselves,
成为这门课程的顶峰，你自己建造的东西，
that we don't hand you a specification for.
我们没有给你一个规范。
But it's your final offboarding, so that when you exit CS50,
但这是你最后的离职培训，所以当你退出 CS50 时，
you don't need CS50 anymore.
你不再需要 CS50 了。
You don't need me.
你不需要我。
You don't need your TF.
你不需要你的助教。
You can actually write code and solve problems on your own.
你实际上可以自己编写代码和解决问题。
So this picture here is one of our past photos from earlier in the evening.
所以，这张照片是我们晚上早些时候的照片之一。
Things get a little quieter as we then, around 5:00 AM,
当我们在凌晨5点左右的时候，事情变得安静了一些，
drive anyone who's still awake and energetic to a nearby IHOP
把任何仍然清醒和精力充沛的人开车到附近的 IHOP
for pancakes, around then.
吃煎饼，大约那个时候。
But here is how most of the evenings tend to end for at least some
但这里是如何大多数的晚上往往结束至少一些
of your classmates prior.
你的同学以前。
But at the very end of the class is the so-called CS50 Fair,
但在课程的最后，是所谓的 CS50 博览会，
an exhibition of all of your final projects for friends, faculty,
你所有最终项目的展览，面向朋友，教职工，
students, and staff across campus, whereby
学生，以及校园里的工作人员，
you'll be invited to a space like this.
你将被邀请到这样的空间。
Bring your laptop.
带上你的笔记本电脑。
Bring your phone, whatever it is you have built and created.
带上你的手机，无论你建造和创造了什么。
And we'll just show it off for a bit of the afternoon,
然后我们只是在下午展示一下，
complete with music, and friends from industry,
加上音乐，以及来自行业的朋友，
and candy, and all what makes gathering together at term's end fond.
以及糖果，以及所有让学期结束的聚会变得美好的东西。
And you'll wear, ultimately, very proudly,
最后，你会非常自豪地穿上，
we hope, your very own "I took CS50," stating, very matter of factly,
我们希望，你自己的“我学过 CS50”，非常直白地说，
what I did some years ago; that, indeed, this was a course I, myself, took.
我几年前做过的事情；的确，这是我自己上过的一门课。
So, today, let's focus, then, on computer science, like what is it.
所以，今天，让我们把注意力集中在计算机科学上，比如它是什么。
Well, it's really the study of information.
嗯，这实际上是信息的研究。
But, really, it's, more specifically, about solving problems,
但是，实际上，更具体地说，是关于解决问题，
using certain ideas and techniques, all of which you'll exit the course with.
使用某些想法和技巧，你将在完成这门课后掌握所有这些。
So, as such, problem solving is a goal that we'll
因此，解决问题是我们会
approach by way of something called "computational thinking."
通过一种叫做“计算思维”的方式来解决。
So computational thinking, you can oversimplistically think about it
所以计算思维，你可以过分简单地把它想象成
as thinking like a computer.
像电脑一样思考。
But it's really the application of ideas that we'll dive into today
但实际上，这是我们将今天深入研究的想法的应用，
and we'll finish some weeks from now, that you
我们将在几周后结束，你
can apply to problems from this field or most any other, but in a computational,
可以应用于这个领域或大多数其他领域的问题，但以计算的方式，
that is, a very methodical, very careful way.
也就是说，一种非常有条理，非常谨慎的方式。
And that's what CS really did for me and does for a lot of people.
这就是 CS 真的为我做了，也为许多人做了的事情。
It helps clean up your thought processes.
它有助于理清你的思维过程。
Even if you go off into the real world and do nothing in tech,
即使你走进了现实世界，在科技领域什么也不做，
you have an ability, after classes like this,
经过像这样的课程之后，你具备了一种能力，
to express yourself a little more correctly, more
更准确地表达自己，更
precisely and, generally, having better command
精确地，总的来说，拥有更好的命令
of your own ideas and your language.
用你自己的想法和语言。
So what's problem solving?
那么，什么是解决问题呢？
Let me propose that this is it.
我想说，这就是它。
This is as simple as we can make today's goals and the semester's goals.
这就是我们今天和本学期目标的最简化形式。
Problems to be solved look like this.
待解决的问题是这样的。
You've got some input, the problem to be solved.
你需要一些输入，也就是要解决的问题。
You've got a goal being the output, like the solution there, too.
你有一个目标作为输出，比如那里的解决方案。
And then somewhere in the middle is the secret sauce,
然后在中间某个地方是秘诀，
where we'll spend the next several weeks figuring out how
我们将用接下来的几周时间弄清楚如何
we can convert these inputs to outputs.
将这些输入转换为输出。
But before we can do that, we all just have
但在我们开始之前，我们都需要
to agree on how to represent these inputs and outputs,
就如何表示这些输入和输出达成一致，
whether it's with English or, really, any type of language.
无论是用英语还是任何类型的语言。
But, as I spoiled earlier, you probably came in here already
但是，正如我之前所透露的，你可能已经带着
with a general sense that, yeah, computers somehow
一种普遍的认知走进了这里，没错，计算机以某种方式
only speak or know 0's and 1's, the so-called binary system.
只说或知道 0 和 1，也就是所谓的二进制系统。
But that's just one way of representing information.
但这只是表示信息的一种方式。
Even simpler than binary is unary.
比二进制更简单的就是一元。
So if you've ever, at this age or any prior age, counted on your fingers,
所以如果你曾经，在这个年龄或更早的年龄，用手指计数，
this is unary notation, whereby each of your digits, your fingers
这就是一元记数法，其中你的每个数字，你的手指
literally represent some piece of information;
字面意思上代表了一些信息；
taking attendance, like 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
点名，比如 1、2、3、4、5。
But on your one human hand, how high can you count in this unary notation?
但是，用你的一只手，你能用这种一元记数法数到多高呢？
AUDIENCE: Five.
观众：五。
DAVID J. MALAN: Five, I'm hearing five.
大卫·J·马兰：五，我听到的是五。
Six, I heard one six.
六，我听到一个六。
But I'm going to go further and say the answer, if you're clever about it,
但我要更进一步说，如果你足够聪明，答案实际上是——
is actually--
实际上——
AUDIENCE: 40?
观众：40？
DAVID J. MALAN: Not quite 40.
大卫·J·马兰：还没到 40。
You overbid, but--
你出价过高了，但是——
AUDIENCE: 31.
观众：31。
DAVID J. MALAN: 31 is as high as I can actually count.
大卫·J·马兰：31 是我能数到的最大数字。
And that's because if I actually-- and if you're thinking
这是因为如果我实际上—— 如果你在想
this is weirdly painful now, it will be, but this
现在这有点奇怪地让人痛苦，但它确实如此，但这是
is my hand representing the number 0.
我的手代表数字 0。
Normally, in unary, this is 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, of course, obviously.
通常，在一元记数法中，这是 1、2、3、4、5，当然，很明显。
But what if I take into account the order in which I'm
但如果我考虑一下我
putting my fingers up and down?
上下举起手指的顺序呢？
So maybe this is still 0.
所以也许这仍然是 0。
Maybe this is still 1.
也许这仍然是 1。
But maybe this is now 2, where it's just the single second finger up,
但也许现在是 2，只是第二根手指单独伸起来，
not two of them, total.
而不是两根手指都伸起来。
Maybe this is now 3.
也许现在是 3。
Maybe this is now-- often offensive, with just the middle finger up.
也许现在是—— 经常让人反感，只伸出中指。
This is now [LAUGHS] 5.
现在是 [笑声] 5。
This is now 6.
现在是 6。
This is now 7.
现在是 7。
And my hand just hurts too much if I try to count higher than seven.
如果我尝试数到七以上，我的手就太痛了。
But, theoretically, because each of my fingers can be down or up
但是，理论上，因为我的每根手指可以伸起来或放下去
and I've got five of them, that's actually 32 possible permutations,
而我有五根手指，所以实际上有 32 种可能的排列组合，
up and down.
上下伸起来。
But wait a minute.
等等。
We said, 31, but if you start at 0.
我们说的是 31，但如果你从 0 开始。
You have to subtract 1 from the biggest possible value.
你必须从最大的可能值中减去 1。
So this is to say you and I have been using unary because it's just simple,
所以，也就是说，你和我一直在使用一元记数法，因为它很简单，
and it gets the job done.
而且它可以完成工作。
But if we just think about representation a little more cleverly,
但如果我们更巧妙地思考一下表示方式，
we can do exactly what computers do, using not what mathematicians call
我们就可以做计算机做的事情了，使用的不像数学家所说的
"base-1," where the finger is either there or it's not, but base-2.
“一进制”，手指要么在那里，要么不在那里，而是二进制。
And in base-2, we just need two digits at our disposal.
在二进制中，我们只需要两个数字。
And we could call these digits 1 and 2, A and B, black or white.
我们可以把这些数字称为 1 和 2、A 和 B、黑或白。
We just need two words to describe two pieces of information.
我们只需要两个词来描述两条信息。
Computers keep it simple.
计算机保持简单。
And just like we humans start counting 0, 1, 2, 3 on up,
就像我们人类从 0, 1, 2, 3 开始计数一样，
computers use 0 and 1, and that's it.
计算机使用 0 和 1，仅此而已。
But that's by convention.
但这只是约定俗成。
But why do they do that?
但为什么他们这样做呢？
Well, it turns out, when you use base-2, otherwise known as binary, well,
事实证明，当你使用二进制（也称为二进制）时，
it just maps really readily to the real world.
它很容易映射到现实世界。
Because, at the end of the day, what do we all
因为，归根结底，我们所有人
do, if you've got a laptop, or a phone, or any device?
都做什么，如果你有笔记本电脑、手机或任何设备？
You plug it into the wall because it needs electricity at some point.
你把它插到墙上，因为它在某个时候需要电。
And what if you have electricity or not?
如果有或没有电会怎么样？
Well, there's your two possible values.
那么，这就是你的两个可能值。
Either it's there, or it's not.
要么它在那里，要么它不在那里。
And because computers are electrical devices,
而且因为计算机是电子设备，
this is why binary is just useful.
这就是二进制如此实用的原因。
It's nice and simple.
它简单明了。
Either electricity is there, or it's not.
要么有电，要么没有电。
So when you plug this device in and you've
所以当你把这个设备插上，并且你
got all these electrons or whatever flowing, maybe
有所有这些电子或任何流动的东西，也许
if we just hang on to some of that electricity,
如果我们只是保存一些电能，
we can represent what we'll call a 1.
我们可以用 1 来表示。
And maybe if we let it dissipate or go away, that's a 0.
也许如果我们让它消散或消失，那就是 0。
So on and off maps very readily to this idea of just 0's and 1's.
所以开和关很容易映射到这种只有 0 和 1 的想法。
And if you've ever thought of this, now, as binary digits--
如果你曾经想到过，现在，作为二进制数字 -
"bi" implying 2, 0 and 1-- well, if you've ever heard this term now,
“bi” 表示 2，0 和 1 - 如果你曾经听说过这个词，现在，
"bit," it just means binary digit.
“bit”，它仅仅意味着二进制数字。
A single bit is just a 0 or 1.
一个单独的位只是一个 0 或 1。
But we could have called these things anything we want.
但我们本来可以随便给这些东西命名。
Now how does this map to be clear to the real world?
现在这如何映射到现实世界中才能变得清晰？
Well, we can't see the tiny little switches inside of our Macs,
好吧，我们无法看到我们 Mac 内部那些微小的开关，
PCs, and our phones that are actually turning the electricity on
PC 和手机，它们实际上是打开电源
or off, storing electricity or not.
还是关闭，存储或不存储电能。
But they're called transistors.
但它们被称为晶体管。
They've got millions of them in today's hardware.
在今天的硬件中，它们有数百万个。
And they're just on or off, like a switch or a light bulb.
它们只是开或关，就像开关或灯泡一样。
So, for instance, if there's no electricity,
例如，如果没有电，
the switch is off, we would call this, by convention, a 0.
开关关闭，按照惯例，我们将其称为 0。
If, though, you throw the switch and it actually turns on, we would call this--
但是，如果你按下开关，它实际上打开了，我们会称之为 -
AUDIENCE: On.
观众：开。
DAVID J. MALAN: --an "on," exactly, a 1.
戴维·J·马兰：- 一个“开”，没错，一个 1。
We could have reversed it.
我们本可以颠倒过来。
But this is just the way the world decided to standardize.
但这仅仅是世界决定标准化的方式。
And that's it.
就是这样。
So you've either got something on or off, a 1 or a 0.
所以，要么打开，要么关闭，要么是 1，要么是 0。
And this, then, is this thing we know now as a binary digit or a bit.
然后，这就是我们现在所知的二进制数字或位。
So once we've got these values, what about how--
所以，一旦我们有了这些值，那么如何 -
how can we go about, perhaps, representing things?
我们如何才能做到，也许，表示事物？
Well, you know what?
好吧，你知道吗？
It turns out we've got a lot of light bulbs right here.
事实证明，我们这里有很多灯泡。
Let me grab-- thanks.
让我拿一下 - 谢谢。
Excuse me, spot.
打扰一下，这个地方。
Let me grab the little music stand here.
让我拿一下这里的小型乐谱架。
Let me borrow a couple of these bulbs and see
让我借几个这些灯泡，看看
if we can't make clearer than my hand, alone, what's going on here.
是否能比我的手更清楚地解释这里发生了什么。
So I'm going to go ahead and grab two of these.
所以我要去拿两个。
And I'll just put them here.
我把它放在这里。
And I can turn these things on or off now.
现在我可以打开或关闭这些东西。
So if I've got two bits, two switches, two transistors, if you will, well,
所以如果我有两个位，两个开关，两个晶体管，如果你愿意，那么，
if I go ahead and turn on this one, I'm representing what number in binary,
如果我继续打开这个，我用二进制表示的是什么数字，
perhaps?
也许？
AUDIENCE: 1.
观众：1。
DAVID J. MALAN: So just 1.
戴维·J·马兰：所以是 1。
Now, if I'm using unary, I would turn this one on and be done with it.
现在，如果我使用一元制，我会打开这个灯，就完成了。
And that's 2, but not in binary.
那就是2，但不是二进制。
Binary, it's the permutations, which ones are on and off, that matters.
二进制，重要的是排列组合，哪些灯是开着，哪些灯是关着。
So what, now, am I representing here, perhaps?
那么，我现在可能在这里表示什么呢？
AUDIENCE: 2.
观众：2。
DAVID J. MALAN: 2.
戴维·J·马兰：2。
So this is when I put my single pointer finger up.
所以这是我举起一根食指的时候。
But then when I did this, in my human hand,
但当我用我的手这样做的时候，
this was like representing the number 3.
这就像代表数字3。
How do I represent the number 4.
我怎样才能表示数字4呢？
Yeah, I need another light bulb, so I need more hardware, so to speak.
是的，我需要另一个灯泡，也就是说我需要更多的硬件。
So if I turn--
所以如果我打开--
if I leave this one-- if I turn this one on, this one off, this one off,
如果我保留这个-- 如果我打开这个，关闭这个，关闭这个，
now I have the number 4.
现在我得到了数字4。
And someone tell me, saying the words "on"
有人告诉我，说“开”
and "on" and "on," or "on," or "off," or "on,"
和“开”和“开”，或者“开”，或者“关”，或者“开”，
using combinations of "on," "off" and-- "on"
使用“开”，“关”和“开”的组合
and "off," how do I represent 5, from your left to your right?
和“关”，我如何从左到右表示5？
How about over here?
这边怎么样？
AUDIENCE: On, off, on.
观众：开，关，开。
DAVID J. MALAN: "On, off, on," I heard.
戴维·J·马兰：我听到了“开，关，开”。
And that's exactly right.
完全正确。
And how do I represent, maybe, 6?
我如何表示，也许是6？
Over here?
这边呢？
AUDIENCE: Off, on, on.
观众：关，开，开。
DAVID J. MALAN: Off, on, on, not quite.
戴维·J·马兰：关，开，开，不太对。
From left to right?
从左到右？
AUDIENCE: Off-- the other way.
观众：关-- 另一种方式。
DAVID J. MALAN: The--
戴维·J·马兰：那--
[LAUGHS] OK, so from right to left.
[笑] 好吧，从右到左。
So I think we leave this one on.
我认为我们应该保留这个灯开着。
This one, I'm going to claim, represents, now, 6 and 7.
我想说，这个现在代表了6和7。
AUDIENCE: On, off.
观众：开，关。
DAVID J. MALAN: I'm just going to-- it's actually going to be "on, on, on."
戴维·J·马兰：我只是-- 实际上应该是“开，开，开”。
Now, if you're wondering, where are these people coming up
现在，如果你想知道，这些组合是怎么来的
with these combinations, there's actually a system here.
这些组合其实是有规律的。
It's actually hard for me to do it backwards.
对我来说，反过来做其实很难。
But it turns out there's actually a system that's not all that unfamiliar.
但事实证明，其实有一个我们并不陌生的系统。
In fact, let me propose this.
事实上，让我提出这个建议。
Let me propose that we consider what you and I all
我想建议我们考虑一下你和我都
learned in grade school, which was something like the base-10 system, 10
在小学学过的东西，比如十进制系统，10
meaning that you use 10 different digits, not two, 10.
意思是使用10个不同的数字，不是两个，而是10个。
So 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, that's the base-10 system, otherwise known
所以0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9，那就是十进制系统，也叫
as decimal, "dec" implying 10.
十进制， “dec” 代表 10。
So that's what you and I use every day.
所以这就是我们每天使用的东西。
Well, let's think about how we represent numbers in decimal,
好吧，让我们思考一下我们如何在十进制中表示数字，
in the normal human way.
用正常的人类方式。
Well, here is a number.
好吧，这是一个数字。
It's what number, of course?
当然，它是什么数字？
AUDIENCE: 123.
观众：123。
DAVID J. MALAN: 123.
戴维·J·马兰：123。
So we all just have an intuition for that, obviously.
所以我们对此都有直觉，很明显。
But it's not necessarily 123.
但它不一定是123。
You're just assigning meaning to the positions of these digits.
你只是在给这些数字的位置赋予意义。
This is really the pattern 1-2-3.
这实际上是1-2-3的模式。
But you immediately jump, mathematically, to 123, but why?
但你在数学上立即跳到123，为什么呢？
Well, odds are, in grade school, you learned that the rightmost digit is
好吧，很有可能，你在小学的时候学到的是最右边的数字是
the ones place or the ones column.
个位数或个位数列。
This is the tens place or the tens column.
这是十位数或十位数列。
This is the hundreds place.
这是百位数。
And so why is this relevant?
那么，这有什么意义呢？
Well, this is like doing 100 times 1 plus 10 times
好吧，这就像做100乘以1再加上10乘以
2 plus 1 times 3 or, if we multiply that out, 100 plus 20 plus 3,
2再加上1乘以3，或者，如果我们把它们乘出来，就是100加20加3，
ergo, the number, now, that we just take for granted is 123.
因此，现在我们理所当然认为的数字是123。
But that's in base-10, the so-called decimal system,
但那是十进制，即所谓的十进制系统，
whereby each of these digits is in a different column.
其中每个数字都位于不同的列中。
And those columns are, again, ones place, tens, hundreds.
这些列又是各位、十位、百位。
If we keep going, thousand, ten thousand, and so forth.
如果我们继续下去，千位、万位等等。
But where did these come from?
但这些是从哪里来的？
Well, here's the base.
这是基数。
If you remember exponents and all of that,
如果你还记得指数等等，
this is just 10 to the 0, 10 to the 1, 10 to the 2, ad infinitum.
这仅仅是 10 的 0 次方、10 的 1 次方、10 的 2 次方，无限地。
And so, now, what if we just changed the base from 10, 0 through 9,
所以，现在，如果我们只是将基数从 10，即 0 到 9，
to just two digits, 0 and 1?
改为只有两个数字，0 和 1？
Well, now the math is fundamentally the same.
现在，数学本质上是一样的。
But it's 2 to the 0, 2 to the 1, 2 to the 2,
但它是 2 的 0 次方、2 的 1 次方、2 的 2 次方，
which gives us the ones place, twos place, and fours place.
这给了我们各位、二位和四位。
Now, why is this relevant?
现在，这为什么重要呢？
If you've got three light bulbs or three bits that are off, off, off,
如果你有三个灯泡或三个位是关的，关的，关的，
what have I done?
我做了什么？
4 times 0 plus 2 times 0 plus 1 times 0 is, obviously, the number
4 乘以 0 加 2 乘以 0 加 1 乘以 0，显然，这个数字
you and I know, in decimal, as 0.
你我用十进制表示为 0。
This, though, represents the number you and I know as--
不过，这代表了我们所知道的数字——
AUDIENCE: 1
观众：1
DAVID J. MALAN: This represents--
大卫·J·马兰：这代表——
AUDIENCE: 2.
观众：2。
DAVID J. MALAN: --3, 4.
大卫·J·马兰：——3，4。
And just to be clear, this is why, when I grabbed the additional light bulb,
说清楚点，这就是为什么当我拿起额外的灯泡时，
we claimed that this now was 4.
我们声称现在是 4。
Because we had "on, off, off," "on, off, off."
因为我们有“开，关，关”，“开，关，关”。
This now is 5.
现在是 5。
This now is 6.
现在是 6。
This now is 7.
现在是 7。
And if I wanted to count higher, what would the pattern of 0's and 1's be
如果我想数到更大的数字，0 和 1 的模式是什么
for the number 8?
对于数字 8？
AUDIENCE: 1, 0--
观众：1，0——
DAVID J. MALAN: 1, 0, 0, 0.
大卫·J·马兰：1，0，0，0。
So we just need more hardware, more bits.
所以我们只需要更多的硬件，更多的位。
So it wasn't arbitrary, even if it was non-obvious,
所以这并不随意，即使它并不明显，
what I was actually doing with turning these light bulbs on and off.
我实际上在做的是开灯泡和关灯泡。
Now, it turns out here we are talking about how to represent information,
现在，事实证明，我们在这里谈论如何表示信息，
like numbers, but we could also use bits, 0's and 1's, light bulbs
比如数字，但我们也可以用位，0 和 1，灯泡
to represent instructions, as well.
来表示指令。
Because, at the end of the day, that's all computers do.
因为，归根结底，计算机做的就是这些。
They process data, information of some sort, whether it's files,
它们处理数据，某种信息，无论是文件，
or numbers, or images, or videos, or the like.
还是数字，还是图像，还是视频，或者类似的东西。
And you do things with those files.
你用这些文件做一些事情。
You open them.
你打开它们。
You print them.
你打印它们。
You edit them and the like.
你编辑它们等等。
So there's this notion of instructions, what the computer can actually do.
所以，有一种指令的概念，即计算机实际上可以做什么。
And I bet we could come up with some pattern of 0's and 1's
我敢打赌，我们可以想出一个 0 和 1 的模式
or, equivalently, light bulbs that tell even Spot what to do.
或者，等效地，灯泡，甚至告诉 Spot 该做什么。
Maybe, go up, or down, or left, or right.
也许，向上，向下，向左，向右。
And it could certainly do this autonomously by using various sensors.
它当然可以通过使用各种传感器自动完成这些操作。
We need to keep things safe today.
今天我们需要确保安全。
We're using Wi-Fi in sending Spot these very instructions.
我们使用 Wi-Fi 向 Spot 发送这些指令。
But what's happening, wirelessly, with our friend Andrew, here, is,
但无线发生的事情是，我们朋友安德鲁在这里，
essentially, he's sending Spot instructions just encoded, wirelessly,
本质上，他正在无线地向 Spot 发送指令，只是编码了，
somehow, as patterns of 0's and 1's.
以某种方式，作为 0 和 1 的模式。
And the folks at Boston Dynamics, who built this robot, programmed
而波士顿动力公司的员工，他们制造了这个机器人，编程了
Spot to recognize certain patterns as meaning "up,"
Spot 来识别某些模式，表示“向上”，
a certain pattern as meaning "down," "left," "right,"
某个模式表示“向下”，“向左”，“向右”，
and any number of other things.
以及任何其他数量的事情。
So, in fact, Spot, come on over here, if you could.
所以，实际上，Spot，如果你能过来的话。
Come on, Spot.
来吧，Spot。
[FOOTSTEPS]
[脚步声]
OK.
好的。
So Spot, for instance, may very well have a pattern
所以 Spot，例如，可能很可能有一个模式
of 0's and 1's that represents shake.
0和1的组合代表摇动。
Shake, Spot.
摇动，斑点。
So he could do that and any number of other movements, as well.
因此，它可以执行此动作，以及其他任何动作。
And maybe, especially with sensors here and also a little human help over here,
也许，特别是在这里有传感器，以及这边的一点人工帮助，
for today, what if we went ahead and did something-- maybe
今天，如果我们继续做些事情，也许
ask Spot some questions?
问问斑点一些问题？
So let's go ahead, and we'll start simple.
让我们继续，从简单的开始。
Spot, here we have some bits, "off, off, on."
斑点，这里我们有一些比特，“关，关，开”。
Spot, what [LAUGHS]-- OK.
斑点，这[笑]—— 好。
Spot, what is this representing, "off, off, on"?
斑点，这代表什么，“关，关，开”？
[SPOT TAPS STAGE]
[斑点敲击舞台]
Correct?
正确吗？
I think so.
我想是的。
Very horse-like, OK.
非常像马，好的。
Thank you.
谢谢。
All right, so a round of applause for Spot here.
好了，所以来为斑点鼓掌。
[APPLAUSE]
[鼓掌]
All right.
好的。
So, Spot, what if we [LAUGHS] turn--
所以，斑点，如果我们[笑]转——
OK.
好的。
We'll turn that one off here.
我们将把那个关掉。
How about if we turn this one on?
如果我们把这个打开呢？
So it's "off, on, off."
所以是“关，开，关”。
Spot, what's this number?
斑点，这个数字是什么？
[SPOT TAPPING STAGE]
[斑点敲击舞台]
Is that correct?
正确吗？
Nice.
不错。
OK.
好的。
[APPLAUSE]
[鼓掌]
[LAUGHS] How about one final flourish?
[笑] 最后一个花招怎么样？
How about, Spot, instead of "off, on, off,"
斑点，除了“关，开，关”，
let's go ahead and do "off, on, on"?
我们继续做“关，开，开”？
So think, in your mind's eye, what the answer should be.
所以，在你脑海里思考一下答案应该是多少。
All right, Spot, "off, on, on."
好的，斑点，“关，开，开”。
[SPOT LANDING ON THE STAGE]
[斑点落到舞台上]
OK.
好的。
And a round of applause for, Spot, as well.
为斑点也鼓掌。
[LAUGHS]
[笑]
[APPLAUSE]
[鼓掌]
So this is to say, no matter how--
所以，这就是说，无论今天多么——
thank you, Spot.
谢谢，斑点。
No matter how fancy today's hardware or software is,
无论今天的硬件或软件多么花哨，
it really just boils down to representing
它实际上只是归结为表示
information and instructions.
信息和指令。
And computers, and phones, and the like really are just
而电脑、手机等实际上只是
operating on those same pieces of information,
操作这些相同的信息，
whether implemented in 0's and 1's or with, really, anything else.
无论是用 0 和 1 实现，还是用其他任何东西。
All right.
好的。
So, where can we take this, once we have this agreed-upon system
所以，有了这种约定俗成的系统，我们能把它带到哪里？
for representing [LAUGHS] information?
用来表示[笑]信息？
Well, it turns out that using three bits, three 0's and 1's, at a time,
结果发现，一次使用三个比特，三个 0 和 1，
isn't actually all that useful.
实际上并没有那么有用。
And you and I, even in conversation, don't often say the word "bit."
你我，即使在交谈中，也不经常说“比特”这个词。
We say the word "byte."
我们说“字节”这个词。
And what is a byte, if familiar?
如果熟悉，什么是字节？
Yeah?
是吧？
AUDIENCE: It's eight bits.
观众：是八个比特。
DAVID J. MALAN: So it's just eight bits.
DAVID J. MALAN：所以它只是八个比特。
It's just a more useful unit of measure.
它只是个更实用的单位。
And it happens to be a power of 2, 2 to the third,
它恰好是 2 的幂，2 的三次方，
which just makes math work out cleanly.
这使得数学运算更简洁。
But it's just a convention, to have more interesting units of measure
但这只是一个约定，为了拥有比单个比特更有趣的计量单位
than individual bits.
而不是单个比特。
So a byte is eight bits.
所以一个字节是八个比特。
So, for instance, this represents, using eight bits, eight light bulbs,
例如，这个用八个比特，八个灯泡，
the number you and I know is 0.
代表你我所知的数字 0。
And this byte of all 1 bits--
而这个全是 1 的字节——
now you've got to do some quick math-- represents what number, instead?
现在你需要进行一些简单的计算——它代表什么数字？
So it's all 1's; eight of them, total.
所以都是 1；总共八个。
How about over here, on the end?
这边怎么样，在最后？
AUDIENCE: 255.
观众：255。
DAVID J. MALAN: So it's, indeed, 255.
DAVID J. MALAN：所以确实是 255。
Now, that's not the kind of math that you
现在，这不是你所知道的数学，
need to do in your head for a class like this, but you could.
你需要在脑子里计算，不过你可以做到的。
This is the ones place, twos, fours, eight, 16, 32, 64, 128.
这是个位数、两位数、四位数、八位数、十六位数、三十二位数、六十四位数、一百二十八位数。
And because they're all 1, you just have to add up all of those columns' values.
因为它们都是 1，你只需要把所有这些列的值加起来。
And you get 255.
然后你就得到 255。
But a little mental trick, too, is that, if you've got eight bits
不过还有一个小的技巧是，如果你有八位
and each of them can be two possible values, 0 or 1,
并且每个位可以是两种可能的取值，0 或 1，
that's like 2 possibilities here times 2 times 2 times 2 times 2, eight times.
就好像这里有 2 种可能性乘以 2 乘以 2 乘以 2 乘以 2，八次。
So that's 2 to the eighth, so that is maybe a little easier to do.
所以就是 2 的 8 次方，这样可能更容易计算。
That's 256.
那就是 256。
Or easier, in the sense that you get used to seeing these numbers in CS.
或者说更简单，因为在计算机科学中你会习惯看到这些数字。
That's 256.
那就是 256。
But wait a minute.
等等。
How do I reconcile this with your 255?
我怎么把这和你说的 255 联系起来？
Because you start at 0.
因为你是从 0 开始的。
So you lose one on the high end because we started counting and representing
所以你在高位失去一个，因为我们从 0 开始计数和表示
the number, like 0.
数字，比如 0。
All right.
好的。
Questions on how we've represented just numbers or, for instance,
对于我们如何表示数字，或者例如，
instructions to Spot, thus far?
迄今为止对 Spot 的指令，有什么问题吗？
Any questions on binary, unary, or the like?
关于二进制、一元或类似的东西，还有什么问题吗？
No?
没有？
All right, so seeing none, let's let things escalate a bit.
好的，既然没有问题，让我们稍微提升一下难度。
So how do you represent letters because, obviously, this
那么如何表示字母，因为很明显，这个
makes our devices more useful, whether it's
让我们的设备更加有用，无论是
in English or any other human language.
英语还是其他任何人类语言。
How could we go about representing the letter A, for instance?
例如，我们如何表示字母 A？
If, at the end of the day, all our computers,
如果说到底，我们所有的计算机，
all our phones have access to is electricity; or, equivalently,
我们所有的手机所能使用的只有电力；或者说等价地，
switches; or, metaphorically, tiny little light bulbs
开关；或者说，比喻来说，里面的小灯泡
inside of them that can be on and off-- that's it.
可以开和关，就这些。
There's no more building blocks to give you.
没有其他构建模块了。
How could we represent something like the letter A?
我们该如何表示字母 A？
Yeah, how about here?
是的，这里呢？
Yeah?
是吧？
AUDIENCE: You could assign a number.
观众：你可以分配一个数字。
DAVID J. MALAN: Perfect.
大卫·J·马兰：完美。
So we could just assign every letter a number.
所以我们可以给每个字母分配一个数字。
And we could do this super simply.
我们也可以非常简单地做到。
Maybe 0 is A, and 1 is B. Or maybe 1 is A,
也许 0 是 A，1 是 B。或者也许 1 是 A，
and 2 is B. It doesn't really matter, so long as we all agree and we all
2 是 B。这并不重要，只要我们都同意，我们都
use the same types of computers, in some sense, ultimately.
使用相同类型的计算机，从某种意义上来说，最终。
Well, for various reasons, the humans that designed this system,
嗯，由于种种原因，设计这个系统的人，
they went with the number 65.
他们选择了数字 65。
So, nowadays, anytime your computer is showing you the capital letter
所以，现在，每当你的计算机显示给你大写字母
A on the screen, underneath the hood, so to speak,
A 在屏幕上，在引擎盖下面，可以这么说，
it's actually storing a pattern of 0's and 1's that represents the number 65.
它实际上存储着一组 0 和 1 的模式，代表数字 65。
And it tends to use seven bits or, typically, eight bits, total,
它倾向于使用七位，或者通常是八位，总共，
even if it doesn't need all of those bits in total.
即使它不需要所有这些位。
So how do we get there?
那么我们如何得到它？
Well, here, for instance, is that same pattern.
嗯，这里，例如，是相同的模式。
Here is that pattern of bits that represents 65.
这里就是代表数字 65 的位模式。
And why?
为什么？
Well, quick check here.
嗯，这里快速检查一下。
This is the ones place, twos, fours, eights, 16, 32, 64's place.
这是个位数、两位数、四位数、八位数、十六位数、三十二位数、六十四位数。
OK, so 64 plus 1 gives me 65.
好的，所以 64 加 1 等于 65。
So that is to say here's how a computer, using some light switches, so to speak,
也就是说，计算机使用一些开关，可以这么说，
would represent the number 65.
会表示数字 65。
And our Macs, our PCs, our phones just all know this.
我们的 Mac、PC、手机都知道这一点。
So whenever they see that in their memory, so to speak,
所以，每当它们在内存中看到它，可以这么说，
they show a capital letter A on the screen.
它们就在屏幕上显示一个大写字母 A。
So that's it.
就是这样。
That's the system known as ASCII, the American Standard
这就是我们所说的 ASCII，美国标准
Code for Information Interchange.
信息交换码。
And the A is actually operative there because we're only talking, thus far,
而 A 实际上起作用，因为到目前为止，我们只谈论
about English letters in our alphabet.
我们字母表中的英文字母。
And, in fact, I claimed, a moment ago, that we only use
事实上，我刚才声称，我们只使用
seven, maybe eight bits to represent letters of an alphabet.
七位，或者八位来表示字母。
So, just to come back to you, if I may, how many
所以，如果可以，我再问你一次，我们能用
possible letters of the alphabet could-- how
多少个字母来表示？
many possible letters of any alphabet could we represent with eight bits?
用八位来表示任何字母表中的字母，我们能表示多少个字母？
AUDIENCE: 256.
观众：256。
DAVID J. MALAN: 256, the numbers 0 through 255.
大卫·马兰：256，从 0 到 255。
Now, that's more than enough for English because we've
现在，这对于英语来说已经足够多了，因为我们有
got A through Z, uppercase, lowercase, a bunch of numbers,
从 A 到 Z，大写，小写，还有很多数字，
a bunch of punctuation symbols.
还有很多标点符号。
But in a lot of languages, with accented characters, a lot of Asian characters,
但在很多语言中，带重音的字符，还有很多亚洲字符，
this is not nearly enough memory or bits with which
这远远不够表示这些值。
to represent all of those possible values.
所以我们需要比 ASCII 更高级，
So we need to do a little better than ASCII,
但我们可以建立在他们几十年前的基础之上。
but we can build on top of what they did years ago.
这是一个 ASCII 码表。
So here is a chart of ASCII codes.
它只是一堆表格，显示了字母和数字之间的映射。
It's just a bunch of columns showing us the mapping between letters
例如，这里是大写字母 A，65；大写字母 B，66；
and numbers.
大写字母 C，67；以此类推。
So, for instance, up here is the capital letter A, 65; capital B, 66;
72 是 H，73 是 I，等等。
capital C, 67; dot, dot, dot.
这里有一些奇怪的东西，比如特殊符号，
72 is H. 73 is I and so forth.
我们以后会学到。
There's some weird things over here, like special symbols,
但每一个英文字母都对应一个数字，就像你提议的那样，
that we'll learn about over time.
包括大写和小写。
But there's a mapping between every English letter
例如，如果我们现在只突出显示其中的几个
of the alphabet and some number, just as you'd propose,
我说我刚收到一条短信或一封电子邮件，
both for uppercase and lowercase.
从底层来说，如果我有能力
So, for instance, if we highlight just a few of these for now
查看哪些开关是开着的，哪些开关是关着的，我收到了这条消息。
and I say that I've just received a text message or an email that,
首先，这不是 CS 的内容，但它很有趣。
underneath the hood, so to speak, if I have the ability
有人知道，如果这是二进制模式，比如个位、两位、四位，这代表什么十进制数吗？
to look at what switches are on and off, I received this message here.
观众：72？
Well, first-- and this is not what CS is about, but just fun fact.
大卫·马兰：72 是正确的。
Does anyone know what number this would represent in decimal,
再说一次，从智力上讲，这不是很有趣，
if this is the binary pattern, like ones place, twos place?
这不是我们作为计算机科学家整天做的事情。
AUDIENCE: 72?
但它遵循了相同的模式，
DAVID J. MALAN: 72 is correct.
它看起来很神秘，但从概念上讲，
And again, not, intellectually, all that interesting
从智力上讲，它最终与我们之前做的一样。
and this is not the kind of math that we spend all day as CS--
所以，我剧透一下接下来的计算。
a computer scientist doing.
它是 72，73，33。
But it's just following the same darn pattern, which
现在，有人还记得我们刚刚拼出的信息吗？
is to say it might look cryptic, but, conceptually,
观众：Hi。
intellectually, it ultimately is exactly as we did before.
So, yes, I'll spoil the rest of the math.
大卫·马兰：是的，事实上，它是“Hi！”
It's 72, 73, 33.
不过，没有人真的很兴奋地说出来。
Now, anyone remember, in your mind's eye, what message we just spelled?
你们注意到 33 是什么了吗？
AUDIENCE: Hi.
观众：感叹号。
大卫·马兰：好的，很多人都注意到了。
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, so it is, in fact, "Hi!"
是的，它是一个感叹号。
Though, no one really said that excitedly.
确实，它在这里很明显。
What's the 33, if you noticed?
33 是感叹号。
AUDIENCE: Exclamation point.
这只是你最终可能会理解的事情。
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, so a lot of people noticed.
但通常情况下，如果你记得大写字母 A 是 65，
Yes, it's an exclamation point.
你至少可以算出这 25 个问题的答案，
And that's, indeed, noticeable right here.
因为它们都是连续的。
33 is the exclamation point.
And that's just something, eventually, that might sink in.
But, for the most part, if you remember capital A is 65,
you can figure out at least 25 other answers to these kinds of questions
because they're all contiguous like that.
So there's the exclamation point.
所以就有感叹号了。
But at the end of the day, we might just have this mapping known as ASCII.
但最终，我们可能只拥有这种被称为ASCII的映射。
And it's how our phones, and computers, and devices, more
而且这就是我们的手机、电脑和设备，更多的
generally, actually store information.
通常来说，实际存储信息的方式。
So we thought we'd make--
所以我们想做…
maybe take a little pressure off of me here.
也许可以减轻一下我的压力。
And could we maybe flip things around?
我们是否可以换个思路？
How about we try applying this newfound knowledge--
我们试试应用一下这个新发现的知识…
if it's, indeed, new to you-- with seven volunteers, seven bits, if we could?
如果你真的以前没见过的话，我们用七个志愿者，七个位，行吗？
OK.
好的。
I saw your hand first.
我看到你最先举手了。
Come on down.
请过来。
Maybe your hand, there.
也许你，过来。
OK, three, come on down over here.
好，三号，请到这边来。
How about four and five?
四号和五号呢？
Yep, come on down.
好的，请过来。
Yep, in the black shirt, yep.
好的，穿黑色衬衫的，是的。
How about let me go farther back?
要不我往后退一点？
How about in the green, over there?
穿绿色的，那个，可以吗？
And how about you, seven, over here?
还有七号，你到这边来。
All right.
好的。
Come on down.
请过来。
[CHATTER]
[聊天声]
Come on down.
请过来。
So a round of applause for our brave volunteers.
让我们为我们勇敢的志愿者鼓掌。
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
All right.
好的。
So if you'd like to stand, roughly, side by side, here in the middle
所以如果你愿意，就站在这里，大致并排站着，在舞台中央
of the stage.
的中间。
First of all, thank you.
首先，谢谢你们。
Let's see.
让我们看看。
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, perfect.
1、2、3、4、5、6、7，完美。
OK.
好的。
And let's go all the way over to this place, here.
然后我们走到这里。
If you would like to introduce yourself to the class.
如果你愿意的话，自我介绍一下。
RACHEL RICHEY: I'm Rachel Richey.
瑞秋·瑞奇：我是瑞秋·瑞奇。
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
大卫·J·马兰：好的。
And what year?
你是哪一届的？
Anything about you?
关于你的任何信息吗？
RACHEL RICHEY: Oh, first year, concentrating in CS.
瑞秋·瑞奇：哦，大一，主修计算机科学。
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
大卫·J·马兰：好的。
Welcome to the stage.
欢迎来到舞台。
Next.
下一个。
SPEAKER: Hi.
演讲者：你好。
I'm [? Kang. ?] Also a first-year concentrating in CS.
我是[？康？]，也是大一，主修计算机科学。
SPEAKER: Hello.
演讲者：你好。
My name is [? Lam. ?] I'm a [INAUDIBLE] student from education department.
我叫[？蓝？]，我是教育学院的一名[听不清]学生。
DAVID J. MALAN: Nice.
大卫·J·马兰：不错。
OK.
好的。
Next.
下一个。
JORDAN MITTLER: Hi.
乔丹·米特勒：你好。
I'm Jordan Mittler, concentrating in economics and maybe some CS.
我是乔丹·米特勒，主修经济学，可能还会学一点计算机科学。
SPEAKER: So, hi.
演讲者：所以，你好。
I'm [? Natalia. ?] First year, and I want to do CS.
我是[？娜塔莉亚？]，大一，我想学计算机科学。
SPEAKER: Hi.
演讲者：你好。
I'm [? Khadija. ?] I'm a first-year, and I want to do CS.
我是[？卡蒂娅？]，大一，我想学计算机科学。
DAVID J. MALAN: [LAUGHS].
大卫·J·马兰：[笑]。
SPEAKER: Hello.
演讲者：你好。
I'm [? Caleb. ?] And, once again, first year, concentrating in CS.
我是[？凯勒布？]，再说一次，大一，主修计算机科学。
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
大卫·J·马兰：好的。
Wonderful.
太棒了。
A pattern, yes.
一个模式，没错。
Thank you.
谢谢。
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
So, if you haven't guessed already, each of these volunteers
所以，如果你还没有猜到的话，这些志愿者中的每一位
is going to represent a bit, from left to right, or right to left,
将代表一个位，从左到右，或者从右到左，
in this case.
在本例中。
So let's see.
所以让我们看看。
If you want to represent-- how about the twos place?
如果你想代表… 二位的？
How about the fours place, the eighths place, 16ths place, 32's, 64, and 128?
四位的呢？八位的呢？十六位的呢？三十二位的呢？六十四位的呢？还有128位的呢？
Although, wait a-- I think I screwed up.
不过，等等… 我想我弄错了。
We needed one-- eighth volunteer.
我们需要一位… 第八个志愿者。
I think you know-- well, I think--
我想你可能知道… 我想…
[CLEARS THROAT] Spot?
[清清嗓子] 哪个位置？
OK.
好的。
Come on over.
请过来。
If you guys could step forward a little bit, and then scooch this way,
如果大家能向前走一点，然后往这边挪一挪，
just to give Spot some room.
给 Spot 留点空间。
[FOOTSTEPS]
So Spot will represent the ones place.
所以 Spot 将代表个位数。
Now, what our volunteers have on the back of their sheets of paper
现在，我们的志愿者在他们纸张的背面
are little instructions.
有一些小指示。
We're going to spell out a three-letter word in English by using three bytes,
我们将使用三个字节拼出一个英文的三个字母的单词，
from left to right, because now we have eight volunteers.
从左到右，因为我们现在有八个志愿者。
I'm going to propose that you raise your hand, if you're
我建议，如果你
supposed to represent a 1.
应该代表 1。
Or you just stand there, without raising your hand,
或者你只是站在那里，不举手，
if you're meant to represent a 0.
如果你要代表 0。
And what we'll have the audience do is do the quick math
我们将让观众做快速计算
to figure out-- one, two, three-- each letter, what number is it.
来算出——一、二、三——每个字母，它是什么数字。
What letter is it?
它是什么字母？
And we'll see what word that we have finally spelled.
我们将看到我们最终拼出的单词是什么。
All right.
好的。
So, in round one--
所以，在第一轮——
you have instructions on your back of your sheet that will tell you to--
在你的纸张的背面有指示告诉你——
what your number is.
你的数字是什么。
If you're 0, stand there.
如果你代表 0，就站在那里。
If you're a 1, raise your hand.
如果你代表 1，就举手。
[PAPER RUSTLING]
What number do these guys seem to be representing?
这些家伙似乎代表了什么数字？
AUDIENCE: 68.
观众：68。
DAVID J. MALAN: 66, I think.
大卫·J·马兰：我认为是 66。
64 plus 2, so 66, which is the letter--
64 加 2，所以是 66，它是字母——
AUDIENCE: B.
观众：B。
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, so, B. OK, so, B. All right.
大卫·J·马兰：好的，所以是 B。好的，所以是 B。好的。
Hands down.
放下手。
Second letter is going to be spelled how?
第二个字母将如何拼写？
[SPOT LANDS ON THE STAGE]
AUDIENCE: Whoa.
观众：哇。
DAVID J. MALAN: [LAUGHS] All right.
大卫·J·马兰：[笑] 好的。
What are we spelling now?
我们现在拼什么？
[INDISTINCT CHATTER]
I think-- psst, yep, OK.
我认为——嘘，是的，好的。
Yeah, I think you're one.
是的，我认为你代表 1。
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
好的。
Now what number are we spelling?
现在我们拼的是什么数字？
AUDIENCE: 79
观众：79
DAVID J. MALAN: 79, I heard, which is the letter?
大卫·J·马兰：我听到是 79，它是哪个字母？
AUDIENCE: O.
观众：O。
DAVID J. MALAN: O. OK.
大卫·J·马兰：O。好的。
So hands down.
所以放下手。
Thank you, Spot.
谢谢，Spot。
One final flourish.
最后再来个华丽的结束。
So we've spelled B-O--
所以我们已经拼出了 B-O——
third letter, go ahead.
第三个字母，继续。
[SPOT LANDS ON THE STAGE]
What number, now, is this?
现在，这个数字是多少？
AUDIENCE: 87.
观众：87。
DAVID J. MALAN: I heard it here, 80--
大卫·J·马兰：我听到的是 80——
AUDIENCE: Seven.
观众：七。
DAVID J. MALAN: --seven, which is?
大卫·J·马兰：——七，它是哪个？
AUDIENCE: W.
观众：W。
DAVID J. MALAN: W, which, of course, spells "bow."
大卫·J·马兰：W，当然，拼出来就是 "bow"。
So if our volunteers could take a bow, Spot included.
所以如果我们的志愿者能鞠躬，包括 Spot。
[APPLAUSE]
So this will make more sense in week one,
所以这将在第一周更有意义，
when we have an assignment involving a certain someone from the Nintendo
当我们有一项作业涉及到任天堂世界中的某个人时，
World.
世界。
But we have a lovely parting gift for each of you.
但我们给你们每个人准备了一份可爱的临别礼物。
SPEAKER: Thank you.
说话者：谢谢。
[LAUGHS]
DAVID J. MALAN: Thank you for volunteering.
大卫·J·马兰：谢谢你的参与。
SPEAKER: Thanks.
说话者：谢谢。
DAVID J. MALAN: You might need to share it with the folks next to you.
大卫·J·马兰：你可能需要和旁边的人分享一下。
[CHATTER]
Oop, here we go.
哎哟，开始了。
There we go.
开始了。
Thank you--
谢谢——
SPEAKER: Thank you.
说话者：谢谢。
RACHEL RICHEY: Thank you.
瑞秋·里奇：谢谢。
DAVID J. MALAN: --so much.
大卫·马兰：——非常感谢。
One more round of applause, if we could, for our volunteers.
如果可以的话，让我们再为我们的志愿者鼓掌一次。
Thank you.
谢谢。
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
Did you lose something?
你丢东西了吗？
OK.
好的。
All right.
好吧。
So, [LAUGHS] Spot's had it.
所以，[笑声]斯波特已经受不了了。
So let's see, then, if we've solved, now,
那么，让我们看看，现在我们是否已经解决了，
the problem of representing English letters of the alphabet,
表示英语字母的问题，
being able to spell out words like "bow," B-O-W. What if we actually do
能够拼出像“bow”这样的单词，B-O-W。如果我们实际上有
have accented characters?
带重音的字符？
What if we do have other glyphs that we want to represent?
如果我们确实有一些我们想表示的其他字形呢？
Well, here, of course, is a standard US English keyboard, which a lot of you
当然，这里有一个标准的美国英语键盘，你们很多人
might have.
可能会有。
But there's also characters that you can type much more
但也有你更容易输入的字符，
easily if you have a foreign keyboard, relative to the US,
如果你有一个外国键盘，相对于美国来说，
or with certain keystrokes on your own Mac, PC, and phone.
或者用你自己的Mac、PC和手机上的某些按键组合。
But, nowadays, too, there's this menu that, probably, you've
但现在，还有这个菜单，你可能
used in the past hour or two to actually send some emoji.
在过去一两个小时里用过它来发送一些表情符号。
An emoji, even though they look like pictures
表情符号，虽然它们看起来像图片，
and they actually are pictures on the screen,
而且它们实际上是屏幕上的图片，
they're, technically, just characters, characters of an emoji alphabet
从技术上来说，它们只是字符，表情符号字母表中的字符，
that happened to use a certain pattern of 0's and 1's to represent
它碰巧使用了一种特定的 0 和 1 模式来表示
each of these faces, each of these people, and places, and things.
每张脸，每个人，每个地方，每件事物。
And it turns out that one of the reasons that we have just
事实证明，我们现在有这么多[笑声]字符的原因之一是，
so many [LAUGHS] such characters nowadays is because we now
现在我们使用 Unicode 而不是 ASCII。
use Unicode instead of ASCII.
我们现在使用 Unicode 而不是 ASCII。
So Unicode is a superset, so to speak, of ASCII,
所以，可以这么说，Unicode 是 ASCII 的超集，
which is to say that we, humans, realized, some time ago, that just
也就是说，我们人类在一段时间前意识到，仅仅
using eight bits to represent letters of the alphabet
使用八位来表示字母
certainly isn't very good when we want to represent
当我们想要表示
other, non-English languages.
其他非英语语言时，显然不太好。
So Unicode doesn't just use eight bits.
所以 Unicode 不仅仅使用八位。
It sometimes uses 16 bits per character, sometimes 24 bits per character,
它有时使用每个字符 16 位，有时使用每个字符 24 位，
and sometimes even 32 bits per character.
有时甚至使用每个字符 32 位。
Now, why those numbers?
现在，为什么是那些数字？
That's just one byte, two bytes, three bytes, or four bytes.
那只是一个字节、两个字节、三个字节或四个字节。
And that gives us--
那给我们——
does anyone know?
有人知道吗？
That gives us the ability to represent as many as 4
这给了我们表示多达 4
billion possible characters.
十亿个可能的字符的能力。
Because if the longest one is 32 bits, that's 2 to the 32,
因为如果最长的一个有 32 位，那就是 2 的 32 次方，
which, if you do out the math, trust me, is roughly 4 billion.
如果你把数学算出来，相信我，大约是 40 亿。
So that's a lot of characters.
所以，那可是很多字符。
And we've got a lot of room, then, for these emoji.
然后，我们就有很多空间容纳这些表情符号了。
But it's not just about having fun, pictorially, on the screen.
但这不仅仅是关于在屏幕上以图片形式玩乐。
Unicode's mission really is to represent and to preserve all human languages
Unicode 的使命实际上是表示和保留所有人类语言，
digitally, both past, present, and future.
以数字方式，包括过去、现在和未来。
So it is really about capturing the entirety of human knowledge,
所以，这实际上是关于捕捉人类知识的全部内容，
as we've expressed it in language, but also
正如我们在语言中表达的那样，而且也是
giving this newfound ability that's been used centuries ago, too-- in writings,
赋予这种全新的能力，这种能力在几个世纪前也被使用过——在写作中，
on walls, and the like-- pictograms via which
在墙壁上等等——象形文字，通过它
we can still communicate, even independently
我们仍然可以交流，即使独立于
of our own human language.
我们自己的语言。
So we'll reduce it, today, to just patterns of 0's and 1's, but
所以，今天我们将把它简化为 0 和 1 的模式，但是
the problem being solved is much greater and well-beyond CS, itself, there.
正在解决的问题要大得多，远远超出了 CS 本身。
So here is a pattern of 0's and 1's using
所以，这里有一个使用
Unicode, so more than eight bits, that represents a very popular emoji, which
Unicode 的 0 和 1 模式，所以超过八位，它表示一个非常流行的表情符号，它
might be a bit of a hint.
可能有点提示。
This is the most popular emoji, as of last year, at least,
至少在去年，这是最受欢迎的表情符号。
statistically, internationally.
从统计数据来看，在国际上也是如此。
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
[声音交叠]
DAVID J. MALAN: Does this help?
大卫·马兰：这有帮助吗？
It's, roughly, this number here.
它大约是这里这个数字。
No?
没有？
It's this one here.
是这里这个。
So this is the most popular emoji, by most measures, as of last year.
所以，根据大多数指标来看，这是去年最受欢迎的表情符号。
But it doesn't always look like this.
但它并不总是这个样子。
Those of you who have a Mac or an iPhone recognize this symbol, perhaps,
你们中拥有 Mac 或 iPhone 的人可能认得这个符号。
immediately.
立刻。
Those of you with Android devices or other platforms
那些使用 Android 设备或其他平台的人
might notice that it's the same idea, but it's a little bit different.
可能注意到它表达的是相同的意思，但略有不同。
And this is because, too, emojis, at the end of the day,
而这也是因为，归根结底，表情符号
just represent character, but those characters can be drawn,
只是代表字符，但这些字符可以被绘制，
can be painted in different ways.
可以用不同的方式描绘。
And reasonable people will interpret differently
而合理的人会对
this emoji, whose official name is "face with tears of joy."
这个表情符号有不同的解读，它的正式名称是“喜极而泣”。
And, indeed, Google interprets it a little differently
事实上，谷歌对它的解读与
from Apple, versus Microsoft, versus Meta, versus other companies, as well.
苹果、微软、Meta 以及其他公司略有不同。
So you can almost think of those different companies
所以，你可以把这些不同的公司
as having different fonts for emoji.
看作是为表情符号提供了不同的字体。
And that really starts to connect things to the world of text and characters.
这确实开始将表情符号与文本和字符的世界联系起来。
So, just so you've seen it.
所以，你已经看到了。
More on this, another time.
我们下次再详细谈谈。
It turns out that emoji and, really, characters, in general,
事实证明，表情符号，以及更普遍地讲，字符，
we don't use binary 0's and 1's to represent them
我们并不使用二进制的 0 和 1 来表示它们，
because no one, myself included, is going to recognize what's what.
因为没有人，包括我自己，能够识别出它们各自代表什么。
It's just too much math.
因为数学运算太复杂了。
It's not interesting.
这也没有什么趣味性。
And even decimal numbers-- that was 4 billion or some--
即使是十进制数字——那是 40 亿或某个
I don't remember which number is which.
我记不清哪个数字代表哪个符号了。
So we represent things a little more compactly.
因此，我们采用了一种更紧凑的表示方式。
And this, too, admittedly, still looks cryptic,
诚然，这种方式看起来仍然很神秘，
but this is a Unicode code point that uses another system, mathematically,
但这是一个 Unicode 代码点，它在数学上采用了另一种系统，
called base-16 or hexadecimal.
被称为 16 进制或十六进制。
More on that, another time.
我们下次再详细谈谈。
But it's just a way of representing numbers even more succinctly,
但它只是以一种更简洁的方式来表示数字，
writing less on the screen, because you're using not just 0
在屏幕上写入更少的字符，因为你不仅使用 0
through 9, as in decimal.
到 9，像十进制那样。
But you're using A through F, as well, so a few letters
而且你也会使用 A 到 F，所以英语字母表中的一些字母
of the English alphabet come into play.
也发挥了作用。
But, for now, that's just a little easier
但就目前而言，这只是一点点更容易
to remember, too, for people who care, that that is the number that
记住，对于那些关心的人来说，那就是代表
represents "face with tears of joy."
“喜极而泣”的数字。
But what if we want a customized emoji?
但如果我们想要一个自定义的表情符号呢？
And this, increasingly, is the case.
而这种情况正在越来越普遍。
Here, for instance, are the five skin tones
例如，这里有五种肤色，
that phones, and laptops, and desktops, nowadays, support.
如今的手机、笔记本电脑和台式电脑都支持这些肤色。
It's based on something called the "Fitzpatrick scale," which essentially
它基于一种叫做“菲茨帕特里克量表”的东西，它本质上
categorizes human skin tone into six or, in this case, five
将人类肤色分为六类，或者在这种情况下是五类，
different categories, from lighter to darker.
不同的类别，从浅色到深色。
But this suggests that, wow, if we want to represent people
但这表明，哇，如果我们想要用
with five different skin tones, like this, that could significantly
五种不同的肤色来代表人，像这样，这可能会显著地
increase how many unique patterns of 0's and 1's we
增加我们需要的 0 和 1 的独特组合的数量，
need for every possible face.
以用于每张可能的图像。
But if we think about it from an engineering perspective,
但如果我们从工程的角度来看，
we can actually just think of skin tone as modifying some default
我们实际上可以认为肤色只是修改了某些默认的
color, for better or for worse.
颜色，无论好坏。
And yellow is the de facto default, Simpson style.
黄色是事实上的默认颜色，就像辛普森一家那样。
But to modify it to look more genuinely human-like, from lighter to darker,
但为了使其看起来更像人类，从浅色到深色，
well, maybe we just use the same pattern of bits
好吧，也许我们只需要使用相同的比特模式
to represent a human thumb, for instance, thumbs up or thumbs down.
来表示一个人的拇指，例如，竖起大拇指或竖起大拇指。
And we just, then, modify that character to be displayed with a different skin
然后，我们只需要修改那个字符，让它以不同的皮肤显示
tone.
色调。
So, for instance, here, then, is the "thumbs up"
例如，这里就是“竖起大拇指”
that you might use on various platforms.
你可能在各种平台上使用。
And let me just stipulate that this is the Unicode code point.
让我先说明一下，这是 Unicode 代码点。
That is the number that Macs, PCs, and phones
它是 Mac、PC 和手机使用的数字
use underneath the hood to represent the default yellow "thumbs up."
在幕后用于表示默认的黄色“竖起大拇指”。
But if you want to give it a medium skin tone,
但如果你想给它一个中等肤色，
you still use that same number, that same pattern of 0's and 1's,
你仍然使用相同的数字，相同的 0 和 1 模式，
or switches, underneath the hood.
或开关，在幕后。
But you use a few more switches that the computer or phone
但你使用了一些额外的开关，计算机或手机
will interpret as, "Oh, you don't want to see the default in yellow
将解释为，“哦，你不希望看到默认的黄色
because of this second number that's in the computer's memory somewhere.
因为这个第二个数字在计算机的内存中。”
You want me to adjust it to be the medium skin tone or any
你想让我把它调整成中等肤色，或者任何
of the other values, instead."
其他值。”
So that's the engineering solution to this problem
所以这就是这个问题的工程解决方案
of just trying to represent different ranges of emoji here.
只是试图在这里表示不同范围的表情符号。
Well, what about something like this?
那么，像这样的东西怎么样？
There's a lot more combinatorics, nowadays,
现在，你的键盘上有很多组合，
on your keyboard for relationships, for instance.
例如，关于你的关系。
So here is a "couple with heart" here.
所以这里有一个“带着心的情侣”。
So the couple, here, of course, is represented with, apparently,
当然，这里的情侣用这个数字表示，
this number here.
就是这个数字。
But that's it.
但就是这样。
But if you want to be more specific-- like man and woman,
但如果你想更具体一些——比如男人和女人，
or man-man, woman-woman-- it's the same idea,
或者男人-男人，女人-女人——想法是一样的，
but we just need to express ourselves a little-- with a little
但我们只需要稍微表达一下自己——用一点
more information.
更多信息。
So, for instance, the way the Unicode folks came up with,
例如，Unicode 人员想出的方法是，
years ago, to represent, for instance, a woman with a heart and a man,
几年前，用来表示，例如，一个女人带着一颗心和一个男人，
from left to right, would be using these values.
从左到右，将使用这些值。
So things just escalated quickly, but only
所以事情很快就升级了，但只是
in the sense that we're using more bits, more 0's and 1's, to represent,
从我们使用更多比特，更多 0 和 1 来表示的角度来看，
more expressively, this particular combination.
更具表现力地，这种特定的组合。
So this happens to be the number in Unicode
所以这个恰好是 Unicode 中的数字
that represents the woman at left.
它代表左边那个女人。
This is the number that represents the man at right.
这个数字代表右边那个男人。
And this is the pair of numbers that represents
而这两个数字代表
the heart in the middle, sometimes red, sometimes pink, displayed here as pink.
中间的心，有时是红色，有时是粉色，这里显示为粉色。
But if we want to change the combination, for instance, to be,
但如果我们想改变组合，例如，变成，
say, woman--
比如，女人——
if we want to change the combination to be woman-woman,
如果我们想把组合改成女人-女人，
notice that, now, the left and the rightmost numbers match.
注意，现在，最左边和最右边的数字匹配。
Or if we flip it back to man-man, it's just using different numbers
或者如果我们把它翻回男人-男人，它只是在尾部使用不同的数字
on the tail end again.
而已。
And meanwhile, if I rewind, there's these two identical values here.
同时，如果我倒带，这里有两个相同的数字。
These are called zero-width joiners or ZWNJ characters.
这些被称为零宽度连接符或 ZWNJ 字符。
It just is a special number that humans reserve to say,
它只是一个特殊的数字，人类保留它来说明，
glue the emoji at the left to the emoji on the right and so forth.
把左边的表情符号粘到右边的表情符号上，等等。
So it connects ideas in this way.
所以它以这种方式连接想法。
So there's actually a lot of emojis, nowadays,
所以现在实际上有很多表情符号，
that are a combination of different things.
是不同事物的组合。
"Heart on fire" is one that's, technically,
“燃烧的心”是一个从技术上来说，
the combination of a heart emoji, the fire emoji,
一个心形表情符号和一个火焰表情符号的组合，
joined together, numerically, in this way.
以这种方式在数字上连接在一起。
So computer scientists who come up with these things
所以想出这些东西的计算机科学家
are just reducing things to representations.
只是将事物简化为表示。
All we have at our disposal are 0's and 1's.
我们能利用的只有 0 和 1。
So we all just need to agree, ultimately--
所以最终我们需要达成一致——
whether we're Google, Microsoft, or the like-- how we're going to standardize
无论是谷歌、微软还是其他公司，我们都要想办法制定标准
these kinds of things as information.
将这些东西作为信息。
Questions, then, on how characters are represented in a computer,
那么，关于字符如何在计算机中表示，你们有什么问题吗？
be it English or any other language?
无论是英语还是其他语言？
Yeah.
是的。
AUDIENCE: How is the plus a number?
听众：加号怎么会是数字呢？
DAVID J. MALAN: How is the what?
大卫·J·马兰：你说什么？
AUDIENCE: The plus, the U+.
听众：加号，U+。
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, the U+ is just a convention, really.
大卫·J·马兰：哦，U+只是一个约定俗成的符号而已。
So U+ represents a special Unicode character,
所以 U+ 代表一个特殊的 Unicode 字符，
which is a U with a plus in the middle.
也就是中间带加号的 U。
And this is just the convention for saying,
这只是一个约定俗成的符号，表示
hey, everyone, here comes a number that represents a Unicode code point.
嘿，大家好，接下来是一个代表 Unicode 码点的数字。
The U and the 1 have no-- sorry.
U 和 1 没有——抱歉。
The U and the plus have no mathematical significance.
U 和加号没有数学意义。
It's just a visual clue to folks.
它只是一个视觉提示。
Other questions on representing text in this way?
还有关于用这种方式表示文本的其他问题吗？
All right.
好的。
So what about colors?
那么颜色呢？
We've already started looking at pictures.
我们已经开始看图片了。
Well, how are those pictures, be it emojis or anything else, represented?
那么这些图片，无论是表情符号还是其他东西，是如何表示的呢？
One of the most common ways is just with RGB--
最常见的一种方式就是使用 RGB——
red, green, and blue.
红、绿和蓝。
It turns out that if we just keep track of how much red should
事实证明，如果我们只跟踪屏幕上应该显示多少红色
be on the screen, and how much green, and how much blue, combined together,
多少绿色，多少蓝色，然后将它们组合在一起，
that gives us every color of the rainbow,
就能得到彩虹中的所有颜色，
from white to black and everything in between.
从白色到黑色，以及所有介于两者之间的颜色。
So how do we represent an amount of red, and green, and blue?
那么我们如何表示红、绿和蓝的比例呢？
Well, frankly, just with three different numbers.
说白了，就是用三个不同的数字。
And this is how computers typically represent colors.
这就是计算机通常表示颜色的方式。
Every one of the dots on your computer screen or your phone screen
你的电脑屏幕或手机屏幕上的每个点
is called a pixel.
被称为像素。
And every single dot underneath the hood has three numbers associated with it,
每个点在内部都与三个数字相关联，
so three numbers, three numbers, three numbers for every little dot.
每个小点都对应三个数字，三个数字，三个数字。
And those three numbers, together, say how much red, green, and blue
这三个数字组合在一起表示在该位置应该显示多少红色、绿色和蓝色。
should the device display at that location.
应该在该位置显示多少红色、绿色和蓝色。
So, for instance, if you had a dot on your screen
例如，如果你屏幕上的一个点
that said, "use this much red, this much green this much blue," because each
表示“使用这么多红色，这么多绿色，这么多蓝色”，因为每个
of these numbers, I'll tell you, are one byte or eight bits,
数字，我告诉你，都是一个字节或八位，
which means the total possible values is 0 to 255--
这意味着可能的总值是 0 到 255——
let me just ballpark that the 72, it feels like a medium amount of red
让我猜一下，72 感觉像是中等程度的红色
because it's in between 0 and 255.
因为它介于 0 和 255 之间。
73 is a medium amount of green, and 33 of blue is just a little bit.
73 也是中等程度的绿色，而 33 的蓝色就少了一些。
So if you combine a medium amount of red, green, and a little bit of blue,
所以如果你将中等程度的红色、绿色和少量蓝色混合在一起，
anyone want to guess what color of the rainbow this is?
有人想猜猜这对应彩虹中的什么颜色吗？
AUDIENCE: Brown.
听众：棕色。
DAVID J. MALAN: Sorry?
大卫·J·马兰：你说什么？
AUDIENCE: Brown.
听众：棕色。
DAVID J. MALAN: Brown?
大卫·J·马兰：棕色？
So, close.
差不多。
It's a little more yellow than it is brown.
它比棕色更偏黄一些。
But if we combine them, it looks a little something like this.
但如果我们将它们组合在一起，看起来有点像这样。
This is just CS trivia, not something that even
这只是一些计算机科学的琐事，即使是我
I would be able to eyeball, unless I came up with that particular example.
也无法凭空想象出来，除非我想出了这个特定的例子。
But wait a minute.
等等。
We've seen these numbers before.
我们之前见过这些数字。
72, 73, 33 represented what--
72、73、33 代表什么——
AUDIENCE: Hi!
听众：嗨！
DAVID J. MALAN: --a few minutes ago?
大卫·J·马兰：——几分钟前？
So it meant "Hi!" but here I am, claiming, no, no, no, no,
所以它代表了“嗨！”，但我现在却说，不，不，不，不，
that means yellow.
这意味着黄色。
How do you reconcile this?
你如何调和这些？
Well, at the end of the day, this is all we have,
好吧，归根结底，这就是我们拥有的全部，
0's and 1's, whether you think of them as numbers,
0 和 1，无论你认为它们是数字，
or letters, or even colors now.
还是字母，甚至现在是颜色。
But it depends on the context.
但这取决于语境。
So if you've received a text message or an email,
所以如果你收到了短信或电子邮件，
odds are the pattern of 0's and 1's that the computer
计算机显示给你的 0 和 1 的模式很有可能
is showing you are going to be interpreted as text because that's
会被解释为文本，因为这就是
the whole point of a text message or an email.
短信或电子邮件的全部意义所在。
If, though, you opened up MacOS's or iOS's or Windows's or Android's
然而，如果你打开 macOS、iOS、Windows 或 Android 的
calculator app, the same pattern of 0's and 1's might
计算器应用程序，相同模式的 0 和 1 可能
be interpreted as numbers for some addition, or subtraction, or whatever.
会被解释为数字，用于加法、减法或其他运算。
If you open the same pattern of 0's and 1's in Photoshop,
如果你在 Photoshop 这样的图形程序中打开相同的 0 和 1 模式，
like a graphics program, they're going to be interpreted, in that context,
它们将在该上下文中被解释
as colors.
为颜色。
So context matters.
所以上下文很重要。
And, indeed, as soon as next week, when you
事实上，下周，当你
start writing code in that language called C,
开始用 C 语言编写代码时，
the onus will be on you, the programmer, to tell the computer, interpret
责任将落到你的肩上，作为程序员，你要告诉计算机，解释
the following sequence of bits as a number, or a letter, or something else.
以下位的序列为数字、字母或其他东西。
And you won't have to even worry about what the 0's and 1's are,
你甚至不必担心 0 和 1 是什么，
but you need to give the computer a hint as to what type of file
但你需要给计算机一个提示，说明你表示的是哪种类型的文件
or piece of data you're representing.
或数据片段。
So that gives us bits.
所以这就给了我们比特。
And you can actually see these dots, these pixels on the screen.
你实际上可以看到这些点，这些屏幕上的像素。
Let me zoom in, zoom in.
让我放大，放大。
And here we have it, just with this emoji, which, at the end of the day,
我们在这儿有它，就用这个表情符号，它归根结底
is a picture that someone at Apple, in this case, drew.
是一张苹果公司的人，在这种情况下，绘制的图片。
And you can see-- if you really zoom in, or take your phone or TV
你可以看到——如果你真的放大，或者拿着你的手机或电视
and really put it close to your face, you'll see all of these dots,
并真正靠近你的脸，你就会看到所有这些点，
depending on the hardware.
取决于硬件。
And each of these dots, these squares, is
而每个点，每个方块，是
storing 24 bits or three bytes, 24 bits, 24 bits, 24 bits.
存储 24 位或 3 个字节，24 位、24 位、24 位。
And that's whey, dot, dot, dot, if you've
这就是为什么，点、点、点，如果你有
got a photograph, for instance, that's three megabytes, which
一张照片，例如，它是 3 兆字节，这
is 3 million bytes, well, odds are there's 1 million pixels therein
是 300 万字节，那么，很有可能其中有 100 万像素
because you're using three bytes per pixel
因为你每像素使用 3 个字节
to represent each of those colors.
来表示每个颜色。
That's a bit of an oversimplification, but that's
这有点过于简化了，但这就是
why images and photos are getting bigger and bigger nowadays.
为什么如今图片和照片越来越大。
Because we're throwing even more pixels into the file.
因为我们正在往文件中添加更多像素。
Music--
音乐——
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[音乐播放]
--how could you represent music, digitally,
——你怎么可以用数字的方式，
using just 0's and 1's, or numbers, really?
只用 0 和 1，或者说，数字来表示音乐？
Any instinct, whether a musician or not?
无论是否音乐家，有什么想法？
Yeah.
是的。
AUDIENCE: The notes could be represented by a number.
观众：音符可以用数字来表示。
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, so we can just represent notes by a number.
大卫·J·马兰：是的，所以我们可以用数字来表示音符。
So A is some number, and B. And maybe sharp or flat is some other number.
所以 A 是某个数字，B 是另一个数字。也许升调或降调是其他数字。
But note might not be quite enough for some--
但音符可能不足以用于某些情况——
yeah?
是吧？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
观众：[听不清]
DAVID J. MALAN: Ah, OK.
大卫·J·马兰：啊，好吧。
So one note-- one number to represent the note, itself,
所以一个音符——一个数字来表示音符本身，
the sound or the pitch; one other number to represent the duration.
音调或音高；另一个数字来表示持续时间。
In the context of piano, how long is the human holding the key down?
在钢琴的情况下，人类按下琴键的时间有多长？
And maybe I can think of a third, the loudness.
也许我可以想到第三个，响度。
How hard has the person played that note?
这个人弹奏那个音符的力度有多大？
So, minimally, with three numbers, you could
所以，最少，用三个数字，你就可以
imagine representing music, as well.
想象一下，用它来表示音乐。
And, indeed, that's very well might be what computers
事实上，这很有可能就是计算机
are doing when you listen to sound.
在你听声音的时候所做的。
What about video?
视频呢？
How could you represent videos, as well?
你怎么用它来表示视频呢？
Yeah?
是吗？
AUDIENCE: Through many images.
观众：通过许多图像。
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, many images.
大卫·马兰：没错，许多图像。
So if you've ever produced a film or looked at some of the fine print,
如果你曾经制作过电影或者看过一些细节的话，
30 frames per second, FPS, or 29 frames per second
每秒 30 帧，FPS，或者每秒 29 帧，
is just how many pictures are flying across the screen.
就是屏幕上每秒播放的图片数量。
But that's really all a video file is on a computer,
但实际上，计算机上的视频文件就是
lots of pictures moving so quickly in front of us that you and I, our brains,
很多图片快速地在我们面前移动，以至于你和我的大脑
interpolate that as being actual motion.
将它们理解为实际的运动。
And, in fact, from yesteryear, motion pictures,
实际上，从过去来说，电影
it's like pictures that are giving the illusion of motion,
就像图片创造了运动的幻觉，
even though there's only 30 or so of them flying across the screen.
即使只有 30 张左右的图片在屏幕上移动。
So we have a way, now, to represent information, both as
所以现在我们有了一种方法来表示信息，无论是
input and output, whether it's numbers, letters, images, anything else.
输入还是输出，无论是数字、字母、图片，还是其他任何东西。
Let's now focus on what's inside of that black box,
现在让我们关注一下那个黑盒子里面是什么，
so to speak, wherein we have algorithms, step-by-step instructions
也就是说，在里面我们有算法，一步一步的指令
for solving some problem.
用来解决一些问题。
Now, what do I mean by "algorithms" or "step-by-step instructions"?
现在，我所说的“算法”或者“一步一步的指令”是什么意思呢？
Well, maybe, if we were to turn this into code--
嗯，也许，如果我们要把这些变成代码——
and that's how we'll connect the dots, ultimately, today.
这正是我们最终要将这些点连起来的方式。
Code is just the implementation, in computers, of algorithms.
代码只是在计算机中实现算法。
An algorithm can be something we do in the physical world.
算法可以是我们可以在现实世界中做的事情。
Code is how we implement that exact same idea, in the context of a computer,
代码是我们如何在计算机环境中实现相同的想法，
instead.
而不是。
And here, for instance, is a very common application inside of a computer,
例如，这里有一个计算机内部非常常见的应用，
for your context.
为了你的理解。
This is the iOS version of the icon.
这是 iOS 版本的图标。
And, typically, if you click on that icon,
通常，如果你点击这个图标，
you'll see something like all of your contacts here,
你会看到这里的所有联系人，
typically, alphabetical, by first name or last name.
通常按照姓氏或名字的首字母顺序排列。
And your phone or your computer lets you often search for someone's name
你的手机或电脑通常让你可以搜索某人的名字
at the very top.
在最上面。
And it will autocomplete, and it'll be pretty darn fast.
它会自动补全，而且速度非常快。
But it'll be pretty darn fast because the programmers who
但它会很快，因为实现这个应用的程序员
implemented that application are looking for someone quickly for you.
正在为你快速搜索某个人。
Now, I can do this old school style, whereby we have one of these things
现在，我可以按照老方法来做，我们有一个这样的东西
from yesteryear, an actual phone book.
来自过去，一本真正的电话簿。
So, in a physical phone book like this, you might have 1,000 pages.
所以，在一个像这样的实体电话簿中，你可能会有 1000 页。
And on every page are a bunch of names and a bunch of numbers.
每一页都有很多名字和很多号码。
And as I flip through this, I could look for someone specific.
当我翻阅这本书时，我可以寻找某个人。
So suppose I want to call John Harvard, who's-- the first name, of course,
假设我想给 John Harvard 打电话，他的名字是——当然，他的名字
starts with a J. Well, I could just turn, page by page,
以 J 开头。我可以一页一页地翻，
looking for John Harvard.
寻找 John Harvard。
And if he's not there, I keep turning and turning.
如果他不在，我就继续翻阅。
So this is an algorithm.
所以这就是一个算法。
I'm stepping through the phone book, one page at a time.
我正在一页一页地翻阅电话簿。
Is it correct, this algorithm, assuming I'm looking down?
这个算法正确吗，假设我正在向下看？
So, yeah.
所以，是的。
I mean, it's stupidly slow because why am
我的意思是，它非常慢，因为我为什么要
I wasting my time with the A's, and the B's, and the so forth?
浪费时间去看 A，B 等等？
I could probably take bigger bites out of it.
我可以更快地找到。
But it is correct.
但它是正确的。
And that's going to be one of the goals of writing code, is to, of course,
而编写代码的目标之一就是，当然，
solve the problem you care about correctly.
正确解决你关心的问题。
So correctness goes without saying, or else what's
所以正确性是不言而喻的，否则
the point of writing the code or solving-- or implementing
编写代码或解决问题的意义何在？或者实施
the algorithm?
算法？
All right.
好的。
Well, let me at least speed things up.
好吧，至少让我加快速度。
So, instead of one page at a time, so, two, four, six, eight--
所以，一次翻一页，所以，二、四、六、八……
no, ignore that-- 10, 12, 14, 16, and so forth.
不，忽略那个——十、十二、十四、十六，等等。
It's a little hard to do, physically, but it sounded faster.
从物理上来说，这有点难做，但听起来更快。
It was twice as fast, theoretically, but is it correct?
理论上，它快了一倍，但它正确吗？
AUDIENCE: No.
观众：不。
DAVID J. MALAN: So, no.
大卫·J·马兰：所以，不。
Why?
为什么？
Yeah?
是吗？
AUDIENCE: Yeah, you might [INAUDIBLE].
观众：是的，你可能会[听不清]。
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, I might miss John Harvard because, just by accident,
大卫·J·马兰：是的，我可能会错过约翰·哈佛，因为，仅仅是偶然，
he might get sandwiched between two pages.
他可能会被夹在两页之间。
But do I have to throw the algorithm out altogether?
但我必须完全抛弃这个算法吗？
Probably not.
可能不会。
Once I reach the K section, which is past the J section,
一旦我到达K部分，也就是超过J部分，
I could double back at least one page, at least, [PATS TELEPHONE BOOK]
我至少可以翻回一页，至少，[拍电话簿]
and just make sure I didn't blow past him completely.
并确保我没有完全错过他。
So that is twice as fast, because I'm going two pages
所以速度快了一倍，因为我一次翻两页
at a time, plus one extra step.
一次，加一步额外操作。
So it's still an improvement.
所以这仍然是一种改进。
So the first algorithm, worst case, if it's
所以第一个算法，最坏情况下，如果它是
not John, but someone whose name starts with Z,
不是约翰，而是名字以Z开头的某人，
that might take me a full 1,000 steps.
这可能需要我走完1000步。
The second algorithm is just 500 steps because I'm
第二个算法只需要500步，因为我
going two pages at a time plus one, in case I have to double back,
一次翻两页，加一步，以防我必须翻回去，
but that's in the worst case.
但那是最坏的情况下。
But most of us in the-- in yesteryear, and what Apple, and Google, and others
但我们大多数人在——在过去，以及苹果、谷歌和其他
are actually doing is, in software or here, physically,
实际上正在做的是，在软件中或在这里，在物理上，
we're typically going, roughly, to the middle.
我们通常会，大致地，走到中间。
Especially if there's no cheat sheet on the side, like A through Z,
特别是如果旁边没有备忘单，比如从A到Z，
I'm just going to go to, roughly, the middle.
我只是大致地走到中间。
And, oh, here I am, not surprisingly, in the M section.
而且，哦，我在这里，不出所料，在M部分。
But what do I now know.
但我现在知道什么。
If this is the M section, where is John Harvard?
如果这是M部分，约翰·哈佛在哪里？
So, clearly, to the left, alphabetically.
所以，很明显，在左边，按字母顺序排列。
And so here is where we can take a much bigger bite out of the problem.
所以，这里是我们能够从问题中获得更多收益的地方。
We can really divide and conquer this problem
我们真的可以分而治之这个问题
by tearing [TEARS BOOK] the problem in half, throwing half of it
通过撕开[撕书]问题的一半，扔掉一半
away, 500 pages away, leaving me with a smaller problem,
扔掉，500页扔掉，留下一个更小的问题，
half as big, that I can really just now repeat.
小一半，我可以现在重复一遍。
So I go, roughly, here, and now I'm in the E section.
所以我大致地走到这里，现在我在E部分。
So I went a little too far back.
所以我回过头走得太远了。
But what do I now know?
但我现在知道什么？
If this is the E pages, where's John?
如果这是E页，约翰在哪里？
AUDIENCE: To the right.
观众：在右边。
DAVID J. MALAN: So now he's to the right.
大卫·J·马兰：所以他现在在右边。
So I can-- again, hopefully, he's not on that page.
所以我可以——再一次，希望他不在那页上。
I can tear the problem in half again, throw that 250 pages away.
我可以再次把问题撕成两半，扔掉那250页。
And now I've gone from 1,000 to 500 to 250 pages.
现在我已经从1000页变到500页，再到250页。
Now I'm moving because the first algorithm was one page at a time,
现在我正在移动，因为第一个算法是一次翻一页，
second was two.
第二个是一次翻两页。
This is hundreds of pages at a time.
这次是一次翻几百页。
And if I go, roughly, again, to the middle; roughly,
如果我再次大体上走到中间；大体上，
to the middle; roughly, to the middle, hopefully, I'll
到中间；大体上，到中间，希望我会
find John Harvard on one final page.
在最后一页找到约翰·哈佛。
Can only do this once, but one final page.
只能做一次，但只有一页。
So that invites the question, I would think,
所以我想，这引发了一个问题，
if the phone book does have 1,000 or so pages,
如果电话簿有1000页左右，
how many times can I divide the problem in half to get down to one last page?
我需要将问题分成两半多少次才能得到最后的一页？
So it's, roughly, 10.
所以，大约是10次。
And the quick math is 1,000 goes to 500 to 250 to 125 to 67 something.
快速计算一下，从1000页到500页，到250页，到125页，到67页左右。
So we have to deal with rounding issues, eventually.
所以，我们最终必须处理四舍五入的问题。
But assuming we work out the math, it's, roughly, 10 page tears.
但假设我们算出结果，大约需要撕10页。
And that's crazy faster than 1,000 pages and still faster than 500 pages.
这比翻1000页快得多，而且也比翻500页快。
So it's fundamentally better.
所以，从根本上说，它更好。
And, indeed, if I finally get to that final page, in the software world,
实际上，如果我最终找到了最后一页，在软件世界里，
you'd see something like this, John Harvard and his number,
你会看到这样的东西，约翰·哈佛和他的号码，
which you're welcome to call or text.
你可以打电话或发短信给他。
But that's how we now have our answer, much like the single page there.
但这就是我们现在得到答案的方式，就像那里的一页一样。
But let's consider just how efficient that actually is.
但让我们考虑一下这实际上有多高效。
So here's a very rough, broad-- with broad strokes, a chart.
所以，这里有一个非常粗略的图表，用粗线条画的。
So here's an xy plot.
这是一个xy坐标图。
So here, on the horizontal, is going to be the size of the problem.
所以，这里，水平轴上，表示问题的规模。
And, by that, I mean, how many pages are we trying to go through?
也就是说，我们试图翻多少页？
This would be zero pages.
这表示零页。
This would be a lot of pages.
这表示很多页。
How much time does it take to solve the problem?
解决问题需要多长时间？
How long does it take to find John Harvard or anyone else?
找到约翰·哈佛或其他任何人需要多长时间？
This means no time.
这表示不需要时间。
This means a lot of time.
这表示需要很多时间。
So what's the relationship among these algorithms?
那么，这些算法之间有什么关系呢？
Well, the first one is actually just a straight line.
嗯，第一个实际上只是一条直线。
If there's n pages in the phone book, well, I
如果电话簿有n页，那么，我
claim that it's a one-to-one relationship.
认为这是一个一一对应关系。
Because if Verizon or the phone company adds another page next year,
因为如果Verizon或电话公司明年加了一页，
that just means I might have one more step next year,
这也意味着我明年可能需要多走一步，
as well, to find John Harvard or anyone else.
同样，才能找到约翰·哈佛或其他人。
But the second algorithm, it's also a straight line,
但第二个算法，它也是一条直线，
but it's lower, even though it might not look obvious.
但它更低，尽管它可能不明显。
And what do I mean by that?
我的意思是什么呢？
Well, let me just draw some temporary lines.
好吧，让我画一些临时线条。
If this is how many pages are in the phone book-- dot,
如果这是电话簿的页数——点，
dot, dot-- notice that it takes this much time, on the red line,
点，点——注意，在红线上，需要这么长时间，
to solve the problem.
来解决问题。
But if I, instead, use the second algorithm,
但如果我用第二个算法，
it takes me half as much time.
我只需要一半的时间。
So, even though they're both straight lines,
所以，尽管它们都是直线，
one is strictly lower than the other, which means it's faster.
但其中一个严格低于另一个，这意味着它更快。
It's better.
它更好。
But the third algorithm is a fundamentally different shape,
但第三个算法的形状完全不同，
and it looks a little something like this.
它看起来有点像这样。
And it looks like it's going to flatten, flatten, flatten out,
它看起来要变平，变平，变平，
but it never does.
但它永远不会变平。
It just rises ever so slowly.
它只是非常缓慢地上升。
And what this means is that if maybe Cambridge and Allston, here
这意味着，如果也许剑桥和奥尔思顿，在这里
in Massachusetts, merge next year, so we go from 1,000 page phone book
在马萨诸塞州，明年合并，所以我们从1000页的电话簿
to a 2,000 page phone book, that means, if we're here this year,
变成2000页的电话簿，这意味着，如果我们今年在这里，
we're over here next year.
我们明年就在这里了。
It's not all that much higher.
它并没有高很多。
But it would be much higher if we were using the first two algorithms.
但如果我们使用前两个算法，它会高很多。
Why?
为什么？
It'd be an extra 1,000 steps to find someone in that combined phone
在那个合并的电话簿里找一个人，需要多走1000步，
book or maybe another 500 steps.
或者可能还需要多走500步。
But, to be clear, if we're using my third and final algorithm,
但，说清楚，如果我们使用我的第三个也是最后一个算法，
how many more steps will it take me next year,
明年我需要多走多少步，
when Cambridge and Allston merge into one 2,000-page phone book?
当剑桥和奥尔思顿合并成一本2000页的电话簿？
Just one more step, no big deal.
只有一步，没什么大不了的。
It's one more page tear.
这又撕掉了一页。
And this is what we mean, ultimately, about not just writing
最终，我们想要表达的是，不仅仅是编写
code or implementing algorithms that are correct, but, now,
代码或实现正确的算法，而是现在，
that are well-designed or efficient, specifically.
设计良好或高效的算法，特别要强调这一点。
And this is what makes someone a better programmer, perhaps,
而这也许正是让一个人成为比其他人更优秀的程序员的原因，
than someone else, or a better problem-solver than someone else,
或者成为比其他人更优秀的解决问题者，
is acquiring, over time, these skills.
就是随着时间的推移，掌握这些技能。
So that, sure, you could solve the problem quickly and dirtily,
因此，当然，你可以快速且粗糙地解决问题，
so to speak, but if you're going to have a lot of data
可以这么说，但如果你最终要处理大量的数据，
eventually, be it in your phone book or maybe your Google website index,
无论是你的电话簿，还是你的谷歌网站索引，
if you're searching the web, you're going
如果你正在搜索网页，你将会
to want to try to think about how to design algorithms that look like this.
想要尝试思考如何设计类似这样的算法。
Mathematically, this is called a logarithm.
从数学角度来说，这叫做对数。
And it's log base 2 because I'm halving, halving, halving, again and again.
这是以 2 为底的对数，因为我一直在不断地对半分，对半分。
But, for now, just know that it's a fundamentally faster and different
但现在，你只需要知道这是一种从根本上来说更快、更不同的
shape.
形状。
So, among our goals in CS50, ultimately, is not just
因此，在 CS50 中，我们的最终目标不仅仅是
to write and solve problems correctly, but, ultimately, ever more efficiently,
编写代码并正确解决问题，而是最终以更高效的方式来解决问题，
as well.
同样。
Any questions, then, on these ideas of efficiency and design?
那么，关于这些效率和设计方面的想法，有什么问题吗？
Any questions here?
这里有什么问题吗？
Yeah, in back?
好的，最后面的那位同学？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
观众：[听不清]
DAVID J. MALAN: A good question.
大卫·马兰：好问题。
Just to repeat it, can a graph like this capture the accuracy of the algorithm?
我来重复一下，这样的图表可以捕捉到算法的准确性吗？
Short answer, no.
简单来说，不行。
For instance, if I drew a straight line that
例如，如果我画一条直线，
is super low on this graph, which would imply that the algorithm takes
在图表上非常低，这将意味着该算法需要
the same amount of time, no matter how many pages there are,
相同的时间，无论有多少页，
my algorithm might actually be to just pull a random page from the phone
我的算法实际上可能是随机从电话中取出一页，
book, one step, and say, here it is.
簿，一步，然后说，就是它了。
But that's not necessarily going to be accurate,
但这并不一定准确，
unless I get really, really lucky.
除非我非常非常幸运。
So the graph really only speaks to efficiency
因此，图表实际上只反映了效率
and the design of the algorithm, not the correctness of it.
以及算法的设计，而不是它的正确性。
To analyze the correctness, you need to use another mechanism altogether,
为了分析正确性，你需要使用完全不同的机制，
namely, logic.
即逻辑。
Other questions now, on efficiency, in this way?
现在还有其他关于效率方面的问题吗？
No?
没有了？
All right.
好的。
So, with that in mind, let's begin to translate this to some actual code.
因此，考虑到这一点，让我们开始将这些内容翻译成一些实际的代码。
And, in fact, before we look at, today, one actual programming language,
事实上，在我们今天看到一种实际的编程语言之前，
albeit a graphical one, let's consider something called pseudocode.
尽管它是一种图形化的语言，让我们考虑一下一种叫做伪代码的东西。
So pseudocode has no formal meaning.
因此，伪代码没有正式的意义。
Generally, you write it in English or whatever your own human language is.
通常，你用英语或你的母语来编写它。
But you write your thoughts down tersely, succinct, but precisely.
但你用简洁、精炼但精确的语言写下你的想法。
You try to really convey your thoughts, not with a wave of the hand,
你试图真正传达你的想法，而不是用挥手，
metaphorically, but step by step, precisely.
用比喻的方式，而是逐步地，精确地。
So what do I mean by this?
那么，我的意思是呢？
Here might be some representative pseudocode
这里可能有一些代表性的伪代码，
via which I describe that third and final algorithm in a way
通过它们，我以一种能够
that I could hand it to you and you could do the same at home.
将它交给你，你可以在家做同样的事情的方式来描述第三种也是最后一种算法。
Or I could hand it to someone at Google, and they could implement it in Android.
或者我可以把它交给谷歌的某个人，他们可以在 Android 上实现它。
Or I could hand it to someone at Apple, and they could implement it in iOS.
或者我可以把它交给苹果的某个人，他们可以在 iOS 上实现它。
So, step one, I claimed, was "Pick up phone book."
因此，第一步，我声称是“拿起电话簿”。
Step two was "Open to the middle of the phone book."
第二步是“翻到电话簿的中间”。
Step three, "Look at the page," as I did.
第三步，"看看那一页"，就像我做的那样。
And now things get a little more interesting.
现在事情变得有趣起来。
Step four, "If person is on page," I have to make a decision.
第四步，"如果该人在这页上"，我必须做出决定。
Presumably, what should I do if John Harvard is on the page I'm looking at?
据推测，如果我在看的页面上有约翰·哈佛，我应该怎么办？
So stop and probably make the call, or email, or whatever the goal might be.
所以，停下来，可能要打电话或发邮件，或者做任何可能的目标。
And so I'm going to actually indent this, visually, by a few spaces,
因此，我实际上将通过几个空格在视觉上缩进它，
just to make clear that you should only do line five if the answer to line four
只是为了清楚地表明，只有当第四行的答案为是时，你才应该执行第五行。
is yes.
是。
Otherwise, you don't bother.
否则，你就不要费心了。
The next thing I'm going to do, line six, is consider another possibility.
接下来我要做的事情，也就是第六行，是考虑另一种可能性。
"If the person I'm looking for is earlier
"如果我正在寻找的人在更早
in the book," what do I want to do?
在书中"，我想做什么？
Well, I could write--
好吧，我可以写——
I could describe this in a bunch of ways.
我可以用很多方法描述它。
I'm going to do this tersely, as follows.
我将简短地进行如下操作。
"Open to the middle of the left half of the book,
"翻开书的左边一半的中间，
so it's open to the middle of the left half of the book.
所以它翻开了书的左边一半的中间。
And then, what am I going to do?
然后，我要做什么？
Well, I've just divided the problem into something smaller.
好吧，我刚刚把问题分成更小的问题。
But it's fundamentally the same problem.
但它本质上是一样的问题。
It's just a fewer number of pages.
只是页数更少。
So I'm just going to go back to line three and do it again
所以我只是要回到第三行再做一次。
because the problem is just getting smaller and smaller, presumably.
因为这个问题正在变得越来越小，据推测。
Else, if the person I'm looking for is later in the book,
否则，如果我正在寻找的人在书的后面，
open to the middle of the right half of the book,
翻开书的右边一半的中间，
and, also, "Go back to line 3."
同时，“回到第三行。”
But there's a fourth possibility and its failure
但还有第四种可能性，以及它没有实现
to realize, sometimes, that there's other possible outcomes that
有时，会意识到可能存在其他结果，这些结果会
make computers crash, or spinning beach balls, or the like,
导致电脑崩溃，或出现旋转沙漏，或类似的情况，
if a programmer doesn't anticipate some situation.
如果程序员没有预料到某些情况。
What's the fourth possible situation, when looking for John Harvard?
寻找约翰·哈佛时，第四种可能的情况是什么？
AUDIENCE: If they're not in the book.
观众：如果他们不在书里。
DAVID J. MALAN: If they're not in the book, at all.
大卫·J·马兰：如果他们根本不在书里。
And, indeed, I might get to the very last page and John Harvard's not even
实际上，我可能翻到最后一页，约翰·哈佛甚至都不
on that one.
在那一页上。
I'd better handle that and say, else, as a catchall, just quit altogether.
我最好处理一下，并说，否则，作为一个万能的解决方案，直接退出。
And, truly, often, in your Macs, PCs, phones,
实际上，在你的Mac、PC、手机中，
when they freeze, or, again, spinning beach ball, or the like,
当它们冻结，或者再次出现旋转沙漏，或类似情况时，
and just weird things happen, that's just
只是奇怪的事情发生了，那是因为
because some human made a dumb mistake.
因为有些人犯了愚蠢的错误。
And they didn't realize that you could somehow get your phone or your laptop
他们没有意识到你可以以某种方式让你的手机或笔记本电脑
into a configuration that they didn't anticipate.
进入他们没有预料到的配置。
So we're going to try to handle that here.
所以我们将在這裡尝试处理这个问题。
Now this is just one way of writing pseudocode.
现在这只是写伪代码的一种方式。
There's no one way to do this.
没有一种正确的方法可以做到这一点。
All of us in this room could come up with slightly different pseudocode.
我们房间里的每个人都可以想出略微不同的伪代码。
But I think you'll find characteristic are certain building
但我认为你会发现，特征是某些构建的
blocks in all of our answers.
模块存在于我们所有人的答案中。
Here, in yellow, are what, as of today, we're
这里，用黄色标示的是，截止到今天，我们
going to start calling "functions," technically speaking.
开始称之为“函数”，从技术上讲。
These are like actions or verbs that literally, in this case, tell me
这些就像动作或动词，在这种情况下，它们实际上告诉我
what to do.
该怎么做。
Next, we're going to have these things, conditionals,
接下来，我们将拥有这些东西，条件语句，
forks in the road, so to speak, that take me down this path or another,
打个比方，道路的分叉，引导我走这条路或另一条路，
metaphorically.
比喻地说。
So I do this thing or something else.
所以我做这件事或做其他事情。
But how do I decide if I want to go this way, or this way,
但我该如何决定是否要走这条路，或走那条路，
or this way, or this way?
或走这条路，或走那条路？
I need to ask a question.
我需要问一个问题。
And in programming, we'll typically use what
在编程中，我们通常使用什么
are called Boolean expressions, named after a mathematician, Boole.
被称为布尔表达式，以数学家布尔命名。
And a Boolean expression is essentially just a question
布尔表达式本质上就是一个问题
with a yes/no answer, a true or false answer, a 1 or 0 answer.
只有两种答案：是或否，真或假，1或0。
It doesn't matter how you think about it, but it's got two possible answers.
无论你怎么想，它都只有两种可能的答案。
And so you can think of these as being expressions with question marks,
所以你可以把它们看成带问号的表达式，
even though I didn't draw such.
尽管我没画出来。
Person on page, person earlier in book, person later in book,
书页上的人物，书中前面的人物，书中后面的人物，
those are Boolean expressions.
这些都是布尔表达式。
And they tell me whether I should go down one fork in the road or another.
它们告诉我应该走哪条路。
And, lastly, there's this, "Go back to line 3," in two different places.
最后，还有一个“回到第3行”的指令，出现在两个不同的位置。
That represents what we call a "loop," some kind of cycle that's
这表示我们所说的“循环”，一种周而复始的结构，
doing something again and again.
一遍又一遍地执行某件事。
Now these are just a few building blocks here--
这里只是几个基本模块：
functions, conditionals, Boolean expressions, loops.
函数、条件语句、布尔表达式、循环。
But you'll find that they're characteristic of so
但你会发现，它们是如此的
many different languages, one of which we'll look at today, another of which
普遍存在于不同的语言中，我们今天将研究其中一种，另一种
we'll look at next week.
我们将在下周研究。
And those include, indeed, C, and Python, and other languages still.
这些语言包括C、Python，以及其他的语言。
And so this is why we focus on these basics
所以，这就是我们在这最初阶段关注这些基础知识的原因，
and fundamentals in these early days because we're
因为我们将在后面的学习中
going to see them again and again.
一遍又一遍地看到它们。
So even if you feel like that fire hose is hitting you sometime,
所以，即使你感觉被信息轰炸了，
we'll give you, today, ultimately, more visuals
我们今天会提供更多直观的素材，
by which you can hang onto, so as to actually write code, ultimately,
让你能够理解，最终能够编写代码，
in different languages and solve all sorts of problems.
用不同的语言解决各种问题。
Now, we'd be remiss in not bringing up what's behind characters like Spot,
现在，我们不能不谈论像Spot这样的角色背后的技术，
and ChatGPT, and other software, artificial intelligence.
还有ChatGPT，以及其他软件，人工智能。
And it turns out, to get to the point of AI,
事实证明，要达到人工智能的水平，
we're actually going to need more building blocks than just
我们需要的不仅仅是函数、循环和条件语句这些基本模块。
functions, and loops, and conditionals.
这并不像看起来那么简单。
It's not going to be quite that simple.
到目前为止，我们已经学了很多。
But this has been a lot, so far.
我们先休息5分钟。
Let's go ahead, here, and take a five-minute break.
休息回来后，我们将学习人工智能，
And when we resume, we'll take a look not only at AI,
以及一种叫做Scratch的编程语言。
but also a specific language called Scratch.
所以，暂时还没有蛋糕，但我们5分钟后回来。
So no cake, just yet, but we'll come back in five.
在我们重新开始之前，我想介绍一下我们今天的特别嘉宾，
Before we dive back in, I just wanted to call out a special guest
除了Spot，还有一个人从更远的地方来到这里。
that we have here today, beyond Spot, someone
实际上，如果你学过CS50x，也就是CS50的开放课程版本，
who's come from even farther away.
或者过去几年在CS50的一些在线社群中学习过，
And, in fact, if any of you have taken CS50x, the OpenCourseWare version
你可能得到过一位来自新西兰的人的帮助。
of the class, or dabbled in it over the past few years
她今天专程来到这里，与我们一起上这节课。
in some of CS50's online social communities,
她是CS50的Brenda Anderson。
you might have had your questions answered
让我们一起欢迎她。
by a certain human from New Zealand.
[掌声]
And she's come all this way, today, to spend this lecture with us.
这只是一点小小的感谢。
This is CS50's own Brenda Anderson.
多年来，Brenda帮助了成千上万的在线学生。
If you might come up for acknowledgment from all of us here.
事实上，她女儿是今年和未来CS50中“鸭子”形象的创作者。
[APPLAUSE]
感谢Brenda。
It's not much, but just a little token of our thanks.
[掌声]
Brenda has helped, truly, thousands of students online
好的。
for the past many years.
如今，很难回避人工智能的话题。
And, in fact, her own daughter has been the artist
我们想借此机会将一些知识点串联起来。
behind the duck that's about to loom large in CS50 this year and beyond.
[结束]
So, thank you to Brenda.
[APPLAUSE]
[结束]
All right.
So it's hard to escape a discussion of artificial intelligence, nowadays,
[结束]
but we thought we'd use this as an opportunity
to connect some of these dots.
[结束]
Because, indeed, over the course of the semester,
的确，在本学期中，
we'll be-- not only be talking about artificial intelligence or AI,
我们不仅会讨论人工智能或 AI，
but really using it all the more constructively
而且真正地更具建设性地利用它
to help you solve problems, help you get unblocked
帮助你解决问题，帮助你突破障碍
when you hit a wall, cognitively or syntactically, when writing code.
当你编写代码时，在认知上或语法上遇到障碍。
And, indeed, it's no accident that we have this duck here,
而且，我们这里有这只鸭子，这绝非偶然，
looming large, which is really the embodiment of the sort of AI
它非常显眼，它实际上是你将在 CS50 中体验到的 AI 的体现，
that you'll experience within CS50, itself, this year.
今年的 CS50 自身就是。
So let's talk about the so-called chatbots that
所以让我们来谈谈那些被称为聊天机器人的东西
inspired some of those headlines with which we began
激发了我们开始课程时的一些头条新闻
class, that weren't quite on the nose.
那些并不完全切中要害。
So the class will still be taught by us humans,
所以这门课仍然会由我们人类教授，
but helped by this CS50 duck, a chatbot of sorts.
但会受到这只 CS50 鸭子的帮助，它也算是一种聊天机器人。
Now what do I mean by this?
我现在指的是什么？
Well, it turns out that, when it comes to implementing something
事实证明，当谈到实现某些东西时
like an artificial intelligence, we don't quite
比如人工智能，我们还没有完全
have all of the building blocks yet, certainly after just today's week zero,
拥有所有的构建模块，当然，仅仅经过了今天的零周之后，
to implement something like that.
要实现这样的东西。
But I think we can skate in that direction, intellectually.
但我认为我们可以在智力上向那个方向前进。
So, for instance, if we were to take a stab at implementing our own chatbot--
例如，如果我们要尝试实现我们自己的聊天机器人——
some interactive text-based program that talks to us,
一些与我们对话的交互式基于文本的程序，
and answers questions, and the like-- we could
并回答问题等等，我们可以
try borrowing some of today's ideas already, those functions, conditionals,
尝试借用一些今天的想法，比如那些函数、条件语句、
loops, and more.
循环等等。
And I could write something like this.
我可以写出类似这样的东西。
If I am writing code or pseudocode for a chatbot,
如果我正在为聊天机器人编写代码或伪代码，
I could program the chatbot to do something like this.
我可以为聊天机器人编程使其执行类似的操作。
If the student says, hello, to the chatbot,
如果学生对聊天机器人说“你好”，
then the chatbot should say, hello, back.
那么聊天机器人应该回复“你好”。
Else, if the student says, goodbye, well, the chatbot
否则，如果学生说“再见”，那么聊天机器人
should say, goodbye, back.
应该回复“再见”。
Else, if the student asks how you are, the chat bot should say that it's well.
否则，如果学生问“你好吗”，聊天机器人应该说它很好。
But things get a little harder when you start
但当你开始提问
asking more interesting questions, like, else,
更有趣的问题时，就会变得更难，比如，否则，
if the student asks why 111 in binary is 7 in decimal.
如果学生问为什么二进制的 111 等于十进制的 7。
Now, you could imagine that we just have a conditional,
现在，你可以想象我们只有一个条件语句，
with this Boolean expression, that programs the chatbot to just give you
用这个布尔表达式，来编程聊天机器人，让你得到
the answer and explain, in an English sentence, why that, in fact, is.
答案并用英语句子解释为什么确实是那样。
But what if you, the student, asks why 110 is 6 in decimal or why 010 is 2?
但如果你，学生，问为什么 110 等于十进制的 6 或为什么 010 等于 2 呢？
I mean, you can just imagine the explosion in the amount of code
我的意思是，你可以想象我们必须编写的代码量会爆炸性增长
that we would have to write to just anticipate every darn question that you
仅仅为了预测你可能会问的每一个问题而需要编写的代码量
might ask about today and every other class, not to mention all
可能会问关于今天和所有其他课程的问题，更不用说所有
of the knowledge in the universe.
宇宙中的知识了。
So, surely, there are other ways to implement algorithms
所以，当然，还有其他方法可以实现算法
that allow something like a chatbot or AI,
允许像聊天机器人或 AI 这样的东西
more generally, to be fed input, still, like all of the internet, all
更一般地说，被输入信息，仍然像整个互联网，所有
of the worldwide web, all of the pages and textual content therein,
万维网，所有网页和其中的文本内容
but to let it just figure out how to answer our questions based
而是让它根据这些输入
on those kinds of inputs, assuming the inputs, themselves, are accurate.
来想出如何回答我们的问题，假设这些输入本身是准确的。
So "large language models" is a term you might
所以“大型语言模型”是你可能
have heard bandied about over the past several months, or LLMs.
在过去几个月听到的术语，或者说是 LLMs。
And a large language model really is an implementation, in software,
而大型语言模型实际上是软件中的一种实现，
of code that actually takes, as input, lots and lots of language--
代码，它实际上以大量的语言作为输入——
like the text of lots and lots of web pages, dictionaries, encyclopedias,
比如大量的网页、字典、百科全书的文本
Wikipedias, and the like--
维基百科等等——
and infers, from the patterns of English words or any human language,
它从英文单词或任何人类语言的模式中推断
what a typical human might actually say when asked a question.
当被问到问题时，一个普通人实际上会说什么。
And some of these questions are easy, right?
其中一些问题很简单，对吧？
Probably, on the internet, alone, not to mention everyday life, if someone
可能，在互联网上，一个人，更不用说日常生活了，如果有人
extends their hand and says, "Hi.
伸出手说：“你好。
How are you," odds are, with 90% probability, you're going to say,
你好吗？”很有可能，有 90% 的概率，你会说，
"Good.
“很好。
Thanks.
谢谢。
How are you?"
你好吗？”
So I bet we could write software that just
所以，我敢打赌我们可以编写一个软件，它可以
infers what it should say, probabilistically, statistically, based
根据概率，统计学，基于这些模式推断它应该说什么。
on those kinds of patterns online.
这些在线模式。
And that's, indeed, where the world is starting
这确实是当今世界在最复杂的算法领域开始走向的地方，
to go, when it comes to the most sophisticated
你我这些人类
of algorithms, where you and I, the humans,
不会试图预测所有可能的输入。
we don't try to anticipate every possible input.
相反，我们给它一个更通用的
Rather, we give it a more general purpose
输入，比如所有的人类知识，理想情况下，就让它自己去弄清楚。
input, like all human knowledge, and ideally just let it figure things out.
现在，我们还没有达到那个程度。
Now, we're not quite there, yet.
而且你可能听说过这些大型语言模型会产生幻觉或错误。
And odds are you've heard of hallucinations or just mistakes
但它们的输入并不完美。
that these large language models make.
有时候会有一些随机性，因为你不想它总是说完全一样的话。
But their inputs are imperfect.
即使你我可能也会说，“嗯，我今天不太好”10% 的时间。
And sometimes there's a bit of randomness sprinkled
所以你需要以某种方式扰乱输出。
in because you don't want the thing to always say the exact same thing.
但在 CS50 和大型语言模型的世界里，
Even you and I might say, "Eh, I'm not that great today" 10% of the time.
我们确实拥有像 ChatGPT、Bing Chat 以及其他这样的工具。
So you need to perturb the output in some way.
我们会规定，出于 CS50 的目的，
But within CS50 and within this world of large language models,
我们今年的方向是，这就是课程大纲中的内容，等等。
we do have these tools like ChatGPT, and Bing, chat, and others.
使用除 CS50 自有工具之外的基于 AI 的软件是不允许的，会被认为是不合理的。
And we'll stipulate that, for CS50's purposes,
所以这里的目标不是简单地拿走
the direction we're going this year is that this
在我看来，这些工具是不可避免的，而且明显很有帮助
is what's in the syllabus, dot, dot, dot;
并且能节省时间。
that it will not be allowed, it will be considered
但是，我们希望对这些聊天机器人的帮助程度有一些智力上的限制。
not reasonable to use AI-based software, other than CS50's own.
因为你可能已经看到，如果你问它一个问题，
So the goal here is not to simply take away
这些聊天机器人已经很擅长不仅帮你完成当前的想法，还会
tools that are clearly inevitable, in my view, and clearly helpful
帮你完成第二个和第三个想法，并帮你完成作业。
and productivity savers.
但我认为，通过提示，我们可以引导我们自己的工具，
But we'd like there to be some guardrails, intellectually, on just how
作为计算机科学家，朝着一个你认为是正确平衡的方向发展，就像有一个
helpful these chatbots are.
全天候陪伴你的好导师，他不只是给你答案，
Because as you've probably seen, if you ask it a question,
而是试图引导你找到相同的答案。
these chatbots are already pretty good at not just helping
这样你才能从经验中有所收获，理想情况下，三个多月后，
you finish your current thought, but it'll
这些辅助轮也可以拆掉了。
hand you your second and your third thought and do the assignment for you.
你也能独立完成。
But I think, through prompting, so to speak,
所以，使用 CS50 自有的基于 AI 的软件是合理的，
we'll be able to coax some of our own tools,
它将以 CS50 鸭子的形式出现，现在已经可以使用了——
being computer scientists, ourself, in a direction
我们将在整个学期使用它——在 CS50.ai 上，这是一个基于网络的应用程序，
that you actually find to be the right balance, akin to having
它与 ChatGPT 非常相似，但它
a good tutor by your side 24/7, who doesn't just hand you answers,
具有 CS50 教学助教或 TF 或助教 TA 的个性，
but, indeed, tries to lead you to the same.
它还把自己当做一只鸭子。
So you actually get something out of the experience,
所以你实际上可以从体验中获得一些东西，
and, ideally, three-plus months from now,
而且理想情况下，三个月后，
those training wheels can come off, too.
那些辅助轮也可以卸掉了。
And you're able to still stand on your own.
你也能独立地站起来了。
So it will be reasonable to use CS50's own AI-based software which
所以用CS50自己的基于AI的软件是合理的，它
will actually take the form of a CS50 duck, which is actually available now--
实际上会以CS50鸭子的形式出现，现在已经可以使用了--
and we'll use it throughout the term-- at CS50.ai, a web-based application
我们将在整个学期使用它--在CS50.ai，一个基于网络的应用程序
that's quite similar to ChatGPT, but that
它与ChatGPT非常相似，但是
has the personality of a CS50 teaching fellow or TF, or teaching assistant,
拥有CS50助教或TF或助教的性格，
TA, that also happens to think of itself as a duck.
TA，它还认为自己是一只鸭子。
And for reasons we'll get to in a couple of weeks time,
出于某些原因，我们将在几周后讨论，
but rubber ducks, in particular, are a thing in programming.
但橡胶鸭子，尤其是在编程中，是很有意义的。
But more on that, before long, as you can even see from the one
但很快就会更多，甚至从我桌上的那个就能看到
there on my desk.
就在我的桌子上。
With that said, too, well, I'm going to call out CS50's own Brenda
话说回来，我要点名CS50的布伦达
Anderson, whose daughter, Sophie, kindly not only created
安德森，她的女儿索菲不仅很好心地创造了
the first incarnation, digitally, of this duck, but also,
这个鸭子的第一个数字化的化身，而且还
most recently, once it actually did more than quack a random number
最近，它不再只是对着问题随机嘎嘎叫几次，现在
of times in response to questions, has now
已经
been virtually brought to life, too.
被虚拟地赋予了生命。
So, all that and more, over the coming weeks, but you'll find, ultimately,
所以，在接下来的几周里，所有这些以及更多，你最终会发现，
that the goal is to really bring to life the availability of an AI-based tutor
目标是真正让基于人工智能的导师能够使用
that you have access to, a friend in your--
你就可以使用，一个在你身边的伙伴，
next to you, that will help guide you through a lot of the course's
它会帮助你度过课程中的很多挑战
challenges along the way.
一路上的挑战。
And we actually rolled it out this past summer,
事实上，我们去年夏天就推出了它，
already, with some of your predecessors, through the Harvard Summer School.
已经让你们的前辈们在哈佛暑期学校体验过了。
One student wrote, at summer's end, that this duck
一个学生在暑假结束时写道，这只鸭子
"felt like having a personal tutor--
“感觉就像拥有了一个私人导师——
I love how AI bots will answer questions without ego and without judgment
我喜欢人工智能机器人如何不带任何自负或判断地回答问题
generally entertaining even the stupidest of questions
通常会用有趣的方式回答，即使是最愚蠢的问题
without treating them like they're stupid.
而不像对待蠢问题一样。
It has, as one could expect, an inhuman level of patience."
正如人们所期望的那样，它有着非人的耐心。”
So there's actually something really there because as many teachers
所以，这确实很有用，因为像CS50里那么多的老师
as there are in CS50--
像CS50里那么多——
myself, the course's preceptors, teaching fellows, teaching assistants,
我，课程的导师，助教，教学助理，
and course assistants-- there's only so many of us.
还有课程助理——我们人数有限。
And we're only awake so many hours of the day.
而且我们每天清醒的时间也是有限的。
And I think you'll find, too, that we're on the cusp of something
我想你也会发现，我们正处于一个即将发生巨变的时刻，
pretty remarkable, in the coming years, where
在接下来的几年里，将会发生一些非常了不起的事情，
it's going to get a lot more enabling, now, to learn material
现在学习材料会变得容易很多，
not only within the confines of a class, but on your own, ultimately, as well.
不仅仅局限在课堂上，而且最终还可以自学。
And as one other student put it, at summer's end, with respect to the duck,
另一个学生在暑假结束时，谈到这只鸭子时说：
"Love love loved the duck.
“超级超级喜欢这只鸭子。
We're friends now."
我们现在是朋友了。”
So that, too, awaits.
所以，这也是值得期待的。
But, first, we're going to need to start with the basics.
但是，首先，我们需要从基础开始。
And we started today by talking about binary.
而我们今天从二进制开始讲起。
And darn it, here it is again.
可恶，它又出现了。
So we can't actually get to the point of using, or solving, or implementing AI
所以我们还不能使用、解决或实现人工智能
until we understand this.
直到我们理解了它。
And odds are most of you won't know, at a glance, what this piece of software
大多数人可能一眼就看不出这块软件
does.
是干什么的。
But these are the 0's and 1's that represent, perhaps,
但这些是代表着，也许是
the first program that any programmer writes, which is now a clue to some
每个程序员编写的第一个程序，现在对一些
of you who have dabbled in code before.
之前尝试过编程的人来说是个线索。
What does this pattern of 0's and 1's tell a typical computer to do?
这个0和1的模式指示普通计算机做什么？
Might someone guess?
有人能猜猜吗？
AUDIENCE: "Hello, world."
观众：“Hello, world.”
DAVID J. MALAN: It's going to have it say, "hello, world,"
大卫·J·马兰：它会显示 “Hello, world，”
which is one of the very first programmer-- programs
这是大多数程序员编写的第一个程序。
that most any programmer writes.
大多数程序员都会编写这个程序。
Should you be able to recognize these 0's and 1's?
你应该能识别出这些0和1吗？
Do I recognize these 0's and 1's?
我能识别出这些0和1吗？
No, not at all.
不，一点也认不出来。
I just happen to know that they are the same.
我只是碰巧知道它们是一样的。
And that was a leading question.
而且这是一个诱导性问题。
But they are representing data and instructions, ultimately,
但它们最终代表着数据和指令，
data like H-E-L-L-O, comma, W-O-R-L-D and an instruction like,
数据像 H-E-L-L-O，逗号，W-O-R-L-D 以及像 "打印该数据到屏幕上" 这样的指令
"Print that data to the screen."
"打印该数据到屏幕上"
As for what these patterns of 0's and 1's are,
至于这些 0 和 1 的模式是什么，
this is not something that a computer scientist or programmer worries about.
这不是计算机科学家或程序员所担心的问题。
We just stipulate that, OK, someone, somewhere knows how to do this.
我们只是规定，好吧，某个地方的某个人知道如何做到这一点。
And it's probably someone like Intel, who makes
这很可能就是像英特尔这样的公司，他们生产
the hardware inside of the computers.
计算机里面的硬件。
But you and I, starting now, already, in week zero,
但你和我，从现在开始，已经在第零周，
can start to view binary more abstractly.
可以开始更抽象地看待二进制。
We don't care about the 0's and 1's.
我们不在乎 0 和 1。
We only care that you can use 0's and 1's
我们只关心你可以用 0 和 1
to represent more useful quantities, like numbers,
来表示更有用的量，比如数字，
and letters, colors, and more.
字母、颜色等等。
So this, next week, is going to be the code we actually
所以，下周，这将是我们实际编写的代码。
start writing at a keyboard.
开始用键盘打出来。
And this is that language called C. It's the same language I, myself, learned
这就是叫做 C 的语言。这正是我自己多年前学习的语言，当时学习 CS50 时，我们只学了 C 语言。
years ago, when taking CS50, when all we learned at the time was C.
多年前，学习 CS50 的时候，我们只学了 C 语言。
But this, too, has some crypticness to it.
但这也有点难懂。
And if you've never programmed before, you can probably wrap your mind around,
如果你以前从未编程过，你可能可以理解，
OK, I'm guessing the "printf" prints out the "hello, world."
好吧，我猜 "printf" 打印出 "hello, world"。
But what's with the semicolon, the quotes, the backslash,
但是分号、引号、反斜杠
and the curly braces, the #include, and all of this stupid syntax?
以及花括号、#include 和所有这些愚蠢的语法是什么？
A lot of this, in the beginning of any class, is really a distraction.
在任何课程的开始，很多东西都是真正的干扰。
It is not intellectually interesting.
它在智力上并不有趣。
But it's the stupid kind of stuff that's going to trip you up quite often.
但这些愚蠢的东西会经常让你绊倒。
And so, today, what we'll do is focus not
所以，今天，我们要专注的不是
on syntax, characters on the keyboard, but ideas
语法，键盘上的字符，而是想法
because what really matters in this program
因为在这个程序中真正重要的是
is that "printf" is a function here for our purposes.
"printf" 是一个函数。
And that function is to display information on the screen.
它的功能是在屏幕上显示信息。
Everything else, as we'll soon see, has value
其他所有东西，很快你就会发现，都有价值
and will be understood by you, before long, but for now, it's a distraction.
你很快就会理解，但现在，它只是一个干扰。
Let's focus on those building blocks.
让我们专注于这些构建块。
When it comes time to write code, though, for the curious,
但是，当需要编写代码时，对于好奇的人来说，
especially if you've programmed before, we'll
特别是如果你之前做过编程，我们会
use a very popular free and open-source tool
使用一个非常流行的免费开源工具
called Visual Studio Code, or VS Code.
叫做 Visual Studio Code，或者 VS Code。
We'll use a cloud-based version of it that we pre-install everything
我们会使用它的云端版本，我们预先安装了所有你
you need in the cloud for you so you don't
在云端所需的一切，这样你就不会
have to deal with headaches like getting your Mac or PC to work.
要处理像让你的 Mac 或 PC 工作这样的麻烦事。
You'll use instead this URL, cs50.dev, but more
你将使用这个 URL，cs50.dev，但更多
on that in next week, week one.
关于下周，第一周的内容。
For now, we'll use another cloud-based editor called Scratch.
现在，我们将使用另一个叫做 Scratch 的云端编辑器。
And odds are some number of you use this probably
你们中有些人可能使用过它
as early as like middle school or the like.
早在中学的时候，或者类似的时候。
And that was fine to create your own animations, games,
这很好，用来创建你自己的动画、游戏，
interactive art, or the like.
互动艺术，或者类似的东西。
But we'll use it today for just a bit.
但我们今天只会用它一小会儿。
And we'll use it in the course's first homework,
我们会在课程的第一个作业中使用它，
AKA problem set 0, to explore now some of these same ideas.
也就是问题集 0，来探索现在这些相同的想法。
And among the goals today for the remainder of today
今天，对于今天剩下的时间，我们的目标之一
is not to focus so much on Scratch and the particulars
不是要过分关注 Scratch 和细节
because this is not a language that you're
因为这不是你
going to use often but to give you very visual representations of ideas
经常会用到的语言，而是要给你提供非常直观的概念的表示
so that when things do escalate next week to C, to the more cryptic,
这样，在下周，当事情升级到 C，也就是更加隐晦的语言时，
it's the same ideas just typed out instead of dragged and dropped.
它表达的仍然是同样的概念，只是用打字代替了拖放操作。
So by that, I mean this.
我的意思是这个。
I'm going to go ahead and share in just a moment the user interface of Scratch.
我将在一会儿分享 Scratch 的用户界面。
But what's nice about Scratch is that this
但 Scratch 的优点是，这个
is how we're going to implement that same program today.
是我们今天将要实现相同程序的方式。
These are two blocks or puzzle pieces on the screen,
屏幕上这两个是块或拼图。
and they've been interconnected to tell the computer to say "hello, world"
它们被互连起来，告诉计算机说“hello, world”。
on the screen.
在屏幕上。
The user interface that we're about to use
我们即将使用的用户界面
will look generally something like this.
大体上看起来会像这样。
It's a web-based editor that you can also
这是一个基于 web 的编辑器，你也可以
download it locally to use offline.
本地下载它以便离线使用。
And you'll see that at the left here are a whole bunch of puzzle pieces
你会看到这里左边有很多拼图块
or blocks.
或积木块。
They're categorized by color, and the blue ones
它们按颜色分类，蓝色的那些
tend to relate to motion, for instance.
例如，倾向于与运动相关。
The purple ones represent looks.
紫色的代表外观。
The pink one represents sounds.
粉红色的代表声音。
The yellow one represents events.
黄色的代表事件。
More on that soon.
更多内容很快就会讲到。
The orange ones represent control, and then
橙色的代表控制，然后
there's operators, variables, my blocks, and even some extensions
还有运算符、变量、我的块，甚至一些扩展
we can install as well.
我们也可以安装。
So it just categorizes things visually and colorfully so that you
所以它只是用视觉和颜色对事物进行分类，以便你
can find what you're looking for.
可以找到你想要的东西。
But we're going to use these puzzle pieces to drag and drop them
但我们要使用这些拼图块，将它们拖放到这里。
onto this area here.
在这个区域。
And we're going to connect them when we want them to do something.
当我们想要它们做些什么的时候，我们会将它们连接起来。
What can they do?
它们能做什么？
Well, by default, Scratch comes with this cat here, otherwise known
嗯，默认情况下，Scratch 会附带这只猫，也称为
as a sprite, which is a character in a game or in a graphics context.
精灵，它是游戏或图形环境中的角色。
And this cat lives in this two-dimensional world in which
这只猫生活在这个二维世界中，
the cat can go up, down, left, right.
猫可以上、下、左、右移动。
And you can actually change the cat's costume
你实际上可以改变猫的服装，
to be a dog, a bird, or anything else.
可以是狗、鸟或其他任何东西。
It really is more of an idea than it is a specific animal in this case.
在这种情况下，它更像是一种想法，而不是一种特定的动物。
But the world that Scratch lives in looks a little something like this.
但 Scratch 所处的世界看起来有点像这样。
It's like a Cartesian plane with x-coordinates and y-coordinates.
它就像一个笛卡尔平面，有 x 坐标和 y 坐标。
And the numbers don't so much matter fundamentally,
而数字本身并不那么重要，
except that when you want the cat or any character to go up,
除非你想让猫或任何角色向上移动，
down, left, or right by some amount, it's
向下、向左或向右移动一定的距离，这是
useful to know, for instance, that 0, 0 is the middle, 0 comma 0 for x comma y.
很有用的知识，例如，0, 0 是中间，x, y 为 0, 0。
All the way up is a y value of 180.
一直向上是 y 值为 180。
All the way down is -180.
一直向下是 -180。
All the way to the left is -240.
一直向左是 -240。
All the way to the right is 240.
一直向右是 240。
And generally, you're not going to have to worry about numbers.
通常情况下，你不用担心数字。
You're going to use these relatively-- go right, go left, go up, or down.
你将使用这些相对的——向右、向左、向上或向下。
But that's just the world that Scratch itself lives in here.
但这只是 Scratch 本身存在于这里的环境。
So let's go about using Scratch here.
那么让我们开始使用 Scratch 吧。
I'm going to change over to my cloud-based editor
我将切换到我的基于云的编辑器
here, where I've gone to scratch.mit.edu.
在这里，我已经访问了 scratch.mit.edu。
And I've clicked Create in order to create a project.
我已经点击了“创建”来创建一个项目。
And that gives me this blank canvas here.
这给了我一个空白画布。
And I'm going to do these somewhat quickly because I kind of know
我将很快地完成这些操作，因为我已经知道
what I'm looking for.
我想要什么。
But part of the process with problem set zero is going to be clicking,
但问题集零的一部分将是点击，
and dragging, and sort of scrolling around
拖动，以及滚动浏览
to see what building blocks exist.
看看有哪些积木块。
But I know under Events there's this puzzle piece here
但我知道在“事件”下，这里有这个拼图块
when green flag clicked.
当绿色旗帜被点击时。
Why is that germane?
为什么这很重要？
Well, if I zoom out, and go back to Scratch's world at the right here,
嗯，如果我缩小，回到这里右边 Scratch 的世界，
notice that above Scratch's world there's
注意在 Scratch 世界的上方
a green flag, which is going to mean go, and a red stop sign, which,
有一个绿色旗帜，代表开始，和一个红色的停止标志，它
of course, is going to mean stop.
当然，代表停止。
So if I drag this puzzle piece anywhere into the middle,
所以如果我将这个拼图块拖到中间的任何位置，
it's just going to plop where I put it.
它就会被放置在我放置的位置。
But what that means semantically is when someone clicks that green flag,
但这在语义上意味着，当有人点击那个绿色旗帜时，
I want Scratch the cat to do this other thing.
我希望 Scratch 猫去做别的事情。
Well, what do I want it to do?
嗯，我想要它做什么？
Well, let me go under Looks.
嗯，让我到外观下。
And looks here in purple have some puzzle pieces like this.
外观这里，紫色区域有一些像这样的拼图块。
Well, I can say hello for some number of seconds,
我可以说几秒钟的 "你好"，
or I can just go ahead and say hello.
或者我可以直接说 "你好"。
So let's do that.
那就这样做吧。
I'm going to drag this say block.
我将拖动这个 "说" 块。
And notice that as soon as I get close enough,
注意，当我足够靠近时，
it's going to magnetically want to connect.
它就会磁性地想要连接。
So I can let go, and they snap together automatically
所以我可以松开，它们会自动连接在一起
because they're the right shape.
因为它们是正确的形状。
I don't have to say hello, exclamation point.
我不必说 "你好，感叹号"。
I can change it to the more canonical, hello comma world.
我可以把它改成更标准的 "你好，世界"。
So anything in this white oval is editable
所以这个白色椭圆形内的任何内容都是可编辑的
that you can change as just text there.
你可以直接在那里更改为文本。
If I now zoom out, let me go ahead and click the green flag.
如果我现在缩小，让我点击一下绿色旗帜。
And voila-- this should be my first program in Scratch.
瞧，这应该是我在 Scratch 中的第一个程序。
Hello, world.
你好，世界。
Without any of the distractions of syntax
没有任何语法上的干扰
or weird characters on the screen, it's just done what I want it to do.
或屏幕上的奇怪字符，它只是做了我想让它做的事情。
All right.
好的。
Let me go ahead and click Stop there.
让我点击一下那里的停止按钮。
And let me make it a little more connected
让我把它和我们迄今为止讨论的内容联系起来
to what we've discussed thus far.
更紧密一些。
So this puzzle piece here, say hello, world,
所以这个拼图块，"说你好，世界"，
represents what type of building block using the vocabulary of today?
用今天的词汇来说，它代表了哪种类型的构建块？
So it's a function.
所以它是一个函数。
So these purple blocks are functions, say, hello, world.
所以这些紫色的块是函数，说 "你好，世界"。
And let me give you another piece of terminology.
让我再给你一个术语。
These white ovals that take textual input--
这些接受文本输入的白色椭圆形--
in general, those are called parameters or arguments.
一般来说，它们被称为参数或实参。
And they customize the behavior of a function.
它们自定义了函数的行为。
So a parameter or an argument customizes,
所以参数或实参自定义，
modifies the default behavior of a function, like in this case, say.
修改了函数的默认行为，就像在这种情况下，"说"。
Similarly, in the C code from earlier that we'll see next week,
类似地，在之前我们下周将看到的 C 代码中，
the printf function took a quoted phrase like, hello, world, similarly as input.
printf 函数也以类似的方式接受了一个引用的短语，比如 "你好，世界"，作为输入。
But more on that in the future.
但以后会详细介绍。
So how does this connect to the mental model we presented earlier?
那么这如何与我们之前提出的心理模型联系起来呢？
Well, here's problem-solving as I described it earlier, inputs to outputs
嗯，这里是我之前描述的解决问题的过程，输入到输出
with algorithms or code in the middle.
中间有算法或代码。
Well, what we've got here really is an input of, hello, world, the white oval.
嗯，我们这里实际上有一个输入，"你好，世界"，那个白色椭圆形。
The function or algorithm that it's going into as input is the say block.
作为输入的函数或算法是 "说" 块。
And what is the output of using this say block, the say function?
而使用这个 "说" 块，"说" 函数的输出是什么？
It's the visual effect of having the cat have the little speech bubble appear
它是让猫出现一个小气泡的视觉效果
above its head, saying, hello, world.
在它的头上，说 "你好，世界"。
So everything we do, in fact, can be mapped back
所以我们所做的一切，实际上都可以映射回
to that very simple idea of inputs and outputs.
那个非常简单的输入和输出的概念。
Well, let's make it a little more interesting, though.
好吧，让我们让它更有趣一点吧。
It's a little boring to just say "hello, world" all the time.
一直说 "你好，世界" 有点无聊。
Let me go ahead and drag this away.
让我把它拖走。
And if you just drag it to the left and let go, it gets automatically deleted.
如果你只是把它拖到左边然后松开，它就会自动删除。
Let me go under Sensing in light blue here.
让我到这里的浅蓝色 "感知" 下。
And you'll see there's a bunch of blocks, one of which
你会看到这里有一堆积木，其中一个
is an ask block, an ask function, which is going to prompt
是一个询问块，一个询问函数，它将提示
the human, me, for some input.
人类，也就是我，输入一些内容。
So let me go ahead and drag that over here, and it snaps together.
所以，让我把它拖到这里，它就拼在一起了。
I could change the question, but I'm OK with that question.
我可以改变问题，但我对这个问题没问题。
We'll use what's your name.
我们将使用“你叫什么名字”。
But notice that this block, ask, is a little special.
但请注意，这个块，ask，有点特殊。
It is not just going to display like a speech bubble on the screen.
它不会像屏幕上的气泡一样显示。
It's actually going to return a value, and this is
它实际上将返回一个值，而这就是
another term of art today and onward.
当今及以后的另一个术语。
A return value is some value that can be handed back to you conceptually
返回值是可以在概念上传回给你的值
from a function so that you can do something with it.
来自函数，这样你就可以用它来做些什么。
It's as though the ask function asks someone for their name,
就像询问函数询问某人的名字一样，
writes it down on a piece of paper, and hands you the piece of paper.
写在一张纸上，然后把纸递给你。
You can do anything now that you want with that name.
你现在可以用那个名字做任何你想做的事情。
And here is how you access the name in this special block called
而你可以在这个特殊的块中访问这个名字，它叫做
answer, which, again, will start calling a return value.
answer，它将再次开始调用返回值。
So if I want to say "hello" to someone specific, I'm going to do this.
所以，如果我想对某个人说“你好”，我会这样做。
Let me zoom out.
让我放大一点。
Let me go back to Looks, and let me go back to Say.
让我回到Looks，再回到Say。
And I'm going to change the say block here to "hello, comma."
我将在这里把say块改成“hello，逗号”。
Then I'm going to zoom out.
然后，我将放大一点。
Well, I need two inputs, I think.
我想我需要两个输入。
So I'm going to grab another say block, and I'm going to put it below.
所以我将抓取另一个say块，把它放在下面。
And I could just type "David," but this is
我可以直接输入“David”，但这样做
going to defeat the whole point of asking me for the name.
就失去了询问我名字的意义。
And it will only work for me.
而且它只对我有效。
So I don't want to do that.
所以我不想要那样做。
So let me go back to Sensing, and notice the shape is important here.
所以，让我回到Sensing，请注意形状在这里很重要。
Even if it's not quite the same size, the shape matters.
即使它不是完全相同的大小，形状也很重要。
And I can actually drag this and change the input of this say function
我实际上可以拖动它并改变这个say函数的输入
to be whatever that return value is, that piece of paper
为那个返回值，那张纸
that has the person's name on it.
上面写着人的名字。
And it grows to fill, but now we have a program
它会一直填满，但现在我们有一个程序
that I think when I click the green flag-- watch-- is going to prompt me.
我想当我点击绿色旗帜时--看--它会提示我。
What's your name?
你叫什么名字？
And now I have room to type down here.
现在我有空间在下面输入。
So I'm going to type D-A-V-I-D. I'm going to hit Enter,
所以我会输入D-A-V-I-D。我会按下回车，
and it should say "hello, Dave."
它应该会说“hello，Dave”。
Wait.
等等。
Hmm.
嗯。
Huh.
Maybe it was-- didn't work.
也许是--没用。
D-A-V-I-D. Here we go.
D-A-V-I-D。来吧。
Hello, David.
你好，David。
Hmm.
嗯。
It's missing the hello, but I'm quite sure we have a hello right there.
它缺少hello，但我敢肯定我们有hello。
So what explains this bug or mistake?
那么，是什么导致了这个错误呢？
Yeah.
对。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
观众：[听不清]
So they overlap.
所以它们重叠了。
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
DAVID J. MALAN：没错。
Put another way, my Mac, my PC, it's just so darn
换句话说，我的Mac，我的PC，它太快了
fast that it did exactly what it was supposed to.
快到它完全按预期执行了。
But it said "hello, David" so fast that we didn't even see, we being the human,
但它说“hello，David”的速度太快，我们，也就是人类，
the slowest part of the puzzle, see the actual hello.
这道谜题中最慢的部分，甚至没有看到真正的hello。
So there's a few different ways to fix this, as you know.
所以，你可能知道，有几种不同的方法可以修复它。
We could have it say "hello" for some number of seconds.
我们可以让它说“hello”几秒钟。
So I could kind of do that.
所以，我可以那样做。
So let me do this.
所以，让我这样做。
I can decouple these by just dragging and letting it go
我可以通过拖动并释放它们来分离它们
so that they're magnetically far apart.
让它们在磁性上相距很远。
Let me go ahead and drag this one, say hello for two seconds.
让我把这个拖过去，说两秒钟的hello。
I'm going to change the grammar here to be hello comma again.
我要在这里把语法改成“hello, again”。
I'm going to go ahead and disconnect these two.
我要继续把这两个断开。
I'm going to throw away the old one that I don't want to use.
我要丢弃那个我不想要的旧的。
And I'm going to reconnect this so that now--
我要重新连接它，这样现在--
OK.
好的。
It's going to say hello for two seconds and then my name, hopefully.
它将先说“hello”两秒，然后是我的名字，希望可以成功。
So let me click Stop and Start.
所以让我点击“停止”和“开始”。
D-A-V-I-D. Enter.
D-A-V-I-D，回车。
OK.
好的。
So it's better, but it's kind of poorly implemented.
所以它更好，但是实现得有点糟糕。
Like, come on.
拜托。
I just wanted to say hello comma David.
我只是想说“hello, David”。
Why is that hard?
为什么这么难？
Well, maybe we can actually combine these a little differently.
嗯，也许我们可以用不同的方式将它们组合起来。
And let me propose this.
我来提议一下。
Let me actually get rid of these blocks again.
让我再次去掉这些块。
And let me go ahead and just say one thing.
让我继续说一件事。
But can I somehow combine this to say hello comma David all in one breath?
但是我能不能以某种方式将它组合起来，一口气说“hello, David”？
Well, it turns out if I go under Operators,
好吧，结果是，如果我进入“运算符”，
I know from having played with this before that there's this puzzle
我之前玩过这个，我知道这里有一个拼图
piece down here called join.
块叫做“join”。
It's an oval.
它是一个椭圆形。
It's a little big, but, again, it will grow to fill.
它有点大，但同样，它会长大到填满。
And by default, it wants to join two words, "apple" and "banana."
默认情况下，它想将两个词“apple”和“banana”连接起来。
But those are just placeholders.
但它们只是占位符。
So let me go ahead and drag this over the default hello.
所以让我继续将它拖到默认的“hello”上面。
Let me change "apple" to hello comma space and then banana.
让我将“apple”改为“hello, ”，然后是“banana”。
Let me go back to Sensing.
让我回到“感知”。
Let me grab answer and drag and drop that.
让我抓取“答案”，并将它拖放。
So now notice that I'm kind of layering my ideas.
所以现在请注意，我正在将我的想法分层。
And put another way, the output of this join block
换句话说，这个“join”块的输出
is presumably going to join two things together,
应该是将两件事连接在一起，
apple and banana or hello comma David.
“apple”和“banana”，或者“hello, David”。
And then the output of join is going to become the input to say.
然后，“join”的输出将成为“say”的输入。
So aesthetically, it just looks better.
所以从美学上看，它看起来更好。
It's still correct, but it's just better.
它仍然是正确的，但它只是更好。
So if I type "David," and hit Enter, hello, David.
所以，如果我输入“David”，然后按回车，就会说“hello, David”。
This is what a normal program would presumably
这应该是正常程序
do, not show you part of the phrase and then the rest of the phrase.
做的，而不是先显示部分短语，然后显示其余短语。
Like, it's just better in this way.
就像，用这种方式更好。
So let's connect this now to this same puzzle piece and this methodology.
所以现在让我们将它连接到这个相同的拼图块和这种方法。
So here's that same puzzle piece, ask.
所以，这是同一个拼图块，“ask”。
How do we fit it into this input and output flow with algorithms?
我们如何用算法将它放入这个输入和输出流中？
Well, the input to that puzzle piece is something like, what's your name,
好吧，那个拼图块的输入类似于“你的名字是什么”，
question mark.
问号。
Then the algorithm or the code implementation thereof
然后算法或其代码实现
is this ask block and wait so the human has a moment to type their response in.
是这个“ask”块和“wait”，这样人类就有时间输入他们的响应。
The output of that function recall is a return value.
那个函数调用的输出是一个返回值。
You don't see anything on the screen by default because we've not used say yet,
默认情况下，你没有看到屏幕上显示任何东西，因为我们还没有使用“say”，
but we get this return value.
但是我们得到了这个返回值。
And let me scooch everything over now so that we can now
让我现在把所有东西都移过去，这样我们现在就可以
join those inputs together.
将那些输入连接在一起。
So here's this puzzle piece.
所以，这是这个拼图块。
Let me go ahead and propose that the inputs now to the join block
让我继续提议，现在“join”块的输入
are two arguments or two parameters, so to speak, hello and answer.
是两个参数，可以这么说，“hello”和“answer”。
They go into that join puzzle piece, whose purpose in life
它们进入那个“join”拼图块，它的生命目标
is to return one joined version thereof.
是返回一个连接的版本。
Let me slide this all over logically now so
让我现在从逻辑上将它全部滑过去，这样
that now that output becomes the input to the say block
现在那个输出成为“say”块的输入，
and now is why the cat has the speech bubble saying all at once,
现在，这就是为什么猫的对话框里会同时说“hello, David”。
hello comma David.
“hello, David”。
So what we've done here is kind of composed the output
所以我们在这里所做的是将输出组合起来
and from one function into the input of another.
并将一个函数的输出作为另一个函数的输入。
And you can think of this in a couple of different ways,
你可以用几种不同的方式来思考这一点，
left to right, as I did there, or kind of
从左到右，就像我之前做的那样，或者像
like stacking these things on top of one another.
把这些东西堆叠在一起。
But at the end of the day, even as programming
但归根结底，即使编程
gets more and more powerful for us, it's just inputs and outputs, inputs
变得越来越强大，它也仅仅只是输入和输出，输入
and outputs.
和输出。
And thankfully, with built-in functionality from our friends
幸运的是，得益于我们来自麻省理工学院的朋友们
at MIT who designed Scratch, I can even do something playful like this.
设计了Scratch，我甚至可以做一些像这样有趣的事情。
I can go to that Extensions button at the bottom.
我可以点击底部那个“扩展”按钮。
And there's a lot of fancy things I can add here, like text-to-speech.
这里有很多我可以添加的有趣功能，比如文本转语音。
So let me go ahead and choose text-to-speech.
所以，让我来选择文本转语音功能。
And let me go ahead here and change the say block in purple.
让我来更改一下这个紫色“说”块。
Let me get rid of the say block, and let me borrow this.
让我去掉这个“说”块，并借用这个。
Let me get the speak block like this.
让我得到这个“说”块，就像这样。
And now let me drag and drop this oval.
现在让我拖放这个椭圆形。
It's going to grow to fill.
它会逐渐填满。
And I think it's just about to be a little more interesting.
我认为它马上就会变得更有趣了。
Let me click Play now, and hopefully this isn't too loud.
我现在点击播放，希望声音不要太大。
D-A-V-I-D. Enter.
D-A-V-I-D. 回车。
SPEAKER: Hello, David.
音箱：你好，大卫。
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
大卫·J·马兰：好的。
[APPLAUSE]
[鼓掌]
Thank you.
谢谢。
That's a low bar.
这太简单了。
[CHUCKLES] Let me go ahead and set the voice too.
[笑声]让我来设置一下声音。
And you might now remember how we began class, where
你可能还记得我们上课一开始的时候，我们
we had a robotic, computerized voice.
用了一个机械的、电脑化的声音。
Well, we didn't use Scratch at the time, but we could change this in Scratch
嗯，我们当时没有使用Scratch，但我们可以在Scratch中更改这一点
alone to be a little different.
让它稍微有些不同。
So D-A-V-I-D.
所以 D-A-V-I-D。
SPEAKER: Hello, David.
音箱：你好，大卫。
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
大卫·J·马兰：好的。
Little creepy, but we can play all day long with that.
有点令人毛骨悚然，但我们可以整天玩这个。
But the point is that these functions are just
但重点是这些函数只是
now doing something a little different.
现在做了一些稍微不同的事情。
But it's just these inputs and outputs.
但它仅仅只是这些输入和输出。
Well, let's make the cat more like a cat.
好吧，让我们让这只猫更像一只猫。
Let me go ahead and throw away all of this asking question stuff.
让我把所有这些问问题的部分都扔掉。
Let me go up to Sound, and let me go ahead
让我向上滑动到“声音”，然后
and drag the play sound meow until done.
拖放“播放声音喵”块直到完成。
And here too it comes with meow.
这里也带了“喵”的声音。
You can add your own sounds as well.
你也可以添加自己的声音。
But I'm just going to use the default meow and here too.
但我只会使用默认的“喵”声音，在这里也是。
Hopefully, this won't be too loud.
希望声音不要太大。
Let's make the cat meow by clicking Play.
让我们点击“播放”让这只猫叫。
[MEOWING]
[猫叫声]
OK.
好的。
It's a little piercing, but it's cute.
有点刺耳，但很可爱。
And if I want the cat to meow twice, I could just play the game twice.
如果我想让这只猫叫两次，我可以玩两次游戏。
[MEOWING]
[猫叫声]
All right.
好的。
But it would be nice to just get it to meow automatically two, or three,
但如果它能自动叫两声、三声，或者更多，那就太好了
or more times.
或者更多次。
So you know what I could do?
所以你知道我可以做什么吗？
I could just drag a second one of these.
我可以再拖放一个。
Actually, you know what?
实际上，你知道吗？
I could even just right-click or Control-click and duplicate them.
我甚至可以右键单击或按住Control键并单击以复制它们。
But I'll just keep dragging and dropping.
但我还是会继续拖放。
There's different ways to solve problems.
解决问题的方法有很多。
And now let me click Play.
现在让我点击播放。
[MEOWING]
[猫叫声]
OK.
好的。
Cat does not sound particularly happy.
这只猫听起来并不高兴。
So we could go under--
所以我们可以到下面去--
how about Control?
控制怎么样？
We could wait one second.
我们可以等一秒钟。
Now, there's no room, but it will sort of expand to give room for me.
现在，没有空间，但它会扩展以腾出空间给我。
So let me try this.
所以让我试试这个。
And now it's going to wait one second in between meows.
现在它将在每次喵叫之间等待一秒钟。
[MEOWING]
[喵叫声]
OK.
好的。
Let me stipulate that is correct.
让我声明这是正确的。
If my goal is to get the cat to meow three times, it meowed three times.
如果我的目标是让猫喵叫三次，它喵叫了三次。
But per our discussion earlier of algorithms and the design thereof,
但是根据我们之前关于算法及其设计的讨论，
this is not the best design.
这不是最好的设计。
[MEOWING]
[喵叫声]
OK?
好吗？
[LAUGHTER]
[笑声]
Thank you for playing along at home.
感谢你在家参与。
Yeah.
是啊。
In what sense is this arguably not well-designed?
从某种意义上来说，这为什么可以说是设计不好的呢？
Yeah.
是啊。
AUDIENCE: You repeated yourself.
观众：你重复了自己。
DAVID J. MALAN: I repeated myself, which actually in programming
大卫·马兰：我重复了自己，实际上在编程中
tends not to be a good thing.
往往不是一件好事。
Now, it was easy.
现在，这很简单。
I almost resorted to copy-paste, which saves me time upfront.
我几乎要使用复制粘贴，这可以节省我最初的时间。
But just imagine a contrived scenario.
但想象一下一个人为制造的场景。
Now, what if I want it to wait like two seconds in between?
现在，如果我想让它在每次喵叫之间等待两秒钟呢？
All right.
好吧。
It's not that big a deal.
这不是什么大不了的事。
I change it here, and I change it here.
我在这里更改，在这里更改。
But what if the program is meant to meow 10 times?
但如果程序要让猫喵叫10次呢？
Then I have to change it here, and here, and here, and here, and here.
那么我必须在这里更改，在这里更改，在这里更改，在这里更改，在这里更改。
And eventually I'm going to screw up.
最终我会搞砸的。
Humans are fallible.
人类是会犯错的。
I'm going to overlook one of them.
我会忽略其中一个。
One time, it's going to be one second.
有一次，它会是一秒钟。
Another is going to be two, and just stupid things will happen.
另一次将会是两秒钟，就会发生一些愚蠢的事情。
You're setting yourself up for failure if you design things poorly.
如果你设计的东西很糟糕，你就是在为失败埋下伏笔。
And so I would propose that we use another type of building block
所以，我建议我们使用另一种类型的构建块
to solve this instead.
来解决这个问题。
Yeah.
是啊。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
大卫·马兰：是啊。
So we could use a loop and just write minimal code
所以我们可以使用循环，只编写最少的代码
but to accomplish even more functionality.
但要实现更多功能。
So let me throw away most of these blocks.
所以，让我扔掉大多数块。
And let's go and grab this repeat block, which we haven't used yet,
然后我们去抓取这个重复块，我们还没用过，
but it's right there.
但它就在那里。
And as the name suggests, this will allow
顾名思义，这将允许
me to repeat something some number of times.
我多次重复某件事。
Let me put these two puzzle pieces inside.
让我把这两块拼图放在里面。
It'll grow to fill.
它会长大以填满。
Let me reconnect it to the green flag.
让我把它重新连接到绿色旗帜上。
I'll change the default 10 to a 3.
我会把默认的10改为3。
And now--
现在--
[MEOWING]
[喵叫声]
It's just sort of better because if now you want it to meow more times,
它只是更好，因为如果你现在想要它喵叫更多次，
you change it one place.
你只需要更改一个地方。
If you want it to slow down, you change it in one place.
如果你想让它慢下来，你只需要更改一个地方。
There's no room for error.
没有出错的余地。
And that's generally a good thing.
这通常是一件好事。
But this is silly.
但这很荒谬。
Like, Scratch comes with a cat.
比如，Scratch自带一只猫。
Why didn't MIT give us a puzzle piece called "meow?"
为什么麻省理工学院没有给我们一块叫做“喵”的拼图呢？
Like, why am I implementing the idea of meowing myself?
比如，为什么是我自己来实现喵叫的想法呢？
Like, that took me what?
比如，那花了我多长时间？
1, 2, 3, 4 puzzle pieces.
1、2、3、4块拼图。
Why isn't there just one puzzle piece that meows for me?
为什么没有一块拼图能帮我喵叫呢？
This too we can do in code, be it in Scratch, or C, or other languages too.
这在代码中也可以做到，无论是Scratch、C语言还是其他语言。
I'm going to go down to these pink my blocks here,
我要到这些粉红色的“我的积木”块这里，
where I can create my own puzzle piece.
在那里我可以创建我自己的拼图块。
And I'm going to call this literally "meow."
我将把它命名为“喵”。
And I'm going to go ahead and just click OK.
我将点击确定。
And notice that it's given me this new type of start connector.
请注意，它给了我这种新型的起始连接器。
It's a start puzzle piece that nothing goes above it.
这是一个起始拼图，上面不能放任何东西。
But you can put anything you want below it.
但你可以在下面放置任何你想要的东西。
And I'm going to go ahead and cheat here.
我要在这里作弊一下。
I'm just going to grab my existing code, so to speak.
我将直接获取现有的代码。
This is code I'm writing, even though it's puzzle pieces.
这是我编写的代码，即使它是由拼图块组成的。
And now let me just claim, and I'll move this aside.
现在，我要声明，然后把这个移到一边。
Here is now an implementation of my own function,
现在，这是我自己的函数实现，
my own block called "meow," whose purpose in life
我自己的名为“喵”的模块，其存在的意义
is to meow until done and then wait one second.
就是一直喵，直到完成，然后等待一秒钟。
But what's powerful now is notice at top left, now that I've made the block,
但现在强大的地方是，请注意左上角，现在我已经创建了这个模块，
I can use it any number of times.
我可以使用它任意多次。
So I can grab this meow block, drag it over here, and you know what?
所以我可以抓住这个“喵”模块，把它拖到这里，你知道吗？
Now that "meow" exists as an idea, I can abstract that away.
现在“喵”作为一种概念存在了，我可以把它抽象出来。
And I'm just going to arbitrarily drag it way to the bottom.
我要随意地把它拖到最底部。
I'm not deleting it.
我没有删除它。
I'm just putting it out of sight, out of mind so
我只是把它隐藏起来，不再想它，以便
that we can focus now on this idea.
我们可以专注于这个概念。
And I claim that this implementation of meowing
我声称，这种“喵”的实现
is sort of better because it's more compact, it does what it says,
在某种程度上更好，因为它更简洁，它做到了它所说的，
and I don't care about the implementation details of "meow."
而且我不关心“喵”的具体实现细节。
So this idea of abstraction, something we're going to use frequently.
所以这种抽象的概念，我们会经常用到。
To abstract something away is to simplify.
抽象化就是简化。
Don't think about the underlying implementation details.
不要考虑底层的实现细节。
Just care about what it does or what it's called.
只要关心它做什么或者它叫什么名字。
Someone has to care about the implementation details,
总有人需要关心实现细节，
like me 30 seconds ago.
就像我30秒前一样。
But here on out, I don't need to care.
但从现在开始，我不需要关心了。
And so in fact, you and I are using the abstraction
事实上，你和我都在使用抽象
that is Scratch because I don't know how to put a speech bubble on the screen.
就是Scratch，因为我不知道如何在屏幕上放置一个对话框。
I don't know how to create that sound, meow.
我不知道如何创建那个声音，“喵”。
MIT did that, and they abstracted those pieces
麻省理工学院做到了，他们将这些部分抽象出来
of functionality away already for us by just giving us
让我们可以直接使用这些功能，通过简单地提供给我们
these puzzle pieces we see here.
这些我们看到的拼图块。
So the code will work the exact same.
所以代码将以完全相同的方式工作。
[MEOWING]
[喵叫声]
But it's sort of better designed now because now I've
但现在设计得更好了，因为现在我已经
abstracted away the idea of meowing.
将“喵”的概念抽象出来了。
But I bet I can improve this further.
但我相信我可以进一步改进。
Can I get rid of the repeat block altogether?
我可以完全删除“重复”模块吗？
And let me just tell the meow block how many times to meow.
然后我可以直接告诉“喵”模块要喵多少次。
Well, let me go down to the bottom and look at the implementation details.
好吧，我将移到底部查看实现细节。
I'm going to right-click or Control-click on this,
我将右键单击或使用Ctrl键单击它，
and I'm going to edit it.
然后我会编辑它。
So I'm going to make a change.
我要做一些改变。
And I didn't do this before, but I'm going to call it "meow," as before.
以前我没有这样做，但我要像以前一样把它命名为“喵”。
I'm going to add an input.
我要添加一个输入。
And just so I know what it says what it does,
为了让我知道它做什么，
I'm going to add the word "times" here.
我要在这里添加单词“次数”。
And I'm going to change this placeholder to n.
我要将这个占位符改为n。
n for "number" is the go-to placeholder any time
n 代表“数字”，是我们在计算机科学中谈论数字时常用的占位符。
we want to talk about a number in CS.
我们想要谈论计算机科学中的数字。
So now notice the puzzle piece looks a little different.
所以现在请注意，这个拼图块看起来有点不同。
It takes an argument or a parameter called
它接受一个参数，称为
n, which represents the number of times you want the thing to meow.
n，它代表你想让它喵的次数。
Now, that doesn't do that yet.
现在，它还没有这样做。
So let me go back to my other code.
所以，让我回到我的另一段代码。
Let me just decouple these temporarily.
让我暂时将它们分离。
I'm going to move my loop into my implementation of meowing.
我要将我的循环移动到“喵喵叫”的实现中。
But I don't want to hard code, that is literally write the number 3 anymore.
但我不想硬编码，也就是说不再直接写数字 3。
I'm going to grab this oval and put it there.
我要抓住这个椭圆形并把它放在那里。
So now I've generalized the function.
现在我已经将函数泛化了。
So now it will meow any number of times, 0 on up, by executing that loop
现在它可以通过执行循环来喵任意次数，从 0 次开始。
and now more powerfully.
现在更强大。
Out of sight, out of mind.
眼不见心不烦。
Notice that my code just became so darn simple.
注意我的代码变得如此简单。
Like, my function is called "meow."
比如，我的函数叫做“喵喵叫”。
It meows some number of times.
它会喵一些次数。
All I have to do is type a number there, and it just works.
我只需要在那里输入一个数字，它就会工作。
And I don't care any more about those lower-level, so to speak,
我不再关心那些更低级的，可以这么说，
implementation details.
实现细节。
So here, no surprise.
所以这里，不出所料。
If I type in the number 3, zoom out, and hit Play--
如果我在那里输入数字 3，缩小画面并点击播放 -
[MEOWING]
[喵喵叫]
--it still works just fine.
- 它仍然可以正常工作。
So any questions on what we've just done here?
那么，关于我们刚刚做的事情，有任何问题吗？
It's still just meowing, but that's besides the point.
它仍然只是在喵喵叫，但这并不重要。
It's this creation of our own functions, this modularity,
这是我们自己创建函数、模块化，
this abstraction that's going to be the idea that keeps coming back to us.
这种抽象，将是我们反复出现的概念。
No?
没有？
All right.
好的。
So let's make this a little more cat-like.
让我们让它更像猫一点。
Let me throw away all of this code.
让我把所有这些代码扔掉。
And let me go ahead--
让我先 -
oops-- let me throw away this code first and then the rest of this code.
糟糕 - 让我先把这段代码扔掉，然后再扔掉剩下的代码。
And let me go ahead and give myself another green flag block.
让我再给自己添加一个绿色旗帜块。
And let me go ahead, and let's create a cat that allows us to pet it
让我继续，让我们创建一个猫，让我们可以抚摸它
by moving my cursor over the cat.
通过将我的鼠标悬停在猫上面。
And maybe it likes that, so it'll meow when I do that.
也许它喜欢这样，所以我这样做的时候它会喵喵叫。
So let me go under Control, and let me grab this if conditional,
让我进入“控制”模块，然后抓住这个“如果”条件语句，
which we talked about as a building block earlier.
我们之前说过它是基础构建块。
Let me go to Sensing, and we haven't used this before.
让我进入“感测”模块，我们以前没有使用过它。
But here is a weird sort of diagonal shape
但是这里有一个奇怪的斜形
that says touching mouse pointer question mark.
它表示“是否触碰鼠标指针”。
So that's a Boolean expression.
所以这是一个布尔表达式。
So I'm going to drag that, and it's definitely the wrong size.
所以我将把它拖动，它的大小肯定不对。
But it is the right shape, so it will grow to fill.
但它的形状是正确的，所以它会自动扩展。
And the question I want to ask is if the cat is touching the mouse pointer,
我想问的问题是，如果猫触碰了鼠标指针，
then go ahead and meow happily.
就让它开心地喵喵叫。
So let me grab the meow sound, put it in there.
让我抓住“喵喵叫”声音，把它放在那里。
And so I think when I click the green flag to start the program,
所以我想，当我点击绿色旗帜启动程序，
and now I let the mouse pointer touch the cat, we should hear--
现在我让鼠标指针触碰猫，我们应该听到 -
huh.
嗯。
Doesn't seem to be working.
好像没有起作用。
There's a bug or a mistake in this program too.
这个程序里也有个错误或者错误。
What did I do wrong?
我哪里做错了？
Yeah.
是的。
AUDIENCE: You didn't specify the sprite [INAUDIBLE]..
观众：你没有明确指定精灵[听不清]。
DAVID J. MALAN: I don't need to specify the sprite explicitly
大卫·J·马兰：我不需要明确指定精灵
because a detail I didn't discuss earlier.
因为我之前没有讨论过一个细节。
In the bottom right of the screen, notice
在屏幕的右下角，注意
that the cat is already selected.
猫已经被选中了。
So this code relates to that cat.
所以这段代码是针对那只猫的。
So your instinct is good if we had two or more sprites,
所以，如果我们有两个或更多精灵，你的直觉是对的，
but I just have one, so I'm covered there.
但我只有一只猫，所以这里不用担心。
Other thoughts.
其他想法。
Yeah.
是的。
AUDIENCE: It only checks once.
观众：它只检查一次。
DAVID J. MALAN: It only checks?
大卫·J·马兰：它只检查？
AUDIENCE: Once.
观众：一次。
DAVID J. MALAN: Once.
大卫·J·马兰：一次。
So I click the green flag.
所以，我点击绿色旗帜。
The computer did what I told it to do.
计算机做了我告诉它做的事。
The mouse pointer was not touching the cat at that moment
此时此刻，鼠标指针没有触碰猫咪
because it was touching the green flag.
因为它正在触碰绿色旗帜。
So, of course, it didn't meow.
所以，当然，它没有喵喵叫。
So what maybe is the fix here?
那么，这里可能有什么解决方法？
What puzzle piece can we add?
我们可以添加什么拼图块？
AUDIENCE: After the green flag is [INAUDIBLE]..
观众：在绿色旗帜[听不清]之后…
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
大卫·J·马兰：好的。
OK.
好的。
Interesting solution.
有趣的解决方案。
So let me go ahead, and under Control let me grab a-- wait one second.
所以让我继续，在控制下，让我抓一个 - 等一下。
I'm going to change the 1 to 5, and now I'm going to click the green flag.
我要把 1 改成 5，现在我要点击绿色旗帜。
So here we go.
所以，我们开始吧。
1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5。
Damn it.
该死。
[MEOWING]
[喵喵叫]
OK.
好的。
That was yours, not mine.
那是你的，不是我的。
[LAUGHTER]
[笑声]
It didn't work.
它不起作用。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID J. MALAN: Sorry?
大卫·J·马兰：抱歉？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, maybe forever.
大卫·J·马兰：哦，也许永远。
So your approach would work, but it's very much a hack, if you will.
所以你的方法可以，但它很像一个技巧，如果你愿意。
Like, I would have to time it perfectly so that the mouse pointer is touching
就像，我必须完美地计时，以便鼠标指针接触
it, or, conversely, I have to drag it there and just
它，或者反过来，我必须把它拖到那里，然后就
leave it there for five seconds.
把它放在那里五秒钟。
And that's a little weird because you don't just touch a cat
这有点奇怪，因为你不会只是碰一只猫
and then five seconds later it meows at you.
然后五秒钟后它向你喵喵叫。
Like, presumably, we want it to be more interactive.
就像，我们可能希望它更具互动性。
So I like this idea of a loop.
所以我喜欢循环的想法。
Right?
对吧？
Why don't we just tell the cat to forever listen for the cursor
为什么我们不直接告诉猫咪永远监听光标
as by using not repeat but forever?
通过使用不是重复而是永远？
Let me move this in here.
让我把它移到这儿。
So now the cat's going to be told when the green flag is clicked just forever,
所以现在当绿色旗帜被点击时，猫咪将被告知永远，
if touching, if touching, if touching.
如果触碰，如果触碰，如果触碰。
Oh, meow when actually touched.
哦，当实际触碰时喵喵叫。
So now if I zoom out and hit Play, nothing's happening.
所以现在如果我缩小并点击播放，什么也不会发生。
I don't have to wait any number of seconds.
我不必等待任何秒数。
But when I do touch the cat--
但当我触碰猫咪时 -
[MEOWING]
[喵喵叫]
[APPLAUSE]
[鼓掌]
[CHUCKLES] Fan section here.
[轻笑] 这里的粉丝区。
Thank you.
谢谢。
[MEOWING]
[喵喵叫]
So now it's actually working quite well.
所以现在它实际上运行良好。
So there we have sort of a logical bug.
所以我们这里有点逻辑错误。
But it does make sense if you think about what it was
但如果你想想它是什么
you told the computer to actually do.
你告诉计算机实际做的事情。
Well, let's make things even more interesting
好吧，让我们让事情更有趣
by using one of these extensions.
通过使用其中一个扩展。
In this bottom left corner, this is how I got to text-to-speech earlier.
在这个左下角，这是我之前如何获得文本到语音的。
Let me go to Video Sensing over here too.
让我也去这里看看视频感应。
And I can actually-- there we go-- literally, the video has come on.
我实际上可以 - 瞧 - 实际上，视频已经开始了。
Let me go ahead and do this.
让我继续做这个。
Get rid of this code, and let me step out of the frame.
去掉这段代码，让我走出画面。
When video motion is greater than--
当视频运动大于 -
well, this is CS50, so let's just type in 50,
好吧，这是 CS50，所以让我们只输入 50，
which is just a measure of motion.
这只是一个运动的度量。
Let me go and play sound meow.
让我去播放声音喵喵叫。
OK.
好的。
And let me stop and restart.
让我停止并重新开始。
All right.
好的。
So there's the cat.
所以，这就是那只猫。
[MEOWING]
[喵喵叫]
OK.
好的。
It worked.
它奏效了。
The cat's a little insensitive.
这只猫有点迟钝。
[MEOWING]
[喵喵叫]
There we go.
我们去。
Actually, you know what?
实际上，你知道吗？
Maybe it's just-- let me put-- let's change it.
也许是，让我放一下，让我们改变它。
20.
Oh, my God.
哦，我的天哪。
Oh, that's OK.
哦，没事。
[MEOWING]
[喵喵叫]
There we go.
好了。
All right.
好的。
There we go.
好了。
So now it's a little more sensitive to the petting by using the camera.
所以现在通过使用摄像头，它对抚摸更敏感了。
Now, this is kind of a weird example.
现在，这是一个有点奇怪的例子。
And if I just start moving around crazily, like,
如果我开始疯狂地四处移动，就像，
it's just going to meow incessantly, which was what was happening--
它就会不停地喵喵叫，这就是之前发生的事情。
[MEOWING]
[喵喵叫]
Stop.
停。
[LAUGHTER]
[笑声]
OK.
好的。
When in doubt, this is when you reload the page.
有疑问时，这就是你重新加载页面的时机。
[LAUGHTER]
[笑声]
All right.
好的。
So now we're back to where we wanted to be.
所以现在我们回到了我们想要的地方。
But where can we now use these kinds of building blocks?
但是现在我们可以在哪里使用这些积木？
Like, we were doing such tiny little programs.
比如，我们正在做非常小的程序。
But even that we could turn into a whole game, I bet.
但我敢打赌，即使那样我们也能把它变成一个完整的游戏。
Could we get like one volunteer to come on up?
我们能找一位志愿者上来吗？
One volunteer?
一位志愿者？
Everyone's looking down.
大家都在低头看。
OK.
好的。
On the end here.
这边。
Come on down.
下来吧。
Yeah.
好。
All right.
好的。
Round of applause for our one brave volunteer here.
让我们为我们这位勇敢的志愿者鼓掌。
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
All right.
好的。
These Super Mario cookies are on the line for you,
这些超级玛丽饼干就等着你，
depending on how this goes.
取决于事情进展如何。
So I'm going to have you come over here.
所以我让你过来这里。
And in advance on Scratch's website, we have some pre-made games,
在 Scratch 网站上，我们提前准备了一些游戏，
one of them written by one of your predecessors, a former student,
其中一个是由你的前辈，一位前学生写的，
that they implemented this sort of "Whac-A-Mole" game.
他们实现了一种类似“打地鼠”的游戏。
So what you're about to see is the camera turn on on you.
所以你即将看到摄像头对着你打开。
And you're going to see four moles above, below, left, and right.
你会看到四个地鼠，分别在上方，下方，左方和右方。
And using only your head--
只需使用你的头。
up, down, left, right-- the goal is to whack a mole
上下左右，目标是打地鼠
to get a point every time your head touches one of these sprites.
每次你的头碰到这些精灵，你就能获得一分。
So you're about to see things get very interesting very quickly.
所以你将看到事情很快就会变得非常有趣。
But using these building blocks, just those simple
但使用这些积木，仅仅是那些简单的
blocks but have four sprites, not four cats but four moles in this case.
积木，但有四个精灵，不是四只猫，而是四个地鼠。
We can actually turn these into actual games.
我们实际上可以把这些变成真正的游戏。
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[音乐播放]
So here we go.
好了，开始吧。
Click Beginner.
点击初学者。
OK.
好的。
And we just need you to center your head first.
我们只需要你先把头放在正中间。
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[音乐播放]
[INDISTINCT CHATTER]
[模糊的聊天声]
[CHUCKLES]
[轻笑]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[音乐播放]
Nice.
不错。
Ten seconds.
十秒。
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[音乐播放]
Nice.
不错。
Two seconds.
两秒。
AUDIENCE: [LAUGHS]
观众：[笑声]
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
大卫·马兰：好的。
A round of applause.
让我们鼓掌。
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
Thank you.
谢谢。
You want to introduce yourself?
你想介绍一下自己吗？
AUDIENCE: Hi, everybody.
观众：大家好。
My name is [? Vanilla. ?] I'm a first year,
我的名字是[？香草。？]我是一年级，
and I'm going to be majoring in computer science and economics.
我将主修计算机科学和经济学。
DAVID J. MALAN: Nice to meet you.
大卫·马兰：很高兴认识你。
Here we go.
好了。
Thank you.
谢谢。
AUDIENCE: Nice to meet you.
观众：很高兴认识你。
[APPLAUSE, CHEERING]
[掌声，欢呼声]
DAVID J. MALAN: So we won't look at the code for that actual game.
大卫·J·马兰：所以我们不会去看那个实际游戏的代码。
It was written by one of your predecessors.
它是由你们的前辈之一编写的。
And you can see it online if you're curious.
如果你好奇的话，你可以在网上看到它。
But you can think about now with our functions, conditionals,
但是现在你可以想想，有了我们的函数、条件语句，
Boolean expressions, loops how you could kind of compose that kind of program.
布尔表达式、循环，你如何才能编写那种程序。
So odds are there was a loop that was just constantly listening
所以很有可能有一个循环，它一直在监听
for that kind of connectivity, or it was one
那种连接，或者它是一个
of those extensions that was waiting for motion to go
那些等待运动的扩展之一
touch one of those sprites.
接触那些精灵之一。
Notice that there's these numbers up here.
注意上面有这些数字。
And we haven't talked about this yet.
我们还没谈过这个。
But just like in math, where you can have variables x, y, and z,
但就像数学中，你可以有变量x、y和z一样，
in programming, you can create variables using other puzzle pieces
在编程中，你可以使用其他拼图块创建变量
in Scratch that just keep track of how many seconds are left,
在Scratch中，这些拼图块只跟踪剩余多少秒，
that keeps track of how many times her head hit one of the moles.
它跟踪她的头击中地鼠的次数。
And so you can implement the mechanics of games using very simple building
因此，你可以使用非常简单的构建块来实现游戏的机制
blocks.
块。
But how do you go about building something
但是，你如何才能构建一些
that's more interesting and interactive like that?
更有趣、更具互动性的东西？
Let me go ahead and bring up, for instance,
让我举个例子，
one of the very first things I wrote years ago
几年前我写的第一件事之一
when I was in graduate school and Scratch had just come out.
当时我在研究生院，Scratch刚问世。
I was taking a class at MIT's Media Lab.
我在麻省理工学院媒体实验室上了一门课。
And they invited us to beta test-- that is, try out the software before it then
他们邀请我们进行测试版测试，也就是在它成为世界上的一部分之前试用该软件。
became part of the world.
成为世界的一部分。
And the game I made was this one here.
我做的游戏是这个。
Let me find the right version of "Oscartime."
让我找到“奥斯卡时间”的正确版本。
So "Oscartime" is a game that took me tens of hours probably in the end.
所以“奥斯卡时间”是一个游戏，最后可能花了我几十个小时。
It was a little bit addictive, but let me go ahead and full-screen it.
它有点上瘾，但让我全屏显示它。
And I won't play the whole game.
我不会玩整个游戏。
But it looked a little something like this.
但它看起来有点像这样。
OSCAR: (SINGS) Oh, I love--
奥斯卡：（唱歌）哦，我爱——
DAVID J. MALAN: Where trash is falling from the sky.
大卫·J·马兰：哪里垃圾从天而降。
And I can click on it and drag it.
我可以点击它并拖动它。
And notice as I get close, the lid opens up like this.
注意，当我靠近时，盖子像这样打开。
And if I let it keep falling, it goes in, and Oscar gives me a point.
如果我让它继续掉下去，它就会进去，奥斯卡会给我一分。
And I can do this again.
我可以再做一次。
OSCAR: If you really want to see something trashy--
奥斯卡：如果你真的想看点垃圾——
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
大卫·J·马兰：好吧。
Here comes something else.
来了别的。
OSCAR: I have here a sneaker that--
奥斯卡：我这里有一双运动鞋——
DAVID J. MALAN: So now there's two pieces of trash.
大卫·J·马兰：所以现在有两块垃圾。
OSCAR: It's all full of holes, and the laces are--
奥斯卡：它到处都是洞，鞋带——
DAVID J. MALAN: And it just keeps going, and going, and going.
大卫·J·马兰：它一直在不停地下去，下去，下去。
And if we can lower the volume for just a moment, we'll let more trash fall.
如果我们能把音量调低一下，我们会让更多的垃圾掉下来。
But to your comment earlier about one sprite or more
但回到你之前关于一个精灵或多个精灵的评论
sprites, that's what we're seeing here.
精灵，这就是我们在这里看到的。
Even though our examples thus far are just one cat, one or two puzzle
尽管我们到目前为止的例子只是一只猫，一个或两个拼图
pieces, or a few puzzle pieces.
块，或几个拼图块。
Here is, I claim, a sprite.
这是一个精灵。
Here is another sprite.
这是另一个精灵。
And by toggling among them in that bottom right-hand corner,
通过在右下角切换它们，
I can just associate different puzzle pieces with each of these sprites.
我可以将不同的拼图块与这些精灵中的每一个关联起来。
Now, I didn't start off by implementing this whole game.
现在，我并没有一开始就实现整个游戏。
And in just a moment, if we can raise the volume a little bit,
再过一会儿，如果我们能把音量调高一点，
we'll see even more trash is falling.
我们会看到更多垃圾掉下来。
So this is what--
所以这是——
I hate this song now, like 10 plus hours listening to this song on loop
我现在讨厌这首歌，就像循环播放这首歌十多个小时一样。
just to get the timing right.
仅仅是为了让时间安排得当。
But it brings to life all of these different sprites.
但这赋予了所有这些不同的精灵生命。
And if you play it again and again, it's always a little bit different
如果你一遍又一遍地播放它，它总会有所不同
because I'm using some randomness.
因为我用了一些随机性。
So this newspaper doesn't always fall from there.
所以这份报纸并不总是从那里掉下来的。
Sometimes it's here.
有时它在这里。
And so here, again, we have mechanics of a game where
因此在这里，我们再次看到了游戏机制，即
things are being perturbed a little, randomized a little bit
事物会稍微受到扰动，稍微随机化
to keep things more interesting.
让事情更有趣。
And let me go ahead.
让我继续。
OSCAR: (SINGS) I love trash.
奥斯卡：（唱歌）我爱垃圾。
DAVID J. MALAN: There we go.
大卫·J·马兰：好了。
How. about raise a little volume?
怎么样？稍微提高一下音量？
One more piece of trash.
再加一个垃圾。
So a clock.
所以是一个时钟。
It just goes on forever, this kind of game.
这种游戏会永远持续下去。
But let's go ahead and consider.
但让我们继续考虑。
Let me close that.
让我关闭它。
Let me go ahead and consider.
让我继续考虑。
How I went about implementing that from the get-go.
我从一开始是如何实现它的。
So I will stipulate--
所以我要说明——
let me open a few of these versions here-- that the very first thing I did
让我在这里打开其中几个版本——我做的第一件事
was pretty much just implement the stage.
几乎就是实现舞台。
Right?
对吧？
I was kind of procrastinating, so I poked around.
我有点拖延，所以我四处查看。
I found the Sesame Street lamppost, and I dragged it into the world.
我找到了芝麻街的路灯，然后把它拖进了世界。
And done.
然后就完成了。
Version one is done.
第一个版本完成了。
It didn't do anything, but at least I had the world sort of laid out.
它什么也没做，但我至少把世界大致布局好了。
That is to say I took a baby step toward my goal.
也就是说，我朝着我的目标迈出了一小步。
Then I started thinking about, all right,
然后我开始思考，好吧，
how do I bring the trash to life, even if it doesn't do much of anything else?
我如何让垃圾活起来，即使它什么也没做？
And so I created another sprite by clicking the appropriate button
所以我通过点击右下角的相应按钮创建了另一个精灵
in that bottom right-hand corner.
在右下角。
And I thought about, well, what do I want this trash to do?
我思考着，嗯，我想让这个垃圾做什么？
I want it to just kind of fall from the sky.
我想让它从天空中掉下来。
And so what I did here was the following.
所以我在这里做的是以下事情。
If I go to this trash piece here or-- actually, sorry.
如果我去这个垃圾块这里，或者——实际上，抱歉。
Out of order.
顺序错了。
What I actually did first was I didn't even have the trash fall.
我实际上最开始没有让垃圾掉下来。
If I play this game, the trash just stays there in the air.
如果我玩这个游戏，垃圾就停留在空中。
But I can do this.
但我可以这样做。
I can drag it, and as before, as I touch the other sprite,
我可以拖动它，和之前一样，当我触碰另一个精灵时，
I get the trash can lid to go up.
我让垃圾桶盖子向上翻。
So how do I do that?
那我怎么做呢？
Well, let me click on Oscar down there, my first sprite.
好吧，让我点击下面的奥斯卡，我的第一个精灵。
And here are the puzzle pieces via which I implemented this idea.
这是我实现这个想法的拼图碎片。
I changed Oscar's costume, his appearance,
我改变了奥斯卡的服装，他的外貌，
to be just number one, which was one of the images I imported into the program.
仅仅是数字一，这是我导入程序的一张图片。
And then I forever did this.
然后我永远做这样的事情。
If Oscar is touching the mouse pointer, then
如果奥斯卡触碰了鼠标指针，那么
change Oscar's costume to number two, otherwise change it back to one.
将奥斯卡的服装改为数字二，否则恢复为数字一。
So it's super simple animation.
所以这是一个超级简单的动画。
I'm just toggling between lid up, lid down, lid up, lid down,
我只是在盖子向上、盖子向下、盖子向上、盖子向下之间切换，
but it kind of feels interactive.
但它感觉有点互动。
And if I wanted to really make this pretty,
如果我真的想让它变得漂亮，
I could have 30 different costumes where the lid is ever so slightly higher.
我可以有30种不同的服装，让盖子稍微高一点。
Then it would look even more like a movie or fluid motion.
然后它看起来会更像电影或流畅的运动。
But this was enough to get the job done, which
但这已经足够完成工作了，这
is to say I didn't try to implement all of "Oscartime" together.
也就是说，我没有尝试将所有“奥斯卡时间”都一起实现。
I just took a second baby step toward my goal.
我只是朝着我的目标迈出了第二小步。
And then my next version of "Oscartime" might
然后我的下一个“奥斯卡时间”版本可能会
have looked a little something like this, where now the trash--
看起来有点像这样，现在垃圾——
there's more going on here.
这里还有更多事情发生。
Let's look at two of these blocks of code.
让我们看看这两个代码块。
The first thing I did was I enabled drag mode to draggable,
我做的第一件事是将拖动模式设置为可拖动，
and I had to Google to figure this out because otherwise it
我不得不谷歌搜索来弄清楚这一点，因为否则它
didn't let me drag the trash while playing the game.
不让我在玩游戏时拖动垃圾。
But once I figured that out, I tell the trash
但一旦我弄清楚了，我告诉垃圾
to go to a random x-coordinate between 0 and 240
到 0 到 240 之间的随机 x 坐标
from left to right and then the y location 180
从左到右，然后是 y 位置 180
because I always want the trash falling from the sky.
因为我总是希望垃圾从天而降。
And then what do I do?
然后我该怎么办？
I told the trash to forever change its y-coordinate, its vertical coordinate,
我告诉垃圾永远改变它的 y 坐标，它的垂直坐标，
by negative 1, negative 1, negative 1, one pixel
每次负 1，负 1，负 1，一个像素
at a time, which creates the illusion of it falling from the sky.
一次一个，这创造了它从天而降的错觉。
But I needed to do one other thing, and let me scroll up.
但我还需要做另一件事，让我向上滚动。
Each of your sprites can have multiple programs, multiple scripts,
你的每个精灵都可以有多个程序，多个脚本，
so to speak, that are not attached to one another.
可以这么说，它们彼此之间没有关联。
They will happen in parallel for you.
它们会并行发生。
The second one is saying this.
第二个正在说这个。
Forever if the trash is touching Oscar, what should it do?
如果垃圾碰到奥斯卡，它应该做什么？
Go to a completely different x and y location at the very top.
移动到最顶部的完全不同的 x 和 y 位置。
Why?
为什么？
Well, as soon as I drag the trash over the Oscar,
好吧，一旦我将垃圾拖到奥斯卡上面，
I want it to disappear as though it's going into the can.
我希望它消失，好像掉进了垃圾桶里。
And I then want it to reappear at the top so more trash falls.
然后我希望它重新出现在顶部，这样更多的垃圾就会掉下来。
So I just thought about what would it mean
所以我只是考虑了一下这意味着什么
for the trash to go into the trash can.
对于垃圾进入垃圾桶。
Well, who cares?
好吧，谁在乎呢？
What really matters to the human user is that it just
对人类用户来说真正重要的是它只是
disappears and teleports elsewhere.
消失并传送到其他地方。
And so that's the idea I implemented here.
这就是我在此实施的想法。
So if you can reduce intuitive ideas to just basic building blocks like this,
因此，如果您能将直观的思想简化为像这样的基本构建块，
you can start to make things much more interactive.
您就可以开始使事物变得更加互动。
And lastly, if I look at this version here,
最后，如果我看看这里的这个版本，
you'll see that we've combined these.
你会看到我们已经将它们结合在一起了。
And so indeed, if I actually go ahead and play this now,
所以确实，如果我现在开始播放它，
not only is it falling.
它不仅在下落。
I can let it fall right on top of Oscar and watch it disappear.
我可以让它掉在奥斯卡的上面，然后看着它消失。
But notice Oscar doesn't pop out yet because that was the fourth version
但请注意奥斯卡还没有弹出来，因为那是第四个版本
and then the fifth version.
然后是第五个版本。
And then I added the annoying music and so forth but sort of
然后我添加了恼人的音乐等等，但有点
composed this program step by step by step
一步一步一步地编写了这个程序
so as to accomplish my larger goal.
以便实现我的更大目标。
And this is going to be true of all of the code you write,
这将适用于你编写的所有代码，
be it in Scratch, or C, or Python, or in the like, trying to come up with--
无论是在 Scratch、C、Python 还是类似的语言中，尝试想出——
or rather, trying to reduce your ideas, your grand vision to just baby steps,
或者说，尝试将你的想法、你的宏伟愿景缩减到只是小步骤，
building blocks so that you start with version one,
构建块，以便从第一个版本开始，
and maybe you submit version 10 or 20.
也许你会提交第 10 版或第 20 版。
But you don't try to implement version 10 or 20 at the get-go.
但你不会一开始就试图实现第 10 版或第 20 版。
You take those incremental steps.
你采取这些渐进的步骤。
All right.
好的。
How about one other?
还有别的吗？
Well, let me propose this.
好吧，让我提议这个。
Let me go ahead and open three games that represent one
让我打开三个游戏，它们代表一个
that your predecessors also implemented, which looks a little something
你的前辈也实施过的游戏，它看起来有点像
like this in version zero.
这样，在第零版。
Suppose I wanted to implement a game that
假设我想实现一个游戏，它
simply has these kinds of mechanics.
只包含这些类型的机制。
I'm touching my arrow keys on my keyboard-- up, down, left, and right.
我正在按键盘上的箭头键——向上、向下、向左和向右。
And I'm moving the Harvard logo.
我正在移动哈佛的标志。
Let me zoom in a bit.
让我放大一点。
So if I hit the up arrow, the Harvard shield goes up.
所以如果我按下向上箭头，哈佛盾牌就会上升。
If I hit the down arrow, the shield goes down.
如果我按下向下箭头，盾牌就会下降。
If I go all the way to the left, it goes left
如果我向左移动到底，它就会向左移动
until it hits the wall and same thing on the right.
直到它碰到墙，右边也是一样。
So this is like the beginnings of a game or a beginning
所以这就像一个游戏的开始，或者一个
of a maze, something like that.
迷宫的开始，类似这样的东西。
Well, how might I implement this?
那么，我该如何实现呢？
Well, let me look inside this one.
好吧，让我看看这个内部。
And there's a lot going on, but, again, I sort of took simple steps.
这里有很多事情发生，但，同样，我采取了一些简单的步骤。
Notice that I've got three sprites--
注意我这里有三个精灵--
a left wall, which is just a straight line,
左边的墙，只是一条直线，
the right wall, which is a straight line.
右边的墙，也是一条直线。
And just intuitively, why did I implement those as sprites?
直觉上，为什么我将它们实现为精灵？
Why do they need to exist as entities themselves?
为什么它们需要作为独立的实体存在？
Yeah, in front.
是的，在前面。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众： [听不清]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
大卫·J·马兰： 是的。
I want it to interact with the shield.
我想要它与盾牌互动。
So I need to be able to ask that Boolean expression, like,
所以我需要能够询问那个布尔表达式，比如，
not touching mouse pointer but touching shield, for instance,
没有接触鼠标指针，但接触了盾牌，例如，
a different type of yes/no question.
一种不同的“是/否”问题。
And so what is the code for the shield actually doing?
那么盾牌的代码实际上在做什么呢？
Well, there's a lot of duplication, and let me focus on the abstraction first.
好吧，这里有很多重复代码，让我先关注抽象部分。
Notice that I've got this one green flag clicked.
注意我这里有一个绿色的旗帜被点击了。
I want the shield to go dead center, 0 comma 0,
我想要盾牌位于正中心，0,0，
and then forever listen for the human's keyboard, and feel for the wall.
然后一直监听人类的键盘输入，并感知墙壁。
So I decided to implement my own pink puzzle pieces that
所以我决定实现我自己的粉色拼图，它们
implement the two separate ideas.
实现这两个独立的想法。
One, just listen for the keyboard-- up, down, left,
第一个，就是监听键盘输入--上，下，左，
right-- and then do something.
右--然后执行一些操作。
And then feel for walls is this idea of whenever I go up,
然后感知墙壁就是这个想法，无论何时我向上移动，
down, left, or right, if I touch a wall, I
向下，向左，或向右，如果我碰到了墙，我
need to stop doing whatever the keystrokes are telling me to do.
需要停止执行键盘输入告诉我的任何操作。
So now if we dive into those implementation details, listen and feel
所以现在如果我们深入那些实现细节，监听和感知
are abstractions, custom puzzle pieces.
都是抽象，自定义的拼图。
Let's look at the implementation details.
让我们看看实现细节。
Well, here's the keyboard.
好吧，这是键盘部分。
If the key arrow up is pressed, change y by 1.
如果按下向上箭头键，将 y 改变为 1。
If key down arrow is pressed, change y by negative 1.
如果按下向下箭头键，将 y 改变为 -1。
And you can probably see where this is going.
你可能已经猜到下一步要做什么了。
Right arrow is x by 1.
右箭头是 x 加 1。
Left arrow is x by negative 1, and that's
左箭头是 x 减 1，这就是
sort of all that's involved with up, down, left, right.
与上、下、左、右相关的全部内容。
But wait a minute.
等等。
Why is there no loop in this listen for keyboard puzzle piece?
为什么这个监听键盘的拼图中没有循环呢？
I needed a loop last time so it constantly works.
上一次我需要一个循环，这样它才能一直工作。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
大卫·J·马兰： 没错。
I put the loop in my main part of my program
我把循环放在程序的主要部分
up top so something is telling me to keep listening again and again.
顶部，所以总是有东西在告诉我不断监听。
So it's got to be somewhere, but it doesn't have
所以它一定在某个地方，但它并不需要
to be in the actual implementation.
出现在实际的实现中。
And lastly, how about this feel for walls?
最后，这个感知墙壁的部分怎么样？
Well, if touching left wall, which is just another sprite, change x by 1.
好吧，如果接触到左边的墙，它只是一个精灵，将 x 改变为 1。
So that is to say if I'm touching the left wall,
也就是说，如果我接触到左边的墙，
I want to bounce it back the other direction
我想要让它弹回另一个方向
and same thing on the right wall.
右边的墙也是一样。
If I'm touching the right wall, I want to bounce it
如果我接触到右边的墙，我想要让它
back to the left, which effectively means that even if the human's hitting
弹回左边，这实际上意味着，即使人类按下了
the key, it's like fighting with this code,
按键，这就像在与这段代码抗争，
but it's never going to go through the wall based on that math.
但是基于这样的数学计算，它永远不可能穿墙而过。
It's going to stop it right there.
它会停在那里。
All right.
好的。
Let's add something else to the mix.
让我们再加入一些东西。
Suppose I want the game to change to be a little something like this,
假设我想让游戏变得有点像这样，
where Yale is some kind of block in between me and the exit.
耶鲁大学就像一个阻挡我通往出口的障碍。
So some dramatic race here.
这里是一场戏剧性的赛跑。
OK.
好的。
I just got by, but the Yale logo doesn't seem
我刚跑过去，但是耶鲁大学的标志似乎
to be doing all that much except bouncing.
除了弹跳之外并没有做太多的事情。
So I'm guessing there's a loop, maybe a conditional checking for those walls
所以我想这应该有一个循环，也许是一个判断这些墙的条件
too.
也是。
So let's go ahead and zoom out, see inside.
所以让我们放大，看看内部。
Let's not worry about Harvard because it's pretty much the same.
别担心哈佛，它基本上是一样的。
Let's look at the Yale puzzle pieces.
让我们看看耶鲁大学的拼图块。
And sure enough, go to the middle.
确实，去中间。
0 comma zero.
0，0。
Point in direction 90, so point horizontally on the grid.
指向90度方向，所以在网格上水平指向。
And then if touching left wall or touching right wall--
然后，如果碰到左墙或碰到右墙——
I'm kind of cheating this time, but cleverly, just spin around and do 180
这次我有点作弊，但很聪明，只需旋转并进行180度旋转
so you effectively bounce off the wall.
这样你就能有效地从墙上弹回来。
This just tightened up my code.
这只是优化了我的代码。
I don't need to do the negative 1 or the plus 1.
我不需要进行负1或加1的操作。
I just say bounce in this form of code, otherwise just
我只需在这种代码形式中说弹跳，否则就
constantly move one step.
不断地移动一步。
Now, if this is a game where Yale is supposed to be better and faster,
现在，如果这是一款耶鲁大学应该更快更强的游戏，
well, let's change the 1 to 5.
好吧，让我们把1改为5。
Move 5 pixels at a time.
每次移动5个像素。
Let's move it 10 back and forth.
让我们来回移动10个像素。
Let's maybe 100.
也许100个像素。
Uh-oh.
糟糕。
So what just happened?
发生了什么？
That is a bug, which we can avoid by just not doing that.
这是一个bug，我们可以通过不做那样来避免。
But why did it break out of the wall?
但为什么它会突破墙壁呢？
Yeah.
是啊。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
观众：[听不清]
At first it was [INAUDIBLE].
一开始是[听不清]。
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
大卫·J·马兰：没错。
Because I'm doing 100 steps at a time, I'm
因为我每次移动100个像素，所以
never actually touching the other sprite because I'm
实际上从来没有触碰到另一个精灵，因为
sort of stepping way over it.
我是在跨过它。
So there's never a moment where they're actually touching.
所以它们实际上从来没有真正接触过。
So previously, I was just getting lucky by doing fewer steps because it's
所以之前，我仅仅因为移动的步数比较少而幸运地避免了这种情况，因为
gradually going over the wall, which gives me
它逐渐地越过墙，这给了我
just enough time to detect as much.
足够的时间来检测。
So I would have to kind of tinker, and he'll
所以我要进行一些调整，他也会
handle this a little bit differently.
以不同的方式处理这个问题。
So it's a bug if it's too fast.
所以，如果速度过快，就会出现bug。
But at least if I keep it slow and reasonable
但至少，如果我保持速度缓慢且合理，
the math actually does work out, so long as it starts again in the middle.
数学计算实际上是有效的，只要它从中间重新开始。
Well, let's do one final flourish here, whereby let's bring MIT into the mix.
好吧，让我们在这里做最后一次修饰，把麻省理工学院加入进来。
Right?
对吧？
They're super smart, so maybe they can kind of
他们非常聪明，所以也许他们可以
track us and follow wherever I'm going.
追踪我们，并跟随我的脚步。
So how might this work?
所以这要如何实现呢？
All right.
好的。
So nothing happens yet because we haven't finished composing the game.
所以现在还没有发生任何事情，因为我们还没有完成游戏的设计。
And notice here--
注意这里——
OK.
好的。
Now MIT is struggling.
现在麻省理工学院正在挣扎。
It's kind of twitching there because it's going just above, and below,
它在那里有点抽搐，因为它正在上下移动，
and then above, and below.
然后又上下移动。
So we could fix that too if we want.
所以我们也可以修复它，如果我们想要的话。
But that's just a function of my math, one pixel at a time.
但这仅仅是我的数学计算的结果，一次移动一个像素。
Let me open up this one, see inside, and click on MIT.
让我打开这个，看看内部，然后点击麻省理工学院。
And it doesn't take much to implement MIT, it seems.
而且似乎实现麻省理工学院并不需要太多东西。
So go to random position, forever point towards the Harvard logo outline,
所以随机移动，永远指向哈佛标志的轮廓，
AKA the shield, and then move one step.
也就是盾牌，然后移动一步。
So if I wanted to make MIT even smarter, even faster, what do I change here?
所以如果我想让麻省理工学院变得更聪明、更快，我应该在这里改变什么？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
大卫·马兰：对。
Change one step to two steps to double their speed or five steps, 10 steps,
把一步改为两步，使他们速度翻倍，或者五步、十步，
or 100 steps.
或者一百步。
And the game is going to be over like that.
这样一来，游戏就结束了。
But that's all it takes to now make these kinds of elements.
但这就是现在制作这些元素所需的全部。
So if you are a game player on your phone, or consoles,
所以如果你是在手机、游戏机上玩游戏，
or computer, or whatever, if you think about almost any game,
或者电脑，或者任何东西，如果你考虑几乎所有游戏，
you can probably now start to think about how they implemented
你可能现在就开始思考它们是如何实现的
those mechanics because it's just being reduced to functions, conditionals,
这些机制，因为它们只是被简化为函数、条件语句，
loops, variables, and the like in this case.
循环、变量等等，在本例中就是如此。
So let's go ahead here and have maybe one final volunteer.
所以我们来这里再找一个志愿者。
We've got one more bag of Oreos here.
这里还有一袋奥利奥饼干。
OK.
好的。
That was super fast.
那真的很快。
Do you want to come on up?
你想上来吗？
All right.
好的。
Brave volunteer.
勇敢的志愿者。
Come on up.
上来吧。
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
All right.
好的。
Let me find the full-fledged version of this that one of your predecessors
让我找找之前有人做的完整版。
made.
制作的。
And let me get the right one.
让我找到正确的那个。
OK.
好的。
Here we go.
我们开始了。
We'll see some instructions on the screen in just a moment.
过一会儿，你就会在屏幕上看到一些指令。
And when we hit Play, you'll see that the mechanics are all combined now
当我们点击播放时，你会看到所有的机制现在都结合在一起了
into one full-fledged game.
形成了一个完整的游戏。
But first, an introduction.
但首先，介绍一下。
It's on.
开始了。
SAM: Hi, everyone.
萨姆：大家好。
I'm Sam.
我是萨姆。
I live in [INAUDIBLE].
我住在[听不清]。
I'm a freshman, and I'm from Nepal.
我是一名大一新生，来自尼泊尔。
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
大卫·马兰：好的。
Welcome to the stage.
欢迎上台。
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
SAM: Thank you.
萨姆：谢谢。
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
大卫·马兰：好的。
So here we go.
我们开始了。
Yep.
是的。
Go ahead and click the green flag.
点击绿色的旗子。
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[音乐播放]
[MC HAMMER, "U CAN'T TOUCH THIS"] You can't touch this.
[MC 哈默，“你不能碰我”]你不能碰我。
DAVID J. MALAN: You see the grid is just bigger this time.
大卫·马兰：你看，这次的网格更大。
(SINGING) You can't touch this.
（演唱）你不能碰我。
DAVID J. MALAN: Nice.
大卫·马兰：不错。
Now there's that Yale element.
现在出现了耶鲁元素。
(SINGING) You can't touch this.
（演唱）你不能碰我。
My, my, my my music hits me so hard.
我的，我的，我的音乐击中了我，如此强烈。
Makes me say, oh, my Lord.
让我说，哦，我的上帝。
Thank you for blessing me with a mind to rhyme and two hyped feet.
感谢你赐予我一个充满韵律的思维和两条充满激情的双脚。
It feels good when you know you're down, a super dope homeboy from the Oaktown.
当你明白自己身处低谷时，感觉很好，一个来自奥克兰的超级酷的兄弟。
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
大卫·马兰：好的。
Third Yale.
第三个耶鲁。
All started at slightly different positions.
所有都从略微不同的位置开始。
(SINGING) I told you, homeboy.
（演唱）我告诉过你，兄弟。
You can't touch this.
你不能碰我。
DAVID J. MALAN: Nice.
大卫·马兰：不错。
All right.
好的。
There's MIT.
那是麻省理工学院。
(SINGING) And ya know you can't touch this.
（演唱）你知道你不能碰我。
[CHEERING, APPLAUSE]
[欢呼声，掌声]
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh.
大卫·马兰：哦。
(SINGING) You can't touch this.
（演唱）你不能碰我。
Yo.
哟。
Let me bust the funky lyrics.
让我来唱出这些funky歌词。
DAVID J. MALAN: Gotta go fast.
大卫·马兰：必须快。
Oh.
哦。
No.
不。
Oh.
哦。
[CHUCKLES]
[轻笑]
(SINGING) Cold on a mission, so fall on back.
（唱歌）冷酷的任务，所以后退。
Let them know that you're too much, and this is a beat they can't touch.
让他们知道你太棒了，这是一首他们无法触及的节奏。
DAVID J. MALAN: Nice.
大卫·马兰：不错。
[EXCLAIMING]
[惊呼]
(SINGING) You can't touch this.
（唱歌）你无法触及这。
DAVID J. MALAN: No more walls but two MITs.
大卫·马兰：除了两所麻省理工学院，再无其他障碍。
(SINGING) Yo, sound the bell.
（唱歌）来吧，敲响钟声。
School's in, sucker.
上课了，小子。
DAVID J. MALAN: Princeton now.
大卫·马兰：现在是普林斯顿。
(SINGING) Give me a song or rhythm.
（唱歌）给我一首歌或一首节奏。
Making them sweat, that's what I'm giving them.
让他们流汗，这就是我要给予他们的。
Now, they know you talk about the Hammer when you're talkin'
现在，他们知道当你谈论锤子的时候，
'bout a show that's hyped and tight.
是在谈论一个炒作且精彩的表演。
Singers are sweatin', so pass them a wipe or a tape to learn.
歌手们正在流汗，所以给他们一块毛巾或一张磁带去学习。
DAVID J. MALAN: Second to last level.
大卫·马兰：倒数第二级。
(SINGING) The chart's legit.
（唱歌）排行榜是合法的。
Either work hard, or you might as well quit.
要么努力工作，要么干脆放弃。
That's word because you know you can't touch this.
这是事实，因为你知道你无法触及这。
You can't touch this.
你无法触及这。
Break it down.
分解它。
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
大卫·马兰：好的。
Clear.
明白了。
There we go.
就这样。
Nice.
不错。
Oh, oh.
哦，哦。
Oh.
哦。
Few more lives.
还剩几条命。
Oh.
哦。
(SINGING) Stop.
（唱歌）停。
Hammer time.
锤子时间。
DAVID J. MALAN: Here we go.
大卫·马兰：开始了。
There we go.
就这样。
[EXCLAIMING]
[惊呼]
All right.
好的。
Couple more tries.
再试几次。
Yes!
是的！
Oh, no.
哦，不。
(SINGING) This is it for a winner.
（唱歌）对于赢家来说，这就是最终目标。
Dance to this, and you're gonna get thinner.
跳这支舞，你就会变瘦。
Now move, slide your rump.
现在动起来，摇摆你的屁股。
DAVID J. MALAN: Starts getting stressful.
大卫·马兰：开始变得有压力了。
(SINGING) Just for a minute, let's all do the bump.
（唱歌）只有一分钟，我们一起做一下“碰碰”。
Bump, bump, bump.
碰碰碰。
Yeah.
是啊。
You can't touch this.
你无法触及这。
Look, man.
听着，哥们。
You can't touch this.
你无法触及这。
You'll probably get hyped, boy.
你可能会变得兴奋，小子。
DAVID J. MALAN: One more try.
大卫·马兰：再试一次。
(SINGING) You can't touch this.
（唱歌）你无法触及这。
Ring the bell.
敲响钟声。
School's back in.
上课了。
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
大卫·马兰：好的。
A round of applause, nonetheless.
无论如何，掌声响起。
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
Nicely done.
做得很好。
Thank you.
谢谢。
So as you might have noticed if your eyes started
所以，如果你注意到你的眼睛开始
to wander to the light bulbs here, there's
飘向这里的光源，这里
actually 64 of these light bulbs.
实际上有 64 个这样的灯泡。
And I'm wondering if you divide 64 by 8, that's 8 bytes of light bulbs.
我想知道，如果你把 64 除以 8，那就是 8 字节的灯泡。
And we now have some Unicode in our vocabulary.
我们现在在词汇表中有了 Unicode。
So might very well be the case that we've
所以很可能是，我们一直在
been spelling something out on the stage here for you all of this time.
一直在这里的舞台上拼出一个东西给你们看。
But before we adjourn for cake to be served in the Transept,
但在我们去横厅享用蛋糕之前，
allow me to introduce some of CS50's human friends,
请允许我介绍一些 CS50 的人类朋友，
the Harvard Krokodiloes and the Radcliffe Pitches,
哈佛鳄鱼合唱团和拉德克利夫音调合唱团，
to give us this exciting ending, "This is CS50."
为我们带来这个令人兴奋的结尾，“这就是 CS50”。
[APPLAUSE, CHEERING]
[掌声，欢呼声]
[HARMONICA NOTE]
[口琴声]
[VOCALIZING]
[发声]
SPEAKER: (SINGING) There's a certain someone who I'm indebted to.
演讲者：（唱歌）我欠了某个人情。
And since the old [? BNC ?] has 50, I have this friend for you.
既然旧的[？BNC？]有 50 个，我给你介绍这个朋友。
A two, three, four.
二三，四。
[VOCALIZING]
[发声]
Oh, rubber ducky, you're the one.
哦，小黄鸭，你是我的唯一。
You make [INAUDIBLE] so much fun.
你让[听不清]变得如此有趣。
Rubber ducky, I'm awfully fond of you.
小黄鸭，我非常喜欢你。
[SCATTING] Rubber ducky, you make me smile, and you help my code compile.
[哼唱] 小黄鸭，你让我微笑，你帮助我编译代码。
Rubber ducky, you're my very best friend.
小黄鸭，你是我最好的朋友。
It's true.
是真的。
When I'm at a standstill, your debugging abilities stun me.
当我陷入困境时，你的调试能力让我震惊。
When I'm at the end of my rope, you just snap, and my code's up and running.
当我无计可施时，你只需轻轻一拍，我的代码就恢复正常运行了。
Rubber ducky, you're so fine, and I'm lucky that you're mine.
小黄鸭，你太棒了，我很幸运有你。
Rubber ducky, you're my very best friend.
小黄鸭，你是我最好的朋友。
It's true.
是真的。
You're my best friend.
你是我最好的朋友。
It's true.
是真的。
Rubber ducky, I'm awfully fond of you.
小黄鸭，我非常喜欢你。
[CHEERING, APPLAUSE]
[欢呼声，掌声]
SPEAKER: Good afternoon, CS50.
演讲者：下午好，CS50。
We are the Harvard Krokodiloes, Harvard's oldest a cappella group,
我们是哈佛鳄鱼队，哈佛最古老的无伴奏人声合唱团，
founded way back in 1946 at the historic Hasty Pudding Club.
成立于 1946 年，在历史悠久的哈佛“急急忙忙布丁俱乐部”。
We'd love to make a big thank you to CS50 staff
我们要向 CS50 工作人员表示衷心的感谢
and to David Malan for having us perform here at Sanders Theater.
以及大卫·马兰，感谢他让我们在桑德斯剧院演出。
And you enjoyed this performance, please come audition for us
如果你喜欢我们的演出，请来参加我们的试镜
this weekend at Farkas Hall.
这个周末在法卡斯厅。
[CHEERING, APPLAUSE]
[欢呼声，掌声]
SPEAKER: Hello, everyone.
演讲者：大家好。
We are some of the Radcliffe Pitches, and we are also
我们来自拉德克利夫音调合唱团，我们也
hosting auditions this weekend.
将在这个周末举办试镜。
You can find more information at our Instagram, @radcliffepitches.
你可以在我们的 Instagram 上找到更多信息，@radcliffepitches。
Now, let me tell you a little bit about just about a year ago
现在，让我告诉你一些关于一年前
today, when I was sitting in your very seats on my first day of CS50 lecture.
今天的事情，当时我坐在你们这些座位上，参加我第一次 CS50 讲座。
And this is just about how I was feeling.
这就是我当时的感觉。
[HARMONICA NOTE]
[口琴音符]
[VOCALIZING]
[发声]
(SINGING) It's the first day of class, and I'm brand new to code.
（唱歌）这是第一天上课，我对代码一无所知。
Is this for me?
这适合我吗？
So many people around.
周围有这么多人。
Can I get through the workload?
我能完成工作量吗？
But it's my dream.
但这是我的梦想。
I tend to stick to English, not science.
我倾向于坚持英语，而不是科学。
But my [INAUDIBLE] friends told me to try this.
但我的[听不清]朋友告诉我试试这个。
Hey, dancing robot dog, you kind of look like you have your life together,
嘿，跳舞的机器人狗，你看起来像是过得很不错，
I guess.
我想是的。
I really need some advice.
我真的需要一些建议。
(ALL SINGING) We know you're feeling unsure,
（所有人一起唱）我们知道你感到不确定，
but this is really the right call.
但这确实是正确的选择。
In CS50, you'll meet new friends, get free food.
在 CS50，你会结识新朋友，获得免费食物。
You'll be all set for this fall in CS50.
在 CS50，你会为这个秋季做好准备。
You have a thousand TAs who will help you.
你有一千个助教会帮助你。
You'll get cupcakes, duckies, Chinese food.
你会得到纸杯蛋糕、小黄鸭、中国菜。
And you can always take this class and set aside.
你总是可以修这门课，并留出时间。
SPEAKER: This is CS50.
演讲者：这是 CS50。
Fist bump.
击掌。
[LAUGHTER]
[笑声]
[APPLAUSE, CHEERING]
[掌声，欢呼声]
DAVID J. MALAN: Thank you to the Kroks.
大卫·J·马兰：感谢鳄鱼队。
Thank you to the Pitches.
感谢音调合唱团。
Cake is now served.
现在提供蛋糕。
Come on up to say hi if you'd like or meet Spot.
如果你愿意，可以上来打个招呼，或者见见 Spot。
See you next time.
下次再见。
[APPLAUSE, CHEERING]
[掌声，欢呼声]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[音乐播放]